. >> GOOD AFTERNOON.
WELCOME TO THE AND YOU GUYS PICTURE THAT?
>> YEAH. GOOD AFTERNOON.
WELCOME TO THE SEPTEMBER 15TH 2026 REGULAR MEETING OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE
ROLL. >> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN PRESENT SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN PRESENT
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY PRESENT SUPERVISOR FIELDER
FIELDER PRESENT SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD PRESENT
SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN PRESIDENT MANDOLIN AND PRESENT SUPERVISOR
MELGAR MELGAR PRESENT SUPERVISOR SADR SADR PRESENT
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL PRESENT SUPERVISOR WALTON
WALTON PRESENT AND SUPERVISOR HUANG WONG PRESENT.
MR. PRESIDENT YOU HAVE A QUORUM.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS ACKNOWLEDGES THAT WE ARE ON THE UNCEDED ANCESTRAL
HOMELAND OF THE RAMA TWO ALONE WHO ARE THE ORIGINAL
INHABITANTS OF THE SAN FRANCISCO PENINSULA.
AS THE INDIGENOUS STEWARDS OF THIS LAND AND IN ACCORDANCE
WITH THEIR TRADITIONS THEIR AMATEUR SHALLOWNESS I HAVE
NEVER CEDED LOST NOR FORGOTTEN THEIR RESPONSIBILITIES AS THE
CARETAKERS OF THIS PLACE AS WELL AS FOR ALL PEOPLES WHO
RESIDE IN THEIR TRADITIONAL TERRITORY.
AS GUESTS WE RECOGNIZE THAT WE WE BENEFIT FROM LIVING
AND WORKING ON THEIR TRADITIONAL HOMELAND.
WE WISH TO PAY OUR RESPECTS BY ACKNOWLEDGING THE ANCESTORS,
ELDERS AND RELATIVES OF THE RAMAKRISHNA LEARNING COMMUNITY
AND BY AFFIRMING THEIR SOVEREIGN RIGHTS AS FIRST
PEOPLES. YOU JOIN ME IN RECITING THE
PLEDGE OF ALLEGIANCE. I PLEDGE ALLEGIANCE TO THE FLAG
OF THE UNITED STATES, THE REPUBLIC FOR WHICH IT STANDS
ONE NATION UNDER GOD, INDIVISIBLE WITH LIBERTY
AND JUSTICE FOR ALL. >> ON BEHALF OF THE BOARD I
WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE STAFF AT S.F. GOV TV AND TODAY THAT
IS PARTICULARLY KALEENA MENDOZA.
THEY RECORD EACH OF OUR MEETINGS AND MAKE TRANSCRIPTS
AVAILABLE TO THE PUBLIC ONLINE .
>> AND WITH THAT, MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO OUR 2 P.M. SPECIAL
ORDER. YES, THE SPECIAL ORDER AT 2
P.M. IS THE APPEARANCE BY THE HONORABLE MAYOR DANIEL LURIE.
THERE BEING NO QUESTIONS SUBMITTED FROM ELIGIBLE MEMBERS
REPRESENTING DISTRICTS ONE THROUGH FOUR THE MAYOR MAY
ADDRESS THE BOARD FOR UP TO FIVE MINUTES.
>> WELCOME MR. MAYOR. GOOD AFTERNOON AND BOARD
PRESIDENT MANAGEMENT MEMBERS OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
AS WE SIT HERE TODAY, MANY OF OUR CONSTITUENTS FEEL SAN
FRANCISCO IS FINALLY MOVING IN THE RIGHT DIRECTION.
BUT WHEN SAN FRANCISCANS SIT DOWN AT THE KITCHEN TABLE AT
NIGHT, MANY ARE ASKING IF THEY CAN STILL AFFORD TO LIVE HERE.
RENTS ARE RISING FASTER HERE THAN ANYWHERE ELSE IN THE
COUNTRY. WE'RE ON TRACK FOR THE MOST
EVICTIONS IN NEARLY A DECADE. AND WITH SO FEW HOMES VACANT
AND AVAILABLE FOR RENT, PEOPLE WHO LOSE THEIR HOMES ARE
STRUGGLING TO FIND SOMEWHERE TO GO.
SAN FRANCISCO IS IN A RENT EMERGENCY.
AND I WANT TO SAY HOW GRATEFUL I AM FOR YOUR PARTNERSHIP
IN COMING TOGETHER TO MEET THIS MOMENT.
>> LAST WEEK MANY OF US WORKED TOGETHER TO DEVELOP A SWEEPING
PACKAGE OF REFORMS AND INVESTMENTS TO GIVE RENTERS
GREATER STABILITY. FIRST WE ARE PROTECTING RENTERS
FROM SUDDEN SPIKES IN HOUSING COSTS.
I WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR DANNY SAUTER FOR HIS LEADERSHIP
IN CAPPING THE IMPACT OF BANKS RENT INCREASES AND CAPITAL
IMPROVEMENTS AND SUPERVISOR MATT DORSEY FOR HIS LEGISLATION
ENSURING THAT EVERY TENANT RECEIVES CLEAR INFORMATION
EVERY YEAR ABOUT PROTECTIONS AND EXPECTED RENT INCREASES.
WE ARE ALSO STRENGTHENING PROTECTIONS AGAINST UNWARRANTED
EVICTION THROUGH LEGISLATION SPONSORED BY SUPERVISOR JACKIE
FIELDER. WE WILL PROTECT RENTERS FROM
LOSING THEIR HOMES IF THEY FALL BEHIND BY LESS THAN ONE MONTH
OF RENT. BUT LET'S BE CLEAR.
PROTECTIONS ON PAPER ONLY MATTER IF PEOPLE CAN USE THEM.
THAT IS WHY THIS YEAR OUR ADMINISTRATION IS INVESTING
MORE THAN $54 MILLION IN RENTAL ASSISTANCE LEGAL DEFENSE
AND EVICTION REPRESENTATION. TODAY I AM INTRODUCING AN
ADDITIONAL $3 MILLION TO EXPAND TENANT RIGHT TO COUNSEL AND IN
PARTNERSHIP WITH CITY ATTORNEY DAVID CHU AN ADDITIONAL $1
MILLION TO LAUNCH A CITYWIDE NO YOUR RIGHTS CAMPAIGN AS WE HELP
PEOPLE STAY IN THEIR HOMES. TODAY WE HAVE TO CONFRONT WHAT
IS DRIVING HOUSING COSTS IN THE FIRST PLACE.
WHEN MORE PEOPLE WANT TO LIVE IN SAN FRANCISCO AND THERE
AREN'T ENOUGH HOMES FOR THEM. RENTS RISE.
THAT IS WHY WE MUST BUILD MORE HOUSING.
LAST YEAR WE WORKED CLOSELY WITH THIS BOARD FOR MONTHS TO
PASS FAMILY ZONING. >> THE FIRST MEANINGFUL UPDATE
IN OUR ZONING MAP SINCE WE DOWNED ZONED 50 YEARS AGO WITH
SUPERVISOR MYRNA MELGAR. WE PUT A MEASURE ON THE BALLOT
TO MORE THAN DOUBLE THE HOUSING TRUST FUND.
SO WE HAVE RESOURCES TO INVEST IN AFFORDABLE HOUSING.
AND THROUGH PERMIT S.F. WE ARE CUTTING THE TIME IT COSTS TO
TAKE IT TAKES TO BUILD AND WE'RE MAKING IT EASIER TO
TURN EMPTY DOWNTOWN OFFICES INTO HOMES WITH MORE THAN 300
UNITS ALREADY IN THE PIPELINE. AND AS OF YESTERDAY 75% OF THE
CITY'S BUILDING PERMITS ARE NOW AVAILABLE ON THE PERMIT SF
PORTAL MAKING IT FASTER AND EASIER TO BUILD NEW HOMES.
>> YET A PARENT WHO GOT HOME LAST NIGHT TO FIND AN EVICTION
NOTICE ON THEIR DOOR CANNOT WAIT FOR THAT HOUSING TO BE
BUILT. >> SO WE ARE GOING TO DO BOTH.
BUILDING MORE HOUSING FOR THE FUTURE AND KEEPING PEOPLE
IN THEIR HOMES TODAY. LASTLY, I AM PROUD TO SHARE
THAT MY OFFICE REACHED EARLY LABOR AGREEMENTS WITH MORE THAN
A DOZEN UNIONS REPRESENTING MORE THAN 80% OF ALL CITY
EMPLOYEES. LAST WEEK.
THIS DEAL PROVIDES A 12% WAGE INCREASE BETWEEN 2027 AND 2031
WITH A GUARANTEE OF NO LAYOFFS FOR PERMANENT CIVIL SERVICE
EMPLOYEES THROUGH JUNE 30TH, 2029.
THIS AGREEMENT HONORS THE WORK OUR CITY EMPLOYEES DO.
IT PROVIDES STABILITY FOR OUR CITY AND RECOGNIZES THE COST OF
LIVING INCREASES AFFECTING SO MANY SAN FRANCISCANS.
I WANT TO THANK THE UNION LEADERS FOR WORKING
CONSTRUCTIVELY WITH US. AND I WANT TO THANK OUR CITY
WORKERS FOR KEEPING SAN FRANCISCO RUNNING EVERY SINGLE
DAY. >> WE STILL HAVE WORK TO DO BUT
THERE IS NO DOUBT NO DOUBT THAT OUR CITY IS MOVING IN THE RIGHT
DIRECTION. THIS IS OUR CHANCE TO BUILD A
RECOVERY THAT IS BROAD BASED AND LASTING A RECOVERY THAT
HELPS SAN FRANCISCANS PUT DOWN ROOTS AND SHARE IN OUR CITY'S
SUCCESS NOT BE DISPLACED BY IT. I LOOK FORWARD TO CONTINUING TO
WORK WITH EACH AND EVERY ONE OF YOU TO MAKE SURE SAN FRANCISCO
IS A CITY WHERE EVERY FAMILY AND COMMUNITY HAS THE
OPPORTUNITY TO THRIVE. >> THANK YOU TO ALL OF YOU
AND TO YOU FOR PRESIDENT. THANK YOU, MR. MAYOR.
COMING UP HERE. >> ALL RIGHT.
>> THE MAD THIS MATTER HAS BEEN DISCUSSED AND IS NOW FILED.
>> AND WITH THAT, MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO BACK TO
COMMUNICATIONS. >> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
THE BOARD WELCOMES YOUR ATTENDANCE IN PERSON.
TO THOSE OF YOU IN THE PUBLIC GALLERY HERE IN ROOM 250 WITHIN
THE BOARD'S LEGISLATIVE CHAMBER WITHIN CITY HALL ON THE SECOND
FLOOR. AND WHEN YOU'RE UNABLE TO BE
HERE, THE PROCEEDINGS ARE AIRING LIVE ON SGV TV'S LOCAL
CABLE CHANNEL OR YOU CAN CATCH THE LIVE STREAM AT S.F. GOV
TV.ORG. IF YOU WOULD LIKE TO SUBMIT
YOUR PUBLIC COMMENT IN WRITING JUST SEND AN EMAIL TO BOSS AT
SELF-GOVERNANCE ORG OR USE THE U.S. POSTAL SERVICE JUST
ADDRESS THE ENVELOPE TO THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
. THE NUMBER ONE DR. CARLETON
CAPITAL B PERIOD GOOD PLACE CITY HALL ROOM 244 SAN
FRANCISCO, CALIFORNIA 94102 IF YOU NEED TO MAKE A REASONABLE
ACCOMMODATION FOR A FUTURE MEETING UNDER THE AMERICANS
WITH DISABILITIES ACT OR TO REQUEST LANGUAGE ASSISTANCE,
JUST CONTACT THE CLERK'S OFFICE AT LEAST TWO BUSINESS DAYS
IN ADVANCE BY CALLING (415) 554-5184.
THANK YOU MEMBERS. >> THAT CONCLUDES MY
COMMUNICATION, MR. PRESIDENT. THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
>> LET'S GO TO APPROVAL OF OUR MEETING MINUTES APPROVAL OF THE
JULY 21ST 2026, THE JULY 28TH 2026 AND SEPTEMBER 1ST 2026
BOARD MEETING MINUTES CAN I HAVE A MOTION TO APPROVE THE
MINUTES AS PRESENTED MOVED BY CHEN SECONDED BY WALTON MADAM
CLERK PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THE MINUTES AS PRESENTED.
SUPERVISOR CHEN HI CHEN I SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI MANDELL
WHEN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SARDAR SARDAR I
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
AND SUPERVISOR WANG HUANG EITHER ARE LEBANESE WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE MINUTES WILL BE APPROVED AFTER PUBLIC COMMENT
AS PRESENTED. >> AND WITH THAT LET'S GO TO
OUR CONSENT AGENDA. >> PLEASE CALL ITEMS ONE
THROUGH 15 TOGETHER ITEMS ONE THROUGH 15 ARE ON CONSENT.
THESE ITEMS ARE CONSIDERED TO BE ROUTINE BUT IF A MEMBER
OBJECTS AN ITEM MAY BE REMOVED AND CONSIDERED SEPARATELY.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEMS ONE THROUGH 15
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR MANDEL MIN MANDEL
MIN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
AND SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I THERE ARE 11 EYES WITHOUT
OBJECTION THESE ORDINANCE ARE PASSED THESE ORDINANCES ARE
PASSED ON FIRST READING AND THE RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO UNFINISHED BUSINESS PLEASE CALL
ITEM NUMBER 16 ITEM 16 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE
PUBLIC WORKS CODE TO ALLOW DEVELOPMENT PROJECTS TO SATISFY
STREET TREE PLANTING REQUIREMENTS THROUGH PAYMENT OF
AN IN LIEU FEE OR TO PROVIDE ALTERNATIVE LANDSCAPING TO
EXEMPT ACCESSORY DWELLING UNITS FROM STREET TREE PLANTING
REQUIREMENTS TO ELIMINATE APPEALS TO THE BOARD OF APPEALS
FOR HAZARDOUS TREE REMOVALS UNDERTAKEN BY THE CITY
DEPARTMENTS AND COMMISSIONS AND TO AMEND THE ADMINISTRATIVE
CODE TO SPECIFY A SEPARATE ACCOUNT WITHIN THE ADOPTED TREE
FUND TO RECEIVE AND IN LIEU FEES FOR STREET TREE
REQUIREMENTS TO AMEND THE PLANNING CODE TO UPDATE STREET
TREE APPLICABILITY REQUIREMENTS TO AMEND THE BUSINESS AND TAX
REGULATIONS CODE TO PRESCRIBE TIMEFRAMES FOR THE HEARING
AND DECISION ON APPEALS OF CERTAIN STREET TREE REMOVALS TO
THE BOARD OF APPEALS AND TO AFFIRM THE SECRET DETERMINATION
AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS PLEASE CALL THE ROLL
ON ITEM 16 SUPERVISOR CHAN CHEN NO SUPERVISOR CHEN ITEM 16 YES
CHEN I SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER NO
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI MAN I
SUPERVISOR MELGAR I MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR NO
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON NO
AND SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I THERE ARE SEVEN EYES AND FOUR
NOS WITH SUPERVISORS CHAN FIELDER SADR AND WALTON VOTING
NO WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS FINAL OVER WELL
WITH OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED AND HELLO
SUPERVISOR MELGAR YOUR YOUR MICROPHONE WAS VERY PRESENT FOR
YOU MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 17 THROUGH 1718 TOGETHER
ITEM 17 AND 18 ARE TWO ORDINANCES THAT PERTAIN TO
CERTIFICATES OF PARTICIPATION FOR THE OPEN SPACE FUND.
ITEM 17 IS AN ORDINANCE TO APPROVE THE ISSUANCE AND SALE
OF COPIES THE CERTIFICATES OF PARTICIPATION IN ONE OR MORE
SERIES ON A TAX EXEMPT AND OR TAXABLE BASIS BY THE CITY
PAYABLE FROM THE BASE RENTAL SECURED BY NET OPEN SPACE FUND
PROPERTY TAX REVENUES OR TO FINANCE OR REFINANCE CERTAIN
PROJECTS IN AN AGGREGATE PRINCIPAL AMOUNT OF 43 MILLION
TO APPROVE THE FORM OF THE PROPERTY LEASE TO AUTHORIZE THE
SALE OF THE CERTIFICATES TO APPROVE THE FORM OF AN OFFICIAL
NOTICE OF SALE AND NOTICE OF INTENTION TO SELL THE
CERTIFICATES TO DIRECT THE PUBLICATION OF THE NOTICE OF
INTENTION TO SELL THE CERTIFICATES TO APPROVE THE
FORM OF THE PURCHASE CONTRACT AND ONE OR MORE INITIAL
PURCHASERS OF THE CERTIFICATES TO APPROVE THE FORM OF AN
OFFICIAL STATEMENT IN PRELIMINARY AND FINAL FORM
TO APPROVE THE FORM OF A CONTINUING DISCLOSURE
CERTIFICATE TO AUTHORIZE PAYMENT OF COSTS OF ISSUANCE
AND TO DECLARE THE CITY'S OFFICIAL INTENT TO REIMBURSE
ITSELF FOR CERTAIN COSTS FROM THE PROCEEDS OF THE
CERTIFICATES AND ITEM 18 THIS ORDINANCE APPROPRIATES THE 43
MILLION IN COPIES SERIES 2026 A FOR THE OPEN SPACE FUND
RECREATION AND PARK PROCEEDS TO THE RECREATION AND PARK
DEPARTMENT FOR FISCAL YEAR 2026 THROUGH 2027 AND TO PLACE THESE
FUNDS ON CONTROLLERS RESERVE PENDING THE RECEIPT OF THE
CERTIFICATES OF PARTICIPATION OF PROCEEDS PLEASE CALL THE
ROLL ON ITEM 17 AND 18 SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN I
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN HI MANDOLIN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I
SUPERVISE FOR SADR SADR EYES SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I AND SUPERVISOR WANG WANG I
THERE ARE 11 EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION THE AUDIENCES ARE
PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEMS 19
THROUGH 22 TOGETHER ITEMS 19 THROUGH 22 ARE THREE
RESOLUTIONS AND ONE ORDINANCE PERTAINING TO AFFORDABLE
HOUSING GENERAL OBLIGATION G.O. BONDS ITEMS 19 THROUGH 21
AUTHORIZE THE ISSUANCE AND SALE OF SERIES 2020 6DE AND F SERIES
AFFORDABLE HOUSING G.O. BONDS TO APPROVE THE FORMS OF THE
OFFICIAL NOTICE OF SALE AND NOTICE OF INTENTION TO SELL
BONDS AND TO DIRECT THE PUBLICATION OF THE NOTICE OF
INTENTION TO SELL BONDS TO APPROVE THE FORM OF THE
PURCHASE CONTRACT TO APPROVE THE FORM OF THE PRELIMINARY
OFFICIAL STATEMENT AND THE EXECUTION OF THE OFFICIAL
STATEMENT RELATING TO THE SALE OF SUCH BONDS AND TO APPROVE
THE FORM OF THE CONTINUING DISCLOSURE CERTIFICATE FOR EACH
RESOLUTION ITEM 19 AUTHORIZES THE ISSUANCE AND SALE OF
APPROXIMATELY 107.5 MILLION IN AGGREGATE PRINCIPAL AMOUNT
ON TAX EXEMPT OR TAXABLE BASES OF CITY AND COUNTY GENERAL
OBLIGATION BONDS FOR SOCIAL BONDS AFFORDABLE HOUSING 2019
SERIES 2026 D ITEM 20 APPROVES A SALE OF 47 MILLION
IN AGGREGATE PRINCIPAL AMOUNT ON A TAX EXEMPT OR TAXABLE
BASIS OF CITY GENERAL OBLIGATION BONDS FOR SOCIAL
BONDS AFFORDABLE HOUSING 2024 SERIES 2026 E ITEM 21 THIS
APPROVES APPROXIMATELY 47.5 MILLION IN AGGREGATE PRINCIPAL
AMOUNT OF TAXABLE GENERAL OBLIGATION BONDS FOR AFFORDABLE
HOUSING 2016 PRESERVATION AND SEISMIC SAFETY SERIES 2026
F AND FOR ITEM 22 THIS ORDINANCE APPROPRIATES
APPROXIMATELY 202 MILLION OF GIO BOND PROCEEDS TO THE
MAYOR'S OFFICE OF HOUSING AND COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT TO
INCLUDE 107.5 OF PROCEEDS FROM SERIES 20 2060 AFFORDABLE
HOUSING GO BONDS FOR MIDDLE INCOME AND SENIOR HOUSING
PROJECTS 47 MILLION OF PROCEEDS FROM SERIES 2026 AFFORDABLE
HOUSING GO BONDS FOR LOW INCOME HOUSING PROJECTS
AND APPROXIMATELY 47.5 FROM SERIES 2026 F PRESERVATION
AND SEISMIC SAFETY GO BONDS TO ACQUIRE, IMPROVE
AND REHABILITATE AND TO CONVERT AT RISK MULTI-UNIT RESIDENTIAL
BUILDINGS TO PERMANENT AFFORDABLE HOUSING IN FISCAL
YEAR 2026 THROUGH 2027 AND TO PLACE THESE FUNDS ON
COMPTROLLERS RESERVE PENDING THE RECEIPT OF THE BOND
PROCEEDS. >> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK.
UNLESS THERE ARE OBJECTIONS WE WILL TAKE THESE ITEMS SAME
HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE
ADOPTED AND THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING PLEASE
CALL ITEMS 23 AND 24 TOGETHER ITEMS 23 AND 24 ARE A
RESOLUTION AND AN ORDINANCE THAT PERTAIN TO HEALTH
AND RECOVERY GENERAL OBLIGATION OR GEO BONDS.
ITEM 23 AUTHORIZES THE ISSUANCE AND SALE OF 83.5 MILLION
IN AGGREGATE PRINCIPAL AMOUNT OF ONE OR MORE SERIES OF BONDS
ON A TAX EXEMPT OR TAXABLE BASIS OF CITY AND COUNTY
GENERAL OBLIGATION BONDS FOR HEALTH AND RECOVERY 2020 SERIES
2026 B TO APPROVE THE FORMS OF THE OFFICIAL NOTICE OF SALE
AND NOTICE OF INTENTION TO SELL BONDS AND TO DIRECT THE
PUBLICATION OF THE NOTICE OF INTENTION TO SELL BONDS TO
APPROVE THE FORM OF THE PURCHASE CONTRACT APPROVE THE
FORM OF THE PRELIMINARY OFFICIAL STATEMENT AND THE
EXECUTION OF THE OFFICIAL STATEMENT RELATING TO THE SALE
OF SUCH BONDS TO APPROVE THE FORM OF THE CONTINUING
DISCLOSURE CERTIFICATE AND FOR ITEM 24 THIS ORDINANCE
APPROPRIATES APPROXIMATELY 43.5 MILLION IN GO BOND PROCEEDS
FROM 2020 HEALTH AND RECOVERY G.O. BONDS SERIES 2025 G FROM
THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH AND APPROPRIATES APPROXIMATELY
83.5 MILLION OF GEO BOND PROCEEDS FROM 2020 HEALTH
AND RECOVERY G.O. BONDS SERIES 2026 B TO THE DEPARTMENT OF
PUBLIC HEALTH AND RECREATION AND PARKS DEPARTMENT IN FISCAL
YEAR 2026 THROUGH 27 AND TOOK PLACE THE APPROXIMATE 83.5
MILLION IN SERIES 26 B PROCEEDS ON CONTROLLERS RESERVE PENDING
RECEIPT OF BOND PROCEEDS AND I THINK WE CAN TAKE THESE ITEMS
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS
ADOPTED IN THE ORDINANCE AS PASSED ON FIRST READING PLEASE
CALL ITEMS 20 FIVE AND 26 TOGETHER ITEMS 25 AND 26 ARE A
RESOLUTION AND AN ORDINANCE THAT PERTAIN TO EARTHQUAKE
SAFETY AND EMERGENCY RESPONSE. ITEM 25 AUTHORIZES THE ISSUANCE
AND SALE OF A 138 MILLION IN AGGREGATE PRINCIPAL AMOUNT
OF CITY AND COUNTY GENERAL OBLIGATION BONDS FOR EARTHQUAKE
SAFETY AND EMERGENCY RESPONSE 2020 SERIES 2026 SEE AND ONE OR
MORE SERIES ON A TAX EXEMPT OR TAXABLE BASIS ITEM 26 THIS
ORDINANCE APPROPRIATES 138 MILLION OF GENERAL OBLIGATION
BOND PROCEEDS FROM 2020 EARTHQUAKE SAFETY AND EMERGENCY
RESPONSE GO BONDS SERIES 20 2062 THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC
WORKS IN FISCAL YEAR 2026 THROUGH 27 AND TO PLACE THESE
FUNDS ON CONTROLLERS RESERVE PENDING RECEIPT OF THE BOND
PROCEEDS. SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED IN THE
AUDIENCE AS PASSED ON FIRST READING PLEASE CALL ITEMS 27
AND 28 TOGETHER ITEMS 27 AND 28 ARE TWO RESOLUTIONS APPROVING
PROFESSIONAL SERVICES AGREEMENTS WITH THE AIRPORT.
ITEM 27 APPROVES THE FIRST MODIFICATION TO THE
PROFESSIONAL SERVICES AGREEMENT FOR AIRPORT CONTRACT NUMBER
12047.41 FOR COMMISSIONING ACTIVATION AND SIMULATION
SUPPORT SERVICES BETWEEN FAITH GROUP PMC AM TO JOINT VENTURE A
JOINT VENTURE BETWEEN FAITH GROUP LLC AND PMC AND TO LLC
AND THE CITY TO INCREASE THE CONTRACT AMOUNT BY 9.5 MILLION
FOR A NEW TOTAL OF 17 MILLION WITH NO CHANGE TO THE CONTRACT
DURATION OF FIVE YEARS FROM JULY 1ST 2024 TO JUNE 30TH 2029
ITEM 28 THIS RESOLUTION APPROVES THE THIRD MODIFICATION
TO THE PROFESSION SERVICES AGREEMENT FOR AIRPORT CONTRACT
NUMBER 12077.41 FOR PROJECT MANAGEMENT SUPPORT SERVICES FOR
THE AIRFIELD IMPROVEMENT PROGRAM 2024 THROUGH 2029 PHASE
FOUR THE SAN FRANCISCO INTERNATIONAL AIRPORT WITH
ADKINS RELEASE USA INC AND THE CITY TO INCREASE THE CONTRACT
BY 8.4 MILLION FOR A NEW TOTAL AMOUNT OF 17 MILLION WITH NO
CHANGE TO THE CONTRACT DURATION OF FOUR YEARS.
FEBRUARY 14TH 2025 TO FEBRUARY 14TH 2020 NINE SAME HOUSE, SAME
CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED.
PLEASE CALL ITEMS 29 THROUGH 31 TOGETHER ITEMS 29 THROUGH 31
PROVIDE RETROACTIVE AUTHORIZATION TO THE DEPARTMENT
OF PUBLIC HEALTH FOR GRANTS ITEM 21 ACCEPTS AND EXPANDS A
GRANT FUNDS FROM THE NATIONAL INSTITUTES OF HEALTH THROUGH
LUNA HEALTH TO PARTICIPATE IN A PROGRAM ENTITLED PREP BROOK
PREP BLUEPRINT EVALUATING IMPLEMENTATION OF A PREP CHOICE
BLUEPRINT ON PREP UPTAKE AND PERSISTENCE A TERM OF EIGHT
MONTHS APRIL 1ST, 2026 THROUGH NOVEMBER 30TH 2026 FOR A TOTAL
AMOUNT OF $148,843. ITEM 30 APPROVES A GRANT
AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE CITY AND THE SAN FRANCISCO GENERAL
HOSPITAL FOUNDATION TO ACCEPT AND EXPEND A $2.3 MILLION GRANT
FROM S.F. G H F FOR PARTICIPATE IN A PROGRAM ENTITLED SOLID
START A THREE YEAR TERM JULY 1ST, 2025 THROUGH JUNE 30TH
2028 AND ITEM 31 TO ACCEPT AND EXPEND AN APPROXIMATE
$204,000 GRANT FROM THE SAN FRANCISCO HEALTH PLAN TO
PARTICIPATE IN A PROGRAM ENTITLED SAN FRANCISCO HEALTH
PLAN COMMUNITY HEALTH ASSESSMENT COMMUNITY HEALTH
IMPROVEMENT PLAN CHP GRANT FOR THE TERM OF JULY FIRST 2025
THROUGH DECEMBER 31ST, 2026. >> LET'S TAKE THESE ITEMS SAME
HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED AND PLEASE CALL ITEMS 32
THROUGH 36 TOGETHER ITEMS 32 THROUGH 36 ARE FIVE RESOLUTIONS
TO PROVIDE RETROACTIVE APPROVAL TO AUTHORIZE THE MAYOR AND
DIRECTOR OF THE MAYOR'S OFFICE OF HOUSING AND COMMUNITY
DEVELOPMENT TO EXECUTE GRANTS WITH THE FOLLOWING ENTITIES.
ITEM 32 IS WITH 163 LINE HOUSING PARTNERS IN AN AMOUNT
OF 2.5 MILLION A 15 YEAR TERM AND SIX MONTHS COMMENCING ON
JULY 1ST 2026 THROUGH DECEMBER 31ST 2042 TO PROVIDE PROJECT
BASED RENTAL SUBSIDIES FOR AN 85 UNIT 100% AFFORDABLE HOUSING
PROJECT EXTREMELY LOW INCOME HOUSEHOLDS AS PART OF THE
AFFORDABLE HOUSING OPPORTUNITY FUND AND PROGRAM ITEM 33 THIS
IS WITH 333300 MISSION PARTNERS LP IN AN AMOUNT OF
APPROXIMATELY 4.4 MILLION FOR A 15 YEAR AND SIX MONTH TERM
THROUGH DECEMBER 31ST 2042 TO PROVIDE PROJECT BASED RENTAL
SUBSIDIES FOR A 35 UNIT 100% AFFORDABLE HOUSING PROJECT FOR
EXTREMELY LOW INCOME HOUSEHOLDS AS PART OF AFFORDABLE HOUSING
OPPORTUNITY FUND AND PROGRAM AND ITEM WELL ITEM 34 WITH THE
AMBASSADOR RATES 4% LP IN AN AMOUNT OF 4.5 MILLION FOR A
TERM OF SIX YEARS AND SIX MONTHS THROUGH JANUARY 1ST 2043
TO PROVIDE PROJECT BASED RENTAL SUBSIDIES FOR A 55 UNIT 100%
AFFORDABLE HOUSING PROJECT HOUSING EXTREMELY LOW INCOME
HOUSEHOLDS FOR ITEM 35 THIS IS WHAT THE 1166 HOWARD STREETS
ASSOCIATES LP FOR 3.2 MILLION FOR A 16 YEAR AND SIX MONTH
TERM TO COMMENCE ON JULY 1ST 2026 THROUGH DECEMBER 31ST 2042
PROVIDING PROJECT BASED RENTAL SUBSIDIES FOR AN 88 UNIT 100%
AFFORDABLE HOUSING PROJECT TO HOUSE EXTREMELY LOW INCOME
HOUSEHOLDS AS PART OF THE AFFORDABLE HOUSING OPPORTUNITY
FUND AND PROGRAM AND FOR ITEM 36 THIS IS WITH MH DC SOUTH
PARK PROPERTIES LP FOR 3.8 MILLION A 16 YEAR AND SIX MONTH
TERM THROUGH DECEMBER 31ST 2043 TO PROVIDE PROJECT BASED RENTAL
SUBSIDIES FOR 160 UNIT 100% AFFORDABLE HOUSING PROJECT TO
HOUSE EXTREMELY LOW INCOME HOUSEHOLDS AS PART OF THE
AFFORDABLE HOUSING OPPORTUNITY FUND AND PROGRAM AND WE CAN
TAKE THESE ITEMS SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED. >> AND WITH THAT, MADAM CLERK,
LET'S GO TO OUR 2:30 P.M. SPECIAL ORDER YES THE 2:30 P.M.
SPECIAL ORDER IS 230 COMMENDATIONS FOR THOSE WHO ARE
IN NEED OF RECOGNITION OF COMMENDATIONS FOR MERITORIOUS
SERVICE TO THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
>> AND WE WILL BEGIN WITH DISTRICT SIX SUPERVISOR DORSEY
THANK YOU PRESIDENT MANDOLIN COLLEAGUES SEPTEMBER IS
NATIONAL RECOVERY MONTH AND TODAY I AM PROUD TO
RECOGNIZE THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH'S LIVING PROOF
S.F. CAMPAIGN TOGETHER WITH THE 11 SAN FRANCISCANS WHO HAVE
SHARED THEIR STORIES OF ADDICTION, TREATMENT
AND RECOVERY WITH OUR CITY SIOBHAN ALLEN, MICHAEL ALVAREZ,
JEAN BRUNO, KEVIN CAMPOS JULIANA COROLLA NUNO ALISSA
IBARRA. JEN JEFFREYS.
DOMINIQUE MCDOWELL. GREGORY MCDOWELL.
ERIKA RAES AND JOEL YATES. CAN YOU COME ON UP TO THE TO
THE LECTERN WILL BE JOINED ALSO BY DAN TSAI.
SO JUST SO SO OVER THERE YOU SEE SO HE IS OVER THERE THIS IS
FINE. SO I WANT TO THANK EACH OF YOU
FOR HELPING MAKE RECOVERY VISIBLE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
I SAY THAT AS SOMEONE WHO'S ALSO IN RECOVERY AND WHO HAS A
VERY PERSONAL CONNECTION TO THIS WORK FOR FAR TOO LONG
ADDICTION HAS BEEN STIGMATIZED. IT IS SOMETHING THAT HAS BEEN
PEOPLE WHO HAVE BEEN EXPECTED TO HIDE AND RECOVERY IS TOO
OFTEN BEEN TREATED THE SAME WAY.
WE NEED TO CHANGE THAT. >> PEOPLE WHO ARE STRUGGLING
NEED TO SEE THAT TREATMENT WORKS AND THAT RECOVERY IS
POSSIBLE AND THAT THERE ARE PEOPLE IN THEIR CITY WHO
UNDERSTAND WHAT THEY'RE GOING THROUGH.
THAT IS WHAT LIVING PROOF DOES SO WELL.
THESE 11 SAN FRANCISCANS MADE THE BRAVE AND INSPIRING
DECISION TO PUT THEIR FACES, THEIR NAMES AND THEIR STORIES
OUT IN THE WORLD AND TO TALK HONESTLY ABOUT SOME OF THE
HARDEST EXPERIENCES IN THEIR LIVES BECAUSE THEY KNEW IT
MIGHT HELP SOMEONE ELSE. THAT TAKES REAL COURAGE.
AND IT ALSO HAS REAL VALUE. STIGMA CONTINUES TO KEEP PEOPLE
FROM SEEKING TREATMENT AND ONE OF THE MOST EFFECTIVE WAYS TO
BREAK THROUGH THAT STIGMA IS FOR PEOPLE IN RECOVERY TO BE
OPEN ABOUT THEIR OWN EXPERIENCES AND TO SHOW OTHERS
THAT THERE IS A REAL PATH FORWARD.
>> I KEEP LIVING PROOF POSTERS ON DISPLAY IN MY CITY HALL
OFFICE BECAUSE IT INSPIRES ME AND BECAUSE I THINK IT IS
IMPORTANT FOR PEOPLE TO SEE RECOVERY REPRESENTED IN THE
PLACE WHERE DECISIONS ABOUT ADDICTION TREATMENT AND PUBLIC
HEALTH ARE BEING MADE EVERY DAY.
RECOVERY BELONGS IN CITY HALL IN OUR NEIGHBORHOODS AND IN THE
BROADER CONVERSATION ABOUT ADDICTION IN SAN FRANCISCO.
EVERY ONE OF THESE INDIVIDUALS HERE IS HELPING CHALLENGE THE
STEREOTYPES THAT STILL SURROUND SUBSTANCE USE DISORDER
AND SHOWING THAT THERE IS NO SINGLE PICTURE OF ADDICTION
JUST THERE IS NO SINGLE PICTURE OF RECOVERY.
SAN FRANCISCO HAS LOST FAR TOO MANY PEOPLE TO ADDICTION
AND OVERDOSE. AND WHILE OVERDOSE DEATHS HAVE
COME DOWN FROM THEIR RECENT HISTORIC HIGHS, WE STILL HAVE A
TREMENDOUS AMOUNT OF WORK AHEAD OF US.
PART OF THAT WORK IS MAKING SURE TREATMENT IS AVAILABLE
WHEN PEOPLE ARE READY FOR IT. BUT ANOTHER PART IS MAKING SURE
PEOPLE BELIEVE THAT TREATMENT CAN WORK.
SOMETIMES THE MOST CONVINCING EVIDENCE IS SIMPLY SEEING
ANOTHER PERSON WHO HAS BEEN THROUGH IT WHO FOUND HELP
AND WHO HAS BUILT A LIFE IN RECOVERY.
>> SINCE LIVING PROOF LAUNCHED IN 2024, THE CAMPAIGN HAS
REACHED MILLIONS OF PEOPLE WITH MESSAGES OF HOPE AND HEALING
AND RECOVERY AND REDEMPTION. THOSE NUMBERS ARE IMPRESSIVE,
BUT WHAT MATTERS MOST IS THE PERSON WHO MAY SEE THOSE
STORIES ON A BUS SHELTER OR ONLINE OR SOMEWHERE IN THEIR
NEIGHBORHOOD. AND TO RECOGNIZE SOMETHING OF
THEMSELVES IN IT. THE PEOPLE PARTICIPATING
IN THIS CAMPAIGN MAY NEVER KNOW WHO DECIDED TO SEEK HELP
BECAUSE OF THEIR STORY BUT KNOW THAT THEY'RE OUT THERE BECAUSE
THAT'S THE KIND OF IMPACT THIS WORK HAS.
SO DURING RECOVERY MONTH I WANT TO THANK THE DEPARTMENT OF
PUBLIC HEALTH FOR CREATING THE LIVING PROOF S.F. CAMPAIGN.
AND SPECIAL THANKS TO SIOBHAN TO MICHAEL JEAN, KEVIN,
JULIANNA, ALYSSA, JEN, DOMINIQUE, GREGORY, ERICA
AND JOEL FOR HAVING THE COURAGE TO BE THE FACES OF IT.
THANK YOU FOR MAKING RECOVERY VISIBLE AND FOR GIVING PEOPLE
HOPE AND FOR REMINDING SAN FRANCISCO THAT TREATMENT WORKS
AND RECOVERY IS POSSIBLE. IT IS MY HONOR TO REPRESENT TO
RECOGNIZE ALL OF YOU TODAY. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH.
BUT WE'LL START WITH DIRECTOR SIMON.
>> WE'VE GOT YOU GUYS ALL RIGHT.
>> YOU GOT IT. OKAY.
I'M DAN. I'M THE HEALTH DIRECTOR HERE
IN SAN FRANCISCO. THANK YOU TO SUPERVISOR DORSEY
AND THE BOARD FOR THIS COMMENDATION.
AND I JUST WANT TO CONGRATULATE AND THANK AND RECOGNIZE THE
INCREDIBLE FOLKS HERE. THEY MAY BE ONE OF THE MOST
WELL KNOWN SETS OF FACES IN SAN FRANCISCO EVERYWHERE.
>> BUS STOPS YOU GO TO CLINICS .
I SEE YOUR FACES EVERYWHERE. AND SOME OF YOU WILL HAVE STOOD
ON THE PODIUM FOR VARIOUS PUBLIC SERVICE ANNOUNCEMENTS OR
OTHER GET OUT THE AWARENESS PIECES WE'VE TRIED TO DO.
AND FROM A PUBLIC HEALTH STANDPOINT, SUPERVISOR DORSEY,
AS YOU'VE NOTED, WE'VE HAD FAR TOO MANY OVERDOSES HERE IN SAN
FRANCISCO. WE HAVE HAD MAJOR PUBLIC HEALTH
CRISES HERE WITH BEHAVIORAL HEALTH, HOMELESSNESS AND THE
INTERSECTION OF THESE PIECES. AND IT'S ALWAYS NICE TO SEE
THAT RECOVERY AND HOPE IS POSSIBLE AND TO SEE FACES LIKE
THIS WHO ARE SHARING THEIR STORIES, IT INSPIRES OTHERS TO
KNOW THAT THERE ARE RESOURCES, THERE'S AND THERE'S HOPE
AND ALSO OUR TEAM AND OUR CLINICIANS AND NON-CLINICAL
STAFF WHO PUT THEIR HEARTS INTO THIS WORK EVERY DAY AND YOU ALL
REMIND CITY STAFF WHY FOLKS DO WHAT THEY DO.
SO I MAINLY WANT TO CONGRATULATE AND THANK FOLKS I
SHOULD NOTE THAT THESE FOLKS WERE NOMINATED TWO TIMES FOR
PUBLIC SERVICE EMMY I'VE NEVER BEEN NOMINATED FOR AN EMMY.
THEY'VE BEEN NOMINATED FOR AN EMMY AND I HAD TO DOUBLE CHECK
THIS FACT BECAUSE I DID NOT BELIEVE IT AT FIRST.
APPARENTLY OVER THE THREE YEARS OF THE CAMPAIGN THERE HAVE BEEN
ROUGHLY 200 MILLION IMPRESSIONS OF THE EITHER VIDEOS OR THE
POSTERS LIKE CLICKS, EYEBALLS, ETC. THAT'S A LOT OF
IMPRESSIONS AND THAT'S A LOT OF IMPACT FOR WHAT WE'RE TRYING TO
DO HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO. >> SO THANK YOU ALL.
AND DOMINIQUE, I'M GOING TO I THINK YOU'RE GOING TO SAY A FEW
THINGS. ALL RIGHT.
MY NAME IS DOMINIQUE AND I'M DEFINITELY A GRATEFUL
RECOVERING PERSON FROM DRUGS. >> WE WANT TO FIRST THANK YOU
ALL FOR SUPPORTING THIS FOR SUPPORTING US IN THIS MISSION
AND IT'S THIS GREAT THING THAT WE'VE WITH WE'VE BEEN ABLE TO
DO WE'VE BEEN ABLE TO TOUCH A LOT OF PEOPLE.
I GET A LOT OF PHONE CALLS FROM FROM PEOPLE LIKE I HAVEN'T
TALKED TO IN YEARS AND EVEN MY DESK MY DAD SO EVEN HELPED
PEOPLE REACH OUT TO HIM LIKE HEY, LET ME GET DOWN, PHONE
HIM. >> I SEE HIM ON A BILLBOARD SO
BUT I'M JUST MORE HUMBLED BY THAT BY THE PROCESS AND IF YOU
LOOK AT US WE ARE WE ARE GAMUT OF PEOPLE WITH A WHOLE
SPECTRUM. SO WE GET WE ARE ABLE TO REACH
ALL THE PEOPLE IN SAN FRANCISCO .
IT'S NOT JUST ONE FACE AND I THINK THAT'S WHAT MADE IT
GREAT. I THINK DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC
HEALTH DONE A GREAT JOB WITH US TO HELP US PUT THIS TOGETHER.
THEY MADE US COMFORTABLE. THEY MADE IT SAFE BECAUSE IT IS
KIND OF SCARY TO PUT YOURSELF OUT THERE.
I DON'T CARE. I DON'T CARE WHO KNOWS YOU KNOW
? BUT I JUST WANT TO SHARE ONE
THING WHICH I BEFORE I GO AND IT'S SOMETHING THAT I STAND
BY IS FOR REASONS PEOPLE CHANGE AND IT STATES THIS IT SAYS
PEOPLE CHANGE WHEN THEY HEARD ENOUGH THAT THEY HAVE TO WHEN
THEY SEEN ENOUGH THEY'RE INSPIRED TO WHEN THEY LEARN
ENOUGH THEY WANT TO AND WHEN THEY RECEIVE ENOUGH THEY'RE
ABLE TO AND WE WERE ALL ABLE TO FIND HOPE, YOU KNOW, IN THE
MIDST OF OUR DARK NIGHTS AND OUR DARK TIMES, YOU KNOW,
THERE'S BEEN SOME VERY DARK DAYS UP HERE.
IF YOU LOOK UP IT'S A LOT OF DARK DAYS AND NOW WE BRING
LIGHT. NOW WE'RE VERY LIGHT.
WE FULL OF HOPE AND WE BRING HOPE TO PEOPLE AND I JUST THANK
YOU THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR LETTING ME BE A
PART OF SUCH A GREAT THING. >> THANK YOU.
I AGAIN THANK YOU SO MUCH. THANK YOU.
ALL RIGHT. NEXT UP DISTRICT TWO SUPERVISOR
CHERYL THANK YOU PRESIDENT OF MANAGEMENT AND COLLEAGUES TODAY
I'M EXTREMELY HONORED TO COMMEND COMMISSIONER PRESIDENT
EXCUSE ME KAT ANDERSON AS WE CELEBRATE OUR 10TH ANNIVERSARY
SERVING THE CITY ON THE REC PARKS COMMISSION AND FOR MORE
THAN THREE DECADES OF LEADERSHIP, VOLUNTEERISM
AND CREATIVE CONTRIBUTION TO SAN FRANCISCO.
>> KAT PLEASE JOIN US UP AT THE PODIUM AND I INVITE MY FAMILY
TO STAND WITH ME. YEAH, GREAT.
YOU GUYS LOOK GREAT. COME ON.
WE'RE MISSING DEE DEE. BUT YOU THREE LOOK GREAT.
>> KAT MOVED TO SAN FRANCISCO IN 1988 CALLING THE MARINA HOME
EVER SINCE AND HER CIVIC ENGAGEMENT BEGAN AT THAT
NEIGHBORHOOD LEVEL SERVING IN LEADERSHIP WITH THE MARINA
COMMUNITY ASSOCIATION AND WRITING FOR THE MARINA
TIMES TO GIVE THAT NEIGHBORHOOD A VOICE.
CAT HAS ALSO DEVOTED HERSELF TO EDUCATION AND PROVIDING
OPPORTUNITY FOR OTHERS ACROSS THE CITY SERVING AS PRESIDENT
OF THE FOUNDATION OF CITY COLLEGE OF SAN FRANCISCO
AND LEADER PHENIX FOUNDING BAY NEWS RISING, A MENTORSHIP
PROGRAM FOR JOURNALISM STUDENTS AT SAN FRANCISCO STATE AND CITY
COLLEGE. AND FOR THE PAST TEN YEARS KAT
HAS SERVED ON THE SAN FRANCISCO RECREATION AND PARKS COMMISSION
INCLUDING AS PRESIDENT GUIDED BY HER BELIEF THAT PARKS ARE
ESSENTIAL CIVIC INFRASTRUCTURE NOT JUST AMENITIES.
SHE'S OVERSEEN A 111 CAPITAL PROJECTS AND PARKS OPENED
DURING HER TIME INCLUDING FRANCISCO PARK AND DISTRICT
TWO. SO I DO SEARCH FOR REC PARKS
NEW GAMES SERVE AS AN ADVISOR TO FLEET WEEK AND IS HERSELF AN
ACTIVE DONOR TO BOTH FLEET WEEK FRANCISCO PARK AND MUCH MORE.
>> BUT OF ALL OF THAT THE THING THAT ALWAYS STICKS OUT TO ME IS
THAT HER FAVORITE PROGRAM IS THE DEPARTMENT'S GARDNER
APPRENTICESHIP PROGRAM WHICH IN PARTNERSHIP IS REC PARK
AND LOCAL 261 HAS FOR NEARLY TWO DECADES TRAINED ASPIRING
GARDENERS AND THE SKILLS NEEDED TO CARE FOR OUR WONDERFUL PARKS
WHILE BUILDING PATHWAYS TO MEANINGFUL CAREER DEVELOPMENT.
>> HER ENTREPRENEURIAL SPIRIT HAS ALSO INFECTED INTO OR
FLOWED SHALL I SAY INTO ALL OF OUR NEIGHBORHOODS.
SHE CO-FOUNDED A RESTAURANT IN THE BAYVIEW DESIGNED AS A
COMMUNITY HUB FOR ARTISTS, MUSICIANS AND CULINARY
CREATORS. SHE RECENTLY DESIGNED ARTWORK
FOR THE AVILA STREET CORRIDOR NEIGHBORHOOD ASSOCIATIONS
UPCOMING BLOCK PARTY FOR THE FLIERS AND THE T-SHIRTS.
THIS DEVOTION TO THE CITY HAS FRANKLY BEEN A NATURAL
EXTENSION OF HER WORK IN LABOR AND EMPLOYMENT LAW TRAINED
RIGHT HERE AT U.C. LAW, SHE SERVED AS INTERIM DIRECTOR OF
THE NEWS UNION PACIFIC MEDIA WORKERS GUILD.
THE SUPPORT OF PEOPLE AT THE BEGINNING OF THEIR CAREERS
IN THE MIDST OF THEIR CAREER IS AT THE TAIL END OF THEIR
CAREERS IS SOMETHING THAT UNDERPIN SO MUCH OF HER WORK
AND CLOSER TO HOME KAT IS THE PROUD MEMBER OF PATRICK WHO IS
JOINING US HERE TODAY AND DEEDEE ANDERSON, BOTH
NATIVE SAN FRANCISCANS WHO SERVE IN THEIR OWN WAYS THIS
CITY THROUGH THEIR WORK AT S.I. AND AT C MARY THE VIRGIN
EPISCOPAL CHURCH AND IS THE PROUD WIFE OF DAVE ANDERSON WHO
HAS SERVED OUR COUNTRY AS THE UNITED STATES ATTORNEY FOR THE
NORTHERN DISTRICT OF CALIFORNIA .
KAT LIKES TO SAY SHE'S SPENT HER LIFE COLLECTING EXPERIENCES
RATHER THAN CLIMBING LADDERS. AND FOR HER THOSE EXPERIENCES
HAVE CENTERED ON PEOPLE, COMMUNITY AND THE PRIVILEGE OF
HELPING MAKE SAN FRANCISCO A BETTER PLACE.
TODAY I SEE OUT IN THE AUDIENCE THE GENERAL MANAGER OF REC PARK
SARAH MEDLAND. I SEE COMMISSIONER VINITA LOUIS
I SEE STEFAN FRIENDS OF THE FRIENDS OF LAFAYETTE PARK.
THESE ARE JUST A FEW AND I KNOW I'M MISSING SOMEBODY.
>> I'M SORRY I'M SURE I'LL GET A TEXT LATER BUT THESE ARE JUST
A FEW OF THE PEOPLE WHO HAVE COME TO SUPPORT KAT IN THE WAY
THAT SHE SUPPORTS SO MANY OF US AND BY SO MANY OF US IN MANY
WAYS I MEAN ME KAT ON A PERSONAL NOTE, I AM DEEPLY
GRATEFUL TO YOU FOR YOUR FRIENDSHIP, FOR YOUR
GRACIOUSNESS AND FOR YOUR EVER BLUNT HONESTY ACCOMPANIED BY A
SMILE AND A HUG THAT HAS GIVEN ME SO MUCH MORE THAN I COULD
EVER GIVE TO YOU. >> I THINK I SPEAK ON BEHALF OF
MOST OF THIS ROOM IN SAYING THANK YOU FOR CONTINUING TO
SERVE SAN FRANCISCO, FOR CONTINUING TO STEP UP TO THE
CALL AND CONTINUING TO MAKE SURE THAT ALL OF OUR FAMILIES
ARE AS HAPPY AND WONDERFUL AS YOURS.
SO KAT, FOR TEN YEARS OF SERVICE TO REC PARK THANK YOU.
AND FOR MANY MANY MORE THAN THAT TO OUR CITY.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
NOW IF WE AND I. I WOULD JUST SUPERVISE CHERYL
AND KAT. >> I WOULD JUST LIKE TO THROW
MY OWN THANKS TO YOU FOR I THINK I'VE PROBABLY KNOWN YOU
NOW FOR AT LEAST A COUPLE OF DECADES AND DURING THAT TIME
YOU HAVE THROWN YOURSELF INTO SERVICE TO SAN FRANCISCO ON REC
PARK BUT IN LOTS AND LOTS OF WAYS AND WE APPRECIATE YOU SO
THIS IS AN EXCELLENT COMMENDATION.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHERYL FOR DOING IT.
>> THANK YOU. I MADE REMARKS AND BEFORE I
START THEM I WANTED TO ASK IF EVERYBODY WHO'S HERE FOR ME
WOULD STAND UP BECAUSE I WANT TO SHARE MY VILLAGE WITH YOU
AND THERE ARE MANY OF YOU HERE IN THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS WHO
ARE PART OF MY VILLAGE. SO IF EVERYONE WHO CAME OUT
HERE COULD PLEASE STAND UP THERE ARE PEOPLE WITH REC
AND PARK ON THE COMMISSION AND THE DEPARTMENT OUR HARBOR
MASTER BEN DAVIS CITY OF ALL STEFAN FRANZ THE BANDSHELL
CONCERTS MY CHURCH FRIENDS OF PARKS I KNOW I'M GOING TO
ROBERT YOU KNOW S.F. BEAUTIFUL MY MY GANG OVER HERE CAROL
AND MARY AND DECKER AND AUSTIN AND VINITA.
>> I JUST I'M COMPLETELY OVERWHELMED.
KIM AND LABORS SO I'D LIKE TO GO INTO MY REMARKS BUT I JUST
WANTED TO THANK EVERYBODY FOR YOUR TIME.
IT'S HARD TO COME OUT HERE, HEIDI AND I REALLY, REALLY
APPRECIATE IT. >> PRESIDENT MANAGEMENT IT
GIVES ME SUCH JOY TO SAY THAT I HAVE GROWN UP WITH RAPHE
LITERALLY WE HAVE GROWN UP IN AGE TOGETHER.
>> SCUSE ME YOU PROBABLY BETTER THAN I ESTEEMED SUPERVISORS
AND ESPECIALLY MY SUPERVISOR STEVEN CHERYL AND I'M SO PROUD
OF YOU. >> I BELIEVE THAT GRATITUDE
AND SERVICE ARE OUR HIGHEST PURSUITS.
NONE OF US GETS THROUGH THIS LIFE ALONE.
WE INHERIT SO MUCH FROM THE PEOPLE AND THE COMMUNITIES WHO
CAME BEFORE US AND THE PEOPLE WHO WALK ALONGSIDE US.
>> GRATITUDE IS RECOGNIZING WHAT WE'VE BEEN GIVEN
AND SERVICE IS CHOOSING TO GIVE SOMETHING BACK AND SOMEWHERE
IN THAT EXCHANGE WE FIND CONNECTION AND THE POSSIBILITY
OF MEANINGFUL CHANGE. >> BECAUSE OF MY WORK ON THE
REC AND PARK COMMISSION THESE LAST TEN YEARS I HAVE AN
UNDERSTANDING OF HOW DEEPLY IMPORTANT OUR PARKS
AND RECREATION SPACES ARE TO THE CONNECTIONS THAT SAN
FRANCISCANS MAKE AS THEY COME TOGETHER TO PLAY EXERCISE,
CELEBRATE OR SIMPLY BE OUR DEPARTMENT STEWARDS THE
GREATEST URBAN PARK SYSTEM IN THE WORLD.
>> YES SARAH MADELINE, WHERE ARE YOU AND SARAH RAISE YOUR
HAND. >> OKAY.
>> WE WOULDN'T HAVE THAT WITHOUT THE SUPPORT OF SAN
FRANCISCANS. >> ALL OF YOU OUR MAYOR AND OUR
INCREDIBLE WORK FORCE. >> VINCE TERESA.
I'VE BEEN AN ACTIVIST AND A VOLUNTEER MOST OF MY LIFE BUT
NOTHING MADE MY COMMITMENT SERVICE MORE MEANINGFUL THAN
BECOMING A MOM. >> AND WHEN PATRICK AND DIANA
WERE LITTLE WE SPENT MANY HOURS IN OUR PARKS AND SOME WERE
WONDERFUL AND SOME WERE SERVICEABLE AND SOME WERE
NEGLECTED. BUT OVER THE LAST 20 YEARS
EXTRAORDINARY TRANSFORMATION HAS OCCURRED AND I WANT TO
RECOGNIZE THE GREAT WORK OF OUR REC AND PARK EMPLOYEES
REPRESENTED BY 17 UNIONS WITH LABORERS LOCAL TO 61
REPRESENTING OUR LARGEST COHORT I BELIEVE IN THE INFINITE
PAYBACK OF INVESTING IN OUR YOUNG PEOPLE AT REC AND PARK.
ONE OF OUR GREATEST ASSETS IS OUR GARDENER APPRENTICESHIP
PROGRAM. FOR ALMOST 20 YEARS THIS
PROGRAM HAS PROVIDED SKILLS, OPPORTUNITY AND HOPE TO THE
NEXT GENERATION WHO WILL CARE FOR OUR PARKS AND MY UNION
MEDIA WORKERS GUILD I CO-FOUNDED BAY NEWS RISING
WHERE STUDENTS RECEIVED MENTORS AND OPPORTUNITIES TO PUBLISH
AND WERE PAID SOMETIMES FOR THE FIRST TIME IN THEIR LIFE FOR
THEIR WORK. >> WHEN WE INVEST IN A YOUNG
PERSON WE'RE NOT JUST CHANGING ONE LIFE.
WE'RE STRENGTHENING FAMILIES, BUILDING CAREERS AND SHAPING
THE PEOPLE WHO WILL CARE FOR THIS CITY FOR GENERATIONS TO
COME. WE ARE STRENGTHENING COMMUNITY.
CAN YOU IMAGINE ANYTHING ELSE THAT IS MORE IMPORTANT?
>> AND I WANT TO ASSOCIATE WITH MY REMARKS SOME OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO'S GREATEST CELEBRATIONS ILLUMINATE CITY OF
ALL EVENTS HARDLY STRICTLY BLUEGRASS OUTSIDE LAND'S FLOWER
PIANO IN THE GARDENS OF GOLDEN GATE PARK AND SAN FRANCISCO
FLEET WEEK. I'M DEEPLY GRATEFUL TO THE
PEOPLE WHO BRING CREATIVITY, ENERGY AND CONNECTION TO THE
CITY THROUGH EVENTS LIKE THESE LIKE THOSE DEEPLY ENGAGED
PEOPLE I WAKE UP WITH THE VIGOR TO DO WHATEVER I CAN TO HELP MY
FRIENDS, COLLEAGUES AND FELLOW RESIDENTS MAKE THIS CITY WELL
AWESOME. I DO NOT ACCEPT THIS HONOR
LIGHTLY. I SHARE IT WITH ALL THOSE
WHO'VE WALKED AND WORKED BESIDE ME, CHALLENGED AND ENCOURAGED
ME AND GIVEN ME THE OPPORTUNITIES TO LEARN AND TO
GIVE BACK AND I WOULD NOT BE STANDING HERE TODAY WITHOUT MY
HUSBAND DAVE, MY SON PATRICK DEDE IS NOT HERE.
MY MOM DIANA, ALL OF MY EXTENDED FAMILY.
THANK YOU. YOU ARE THE LIGHTS OF MY LIFE
AND MY INSPIRATIONAL FIREPOWER AND TO ALL OF YOU THANK YOU FOR
YOUR DEEP COMMITMENT TO THE PEOPLE OF SAN FRANCISCO
ESPECIALLY FOR SUPPORTING PARKS AND RECREATION SPACES AND TO
THOSE WHO WORK IN THEM. THANK YOU FOR INVESTING IN THE
NEXT GENERATION AND I WILL CONTINUE TO STAND WITH YOU AS
LONG AS I CAN AND MAYBE EVEN AFTER I CAN.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR EVERYBODY WITH ME COME ON OUTSIDE.
>> THANK YOU. OH NECK NEXT UP DISTRICT THREE
SUPERVISOR SAUTER THANK YOU, PRESIDENT GENTLEMEN, TODAY I
HAVE THE HONOR OF WELCOMING COMMANDER CHRISTOPHER DELGADO
TO THE CHAMBERS. >> COMMANDER, WOULD YOU PLEASE
COME ON UP AND JOIN US? >> YOU ARE COMMANDER NOW BUT WE
ARE HERE TO THANK YOU AND CELEBRATE YOUR TIME AS
CAPTAIN OF CENTRAL STATION. AND TO DO THAT I KNOW WE'VE GOT
ABOUT HALF THE FORCE HERE. WE'VE GOT COMMUNITY LEADERS
FROM ACROSS THE DISTRICT BUT PROBABLY MOST IMPORTANTLY WE
HAVE YOUR HUSBAND BILLY. WE HAVE OUR CHIEF.
WE HAVE OUR NEW CAPTAIN OF CENTRAL CAPTAIN JOE.
YOU'VE GOT ALL THE RIGHT PEOPLE IN THE ROOM TO CELEBRATE YOU
THROUGH ALMOST 20 YEARS WITH S.F. PD COMMANDER DUGAN, D.O.
HAS BEEN NO STRANGER TO CENTRAL STATION.
HE HAS SERVED AS AN OFFICER, A LIEUTENANT AND A CAPTAIN THERE
AND WE ARE SO VERY LUCKY THAT HE HAS SPENT SO MUCH OF HIS
CAREER AT CENTRAL. >> HE HAS BEEN FULLY COMMITTED
TO THE CULTURE OF CENTRAL STATION WHICH KNOWS WE KEEP
EACH OTHER SAFE BY BUILDING RELATIONSHIPS AND BEING PRESENT
IN THE COMMUNITY. HE'S BEEN FOCUSED ON FOOT
PATROLS RECENTLY, EXPANDING THEM TO FISHERMAN'S WHARF
BECAUSE IN HIS WORDS IF YOU'RE IN A CAR YOU DON'T MAKE THOSE
CONNECTIONS AS MUCH. AND CENTRAL STATION IS A GREAT
EXAMPLE OF WHY WE NEED FOLKS ON THE STREET.
THE CAPTAINS FOCUS IN UNION SQUARE LOVE MARISSA RODRIGUEZ
HAS BEEN A MAJOR REASON WHY WE'RE SEEING THAT ICONIC
NEIGHBORHOOD COME BACK AND FLOURISH WITH EVENTS
AND DOZENS OF NEW STORE OPENINGS.
SO THANK YOU FOR THAT AND I ESPECIALLY APPRECIATE THE FOCUS
THAT YOU'VE BROUGHT TO LOWER HILL AND I SAW BARBARA SWAN OF
THE LOWER NEIGHBORHOOD LOWER HILL NEIGHBORHOOD ALLIANCE HERE
TODAY AS WELL BECAUSE THAT IS A NEIGHBORHOOD THAT HAS TOO OFTEN
BEEN IGNORED AND HAS BEEN IN NEED OF MORE ATTENTION
AND YOU HAVE GIVEN IT THAT ATTENTION AND YOU'VE BEEN
WARMLY WELCOMED IN CHINATOWN WHERE THE COMMUNITY GAVE YOU A
CHINESE NICKNAME MEANING THE GOLDEN CAPTAIN.
COMMANDER DELGADO HAS NOT ONLY BEEN A TREMENDOUS COMMUNITY
PARTNER, HE HAS BEEN A MODEL OF INSPIRATION AND HE HAS BROKEN
BARRIERS AS THE FIRST OPENLY GAY CAPTAIN IN THE HISTORY OF
S.F. PD, HE NOW SERVES AS THE CO-CHAIR OF THE LGBTQ PLUS
ADVISORY FORUM SO THAT S.F. PD CAN CONTINUE TO BE A MODEL OF
WHAT A DIVERSE AND INCLUSIVE POLICE FORCE LOOKS LIKE.
>> SO TO THE FOREVER GOLDEN CAPTAIN OF CENTRAL STATION IT'S
IT'S A GOOD NICKNAME. >> SO YOU DO AND YOU EARNED IT.
I LIKE IT. THANK YOU.
TO CELEBRATE MY COLLEAGUE LIKES TO BRING THE DONUTS I GOT I'VE
GOT SOMETHING ELSE BECAUSE I KNOW YOU'LL BE MISSING NORTH
BEACH WE'VE GOT THE WORLD'S FINEST AKASHA FROM NORTH BEACH
FROM THE 115 YEAR OLD BAKERY BAKERY AND THERE'S ENOUGH TO
SHARE ALL THIS IS ENOUGH TO SHARE WITH EVERYONE BUT
COMMANDER, IT'S BEEN A PLEASURE.
I'M SO HAPPY THAT IN YOUR NEW ROLE AS COMMANDER YOU'RE STILL
WORKING A LOT WITH CENTRAL AND OUR NEIGHBORHOODS ARE
BETTER OFF FOR IT. >> SO THANK YOU AND THE FLOOR
IS YOURS. THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU KNOW FLOOR THE DORSEY ARE YOU OH LET'S GET
AWAY THE FLOOR IS BACK TO THE PRESENT FOR A MOMENT I I WANT
TO THANK YOU SAM REGISTER AND THAT STRIKES ME AS AN
ALARMINGLY HEALTHY VARIATION ON THE DONUT SO I DON'T KNOW ABOUT
THAT BUT I HAVE OH, GOOD. >> DORSEY IS GOING TO SAY SOME
THINGS I, I HAVE HAD THE HONOR AND PRIVILEGE OF GETTING TO
WORK WITH CRYSTAL GANDY AND SEVERAL OF HIS DIFFERENT
POSTINGS AND IT HAS BEEN A VERY HAPPY THING TO WATCH YOU MOVE
YOUR WAY UP THROUGH THE RANKS IN THIS POLICE DEPARTMENT.
I ALWAYS, YOU KNOW, HAVE KIND OF IN THE BACK OF MY HEAD THAT,
YOU KNOW, THIS IS A DEPARTMENT THAT 40 YEARS AGO WHEN MY
PREDECESSOR HARVEY MILK WAS, YOU KNOW, ON THE BOARD THE
RELATIONSHIP BETWEEN THE POLICE DEPARTMENT AND THE GAY
AND LESBIAN COMMUNITY AT THE TIME WAS NOT A STRONG ONE.
IT WAS A TERRIBLE ONE AND I THINK IT IS THERE'S MORE WORK
TO BE DONE OF COURSE, BUT I THINK IT'S WORTH JUST
CELEBRATING YOU KNOW, THE CHANGES IN THAT RELATIONSHIP,
THE FACT THAT YOU DO HAVE PEOPLE WORKING THEIR WAY UP
THROUGH THE RANKS LOOKING FORWARD TO HAVING A WE HAVE A
GREAT CHIEF SO OUR CHIEF NEEDS TO STAY FOR A VERY, VERY LONG
TIME BUT AT SOME POINT WE HAVE TO HAVE A CAREER CHIEF AND OF
COURSE ALSO WANT TO CALL OUT SOME OF THE WOMEN WHO ACTUALLY
HAVE HAVE BEEN ABLE TO TO WORK THEIR WAY UP THE RANKS AS WELL.
THE GAY MEN HAVE BEEN SLIGHTLY STRAGGLING.
>> AND CHRISTOPHER DELGADO, THANK YOU FOR STICKING YOU
KNOW, FOR FOR MAKING IT FOR FOR THE GUYS AND SUPERVISOR DORSEY
THANK YOU PRESIDENT MANDELA AND I JUST WANT TO ECHO AS A AS
A FORMER COLLEAGUE YOU KNOW I LEARNED A LOT FROM YOU BUT ALSO
I THINK AS A MEMBER OF THE LGBTQ PLUS COMMUNITY
AND SOMEONE WHO'S AWARE OF THE HISTORY THAT OUR COMMUNITY HAS
HAD OVER THE DECADES PASSED WITH LAW ENFORCEMENT IN THE
CITY AND ELSEWHERE HOW MEANINGFUL IT IS BUT ALSO
BECAUSE YOU KNOW, HAD IT NOT BEEN FOR AN AIDS CRISIS THAT
REALLY CLAIMED A GENERATION OF GAY MEN, THERE MIGHT HAVE BEEN
OTHERS WHO DIDN'T HAVE THE OPPORTUNITY.
I AM GRATEFUL FOR THE LEADERSHIP OF OUR LESBIAN
SISTERS WHO ARE WHO REALLY PIONEERED SOME SOME LEADERSHIP.
BUT I'M JUST ALSO IMPRESSED AND GRATEFUL THAT YOU GET TO BE
BREAKING BARRIERS NOW FOR THE COMMUNITY AND FOR GAY MEN.
I'M REALLY PROUD OF YOU AND IT'S AN HONOR TO CONTINUE
WORKING WITH YOU AS A MEMBER OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
>> THANK YOU. >> YOU'RE RIGHT.
I WROTE A MINI SPEECH I PROMISE IT'S MANY BUT THANK YOU SO MUCH
FOR THIS WONDERFUL HONOR. THERE'S AN ABSOLUTE PLEASURE
WORKING WITH YOU. TRY AND SOLVE COMPLEX PROBLEMS
IN OUR NEIGHBORHOODS. YOU HELPED BRING TOGETHER THE
POLICE COMMUNITY LEADERS, CITY LEADERS ALL THE WORK HARD TO
MAKE THINGS BETTER AND WITH YOUR HELP I THINK WE
ACCOMPLISHED A LOT. >> I HAVE A FEW MORE THANK
YOU'S FIRST MY OFFICERS AT CENTRAL STATION.
WHEN I ASKED THEY ANSWERED. THEY WORKED HARD AT THE TASK I
GAVE THEM TO BEST SERVE THEIR COMMUNITY AND THE RESULTS
SHOWED I WAS HONORED TO SERVE AMONGST SOME OF THE BEST COPS
IN THE CITY. I LIKE TO THANK MY CENTRAL
STATION CAPTAIN STAFF WHO IS STANDING IN THE BACK OF THE
ROOM. THEY FEEL THAT THROUGH NUMEROUS
REQUESTS THEY CAME THROUGH MY OFFICE AND THANK YOU FOR YOUR
WORK ENSURING SPECIAL EVENTS WENT SMOOTHLY AND THERE WERE
MANY OF THEM. I WOULD ALSO LIKE TO THANK MY
LEADERSHIP TEAM MY LIEUTENANTS AT CENTRAL WHO RAN ALL THE
WATCHERS AND MADE SURE OUR CENTRAL RAN SMOOTHLY DESPITE
BEING ONE OF THE BUSIEST STATIONS AND I WANT TO THANK
THE COMMAND STAFF FOR THEIR SUPPORT AND TO TRUSTING ME TO
RUN MY STATION LIKE I WAS CHIEF OF POLICE OF THE CENTRAL
DISTRICT ALLOWED ME TO BE SUCCESSFUL IN MY OWN RIGHT.
I WANT TO THANK THE COMMUNITY MANY LEADERS WHO ARE HERE TODAY
WHO CARE VERY MUCH ABOUT THE NEIGHBORHOODS THAT THEY LIVED
IN AND WORKED HARD ALONGSIDE US TO MAKE THEIR NEIGHBORHOODS
SAFE. YOU ALL IS ACCOUNTABLE AND WHEN
WE HAD SUCCESSES YOU SHOWERED US WITH GRATITUDE.
YOUR SUPPORT MEANS A LOT TO ME AND THE COPS WHO WORK IN YOUR
DISTRICT. I'D LIKE TO THANK MY HUSBAND
BILLY ALTHOUGH I LIKE TO JOKE THAT YOU SINGLE HANDEDLY FUNDED
UNION SQUARE'S RECOVERY WITH OUR CREDIT CARD YOU PUT UP WITH
THE LONG DAY'S WEEKENDS AWAY LAST MINUTE CHANGES THE PLANS
BECAUSE OF SPONTANEOUS EVENTS OR PROTESTS.
BUT YOUR SUPPORT WAS UNWAVERING AND FOR THAT I AM FOREVER
GRATEFUL. LASTLY, I'D LIKE TO THANK MY
MOM. ALTHOUGH SHE HAS BEEN GONE OVER
20 YEARS SHE WAS THE ONE WHO INSTILLED IN ME TO BE KIND TO
STRANGERS AND HELP THOSE IN NEED.
>> I'M SURE SHE IS LOOKING DOWN ON ME TODAY FILLED WITH PRIDE.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
THANK
. >> UP NEXT WE HAVE DISTRICT
FOUR SUPERVISOR WONG. >> HELLO.
I'D LIKE TO INVITE UP THE BATTALION SIX NEIGHBORHOOD
EMERGENCY RESPONSE TEAM. >> COLLEAGUES SEPTEMBER IS
NATIONAL PREPAREDNESS MONTH A TIME TO REMIND ALL OF US OF THE
IMPORTANCE OF BEING PREPARED AND READY TO RESPOND WHEN AN
EMERGENCY HAPPENS. TODAY I'M PROUD TO RECOGNIZE
MEMBERS OF THE SAN FRANCISCO FIRE DEPARTMENT'S NEIGHBORHOOD
EMERGENCY RESPONSE TEAM OR NURSE.
FURTHER IMPORTANT WORK THEY DO TO HELP KEEP OUR COMMUNITIES
ACROSS SAN FRANCISCO SAFE AND PREPARED.
IT BRINGS TOGETHER RESIDENTS, VOLUNTEERS, FIRE DEPARTMENT
PERSONNEL AND LONGTIME COMMUNITY LEADERS WHO DEDICATE
THEIR TIME TO MAKING SURE SAN FRANCISCANS HAVE THE KNOWLEDGE
AND SKILLS THEY NEED BEFORE AN EMERGENCY HAPPENS WHILE SERVING
AS AN AMERICORPS DISASTER PREPAREDNESS SPECIALIST AT THE
AMERICAN RED CROSS, I BECAME NURSE TRAINED MYSELF AND KNOW
THE FIRST I KNOW FIRSTHAND HOW VALUABLE THIS FIRE DEPARTMENT
PROGRAM IS IN GIVING RESIDENTS THE SKILLS AND CONFIDENCE TO
HELP THEIR FAMILIES AND NEIGHBORS IN AN EMERGENCY.
I'M ESPECIALLY PROUD OF THE WORK HAPPENING IN DISTRICT
FOUR. THE SUNSET TEAM IS PART OF
BATTALION SIX AND HAS BEEN ACTIVE AT OUR SUNSET NIGHT
MARKETS CONNECTING DIRECTLY WITH RESIDENTS AND SPREADING
THE WORD ABOUT DISASTER PREPAREDNESS AND NURSE
TRAINING. >> TODAY I WANT TO RECOGNIZE
THE NURSE ADVISORY BOARD MEMBERS DAN RABINOWITZ
AND STEIGER AS SAFETY PERSONNEL BRANDON TOM, ALLIE SWEENEY,
PATRICIA LU AND HASHIM ANDERSON AND RETIREES DANIEL CASEY,
NORMAN CABA AND ANGELA ROMERO. AS RECOGNIZED NATIONAL
PREPAREDNESS MONTH I WANT TO THANK ALL OF YOU AND THE MANY
NURSE MEMBERS AND VOLUNTEERS ACROSS SAN FRANCISCO FOR THE
TIME AND COMMITMENT YOU GIVE PREPARING OUR RESIDENTS
AND STRENGTHENING OUR COMMUNITIES.
IT IS MY HONOR TO RECOGNIZE AND COMMEND ALL OF YOU FOR YOUR
SERVICE AND DEDICATION TO SAN FRANCISCO.
AND WITH THAT I'D LIKE TO TURN IT OVER TO NURSE PROGRAM
COORDINATOR CAPTAIN BRANDON TOM TO SAY A FEW WORDS ON BEHALF OF
THE TEAM. IF I COULD.
MY NAME'S ERIKA BROWN. I'M ASSISTANT DEPUTY CHIEF
AND HERE ON BEHALF OF CHIEF CHRISTMAN TO REALLY SHOW
APPRECIATION FOR THE WORK THAT THE MEMBERS OF OUR DEPARTMENT
ARE DOING AND TO ANSWER THE QUESTION WHAT ARE WE DOING
TOGETHER? AND THAT IS A COMMUNITY FIRE
DEPARTMENT PARTNERSHIP TO GET OUR CITY READY FOR FOR WHATEVER
MIGHT HAPPEN BIG OR SMALL. SO WITH THAT I'D LIKE TO SAY
CHIEF CHRISTMAN IS VERY APPRECIATIVE OF YOURSELF
AND INTRODUCE BRANDON TOM THANK YOU.
THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR KIND
WORDS. GOOD AFTERNOON PRESIDENT
MANDOLIN AND MEMBERS OF THE SOUTH SCHOOL BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS ON BEHALF OF THE SAN FRANCISCO FIRE DEPARTMENT
AND THE NEIGHBORHOOD EMERGENCY RESPONSE TEAM, I WANT TO TAKE A
MOMENT TO SIMPLY SAY THANK YOU .
>> THANK YOU FOR RECOGNIZING THE IMPORTANCE OF PREPARING OUR
COMMUNITIES BEFORE DISASTER STRIKES.
>> SAN FRANCISCO IS A CITY THAT KNOWS HOW QUICKLY CIRCUMSTANCES
CAN CHANGE AND EARTHQUAKE A MAJOR FIRE, A POWER OUTAGE OR
ANOTHER EMERGENCY CAN HAPPEN WITHOUT WARNING.
AND WHEN THAT MOMENT COMES, THE FIRST PEOPLE ABLE TO HELP MAY
NOT BE FIREFIGHTERS, PARAMEDICS OR POLICE OFFICERS.
>> THEY MAY BE OUR NEIGHBORS. THIS IS WHAT MAKES NURSES
SPECIAL. NURSE IS MORE THAN A TRAINING
PROGRAM. IT IS A COMMITMENT TO
COMMUNITY. IT IS NEIGHBORS LEARNING HOW TO
TAKE CARE OF THEMSELVES, THEIR FAMILIES AND ONE ANOTHER.
WHEN PROFESSIONAL RESPONDERS MAY BE OVERWHELMED OR UNABLE TO
REACH EVERYONE IMMEDIATELY. EVERY PERSON WHO COMPLETES
NURSE TRAINING BECOMES ANOTHER TRAINED SET OF HANDS ANOTHER
PERSON WHO KNOWS WHAT TO DO AND ANOTHER PERSON WHO CAN
PROVIDE HOPE WHEN THEIR COMMUNITY NEEDS IT MOST.
>> BUT THE STRENGTH OF NURSE ISN'T MEASURED ONLY BY THE
NUMBER OF PEOPLE WE TRAIN. IT IS MEASURED BY THE
RELATIONSHIPS WE BUILD PROMOTING NEIGHBORS HELPING
NEIGHBORS. IT IS MEASURED WHEN A NEIGHBOR
CHECKS ON AN OLDER ADULT WHEN TRAINED VOLUNTEERS GATHER
INFORMATION AND SHARE IT WITH THE FIRE DEPARTMENT.
AND WHEN ORDINARY SAN FRANCISCANS STEP FORWARD
AND SAY MY COMMUNITY NEEDS ME AND I AM READY.
>> THAT SPIRIT REPRESENTS THE VERY BEST OF SAN FRANCISCO.
>> I WANT TO THANK CHIEF DEAN CHRISTIAN CHIEF BROWN FOR
SUPPORTING THE PROGRAM AND FOR INVESTING IN PREPAREDNESS AT
THE NEIGHBORHOOD LEVEL. TO OUR VOLUNTEERS.
THANK YOU FOR GIVING YOUR TIME, YOUR ENERGY AND YOUR COMMITMENT
TO YOUR NEIGHBORS. YOU ARE AN ESSENTIAL PART OF
SAN FRANCISCO'S EMERGENCY PREPAREDNESS.
TO MY INSTRUCTORS, THANK YOU FOR SHARING YOUR KNOWLEDGE
AND EXPERTISE. >> WE CANNOT PREVENT DISASTERS
FROM HAPPENING BUT TOGETHER WE CAN MAKE SURE OUR NEIGHBORHOODS
ARE READY PREPARED. NEIGHBORHOODS ARE STRONGER.
NEIGHBORHOODS PREPARE NEIGHBORS BECOME RESILIENT COMMUNITIES
AND RESILIENT COMMUNITIES MAKE SAN FRANCISCO STRONGER.
THANK YOU FOR BELIEVING IN CHURCH.
THANK YOU FOR BELIEVING IN OUR NEIGHBORHOODS.
AND MOST IMPORTANTLY, THANK YOU FOR BELIEVING IN THE PEOPLE OF
SAN FRANCISCO. TOGETHER WE CAN ADVANCE THE
MODEL DO THE MOST GOOD FOR THE MOST PEOPLE.
>> SO I CHALLENGE YOU ALL TO COME AND TAKE NURTURING.
WE ARE FREE TO EVERYBODY WHO LIVES OR WORK IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH. I KNOW
. >> DISTRICT SEVEN SUPERVISOR
MELGAR. >> I'M A LITTLE AFRAID OF THIS
THING. YOU KNOW.
>> THANK YOU. I COULD I HAVE JOY IN.
>> COME UP, PLEASE. I'M GOING TO HAVE A NO ME.
>> THERE YOU ARE. >> COLLEAGUES, TODAY WE ARE
HONORING THE SPIRIT OF ADVENTURE AND EXPLORATION SHOWN
IN A WOMAN WHO HAS MADE HER CAREER OUT OF SHARING HER LOVE
OF TRAVEL WITH HER CLIENTS AND HER STUDENTS AND OUR CITY.
>> JOANNE GIOVANNONI HAS RUN PORTAL WORLD TRAVEL ON OCEAN
AVENUE FOR 47 YEARS. DURING THAT TIME SHE HAS SHARED
HER EXPERIENCE AND EXPERTISE WITH HUNDREDS OF APPRECIATIVE
CUSTOMERS WHO KNOW HER TO BE AN EXPERT FOR ALL DETAILS GREAT
AND SMALL. SHE HAS ORGANIZED TRIPS FOR
CUSTOMERS TO DESTINATIONS ALL OVER THE WORLD FROM AUSTRALIA
TO EASTER ISLAND. >> LONG TIME LOYAL CUSTOMERS
HAVE SHARED THAT JOANNE IS CREATIVE WHEN PLANNING
EXCURSIONS AND TOUGH WHEN NEGOTIATING WITH THE AIRLINES
AND VENDORS. SO BEYOND THE INCREDIBLE WORK
THAT JOANNE HAS DONE FOR ALL OUR NEIGHBORS WITH HER
BUSINESS, SHE ALSO HAS BEEN A MENTOR FOR MANY EMPLOYEES
AND AN INSPIRATION FOR JEN RATIOS OF STUDENTS AT CITY
COLLEGE OF SAN FRANCISCO. FOR THE TRAVEL AND TOURISM
PROGRAM WHICH AS WE ALL KNOW TRAVEL AND TOURISM IS ACTUALLY
THE NUMBER ONE INDUSTRY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
JOANNE SERVED AS CHAIR OF THIS PROGRAM AT CITY COLLEGE BEFORE
RETIRING FROM TEACHING IN 2021 .
>> HER CLASSES WERE FUN, INFORMATIVE AND SHE HAS ALWAYS
PUT THE JUST THE TOP OF THE QUALITY.
FOR ALL THE LATEST INTERNATIONAL TRAVEL TRENDS
JOANNE I WANT TO TAKE YOUR CLASS SO I HAVE YOU MAYBE DO
THAT FAVORITE FOR US AT SOME POINT.
MANY OF HER STUDENTS HAVE GONE ON TO BUILD THRIVING TOURISM
AND TRAVEL CAREERS FOR THEMSELVES AND CONTINUE TO LOOK
AT JOANNE FOR GUIDANCE. UNDER HER INSPIRED LEADERSHIP,
THE TRAVEL AND TOURISM PROGRAM AT CITY COLLEGE GENERATED
SIGNIFICANT REVENUE AND EARNED INTERNATIONAL DISTINCTION
DRIVEN BY HER CLASSES FULL OF INTERNATIONAL STUDENTS.
LOCAL RESIDENTS RETURNING VETERANS ATTAINING THEIR
GRADUATION, THEIR GRADUATION WITH THE GI BILL.
THANK YOU FOR ALL OF THAT, JOANNE.
WHILE SHE IS NO LONGER TEACHING AT CITY COLLEGE, JOANNE
GIOVANNONI IS GENEROUS. SPIRIT CONTINUES TO INSPIRE A
LOVE OF TRAVEL AND CURIOSITY IN OTHER PLACES AND CULTURES.
IN JUST THE LOVE OF THE OTHER INDIAN ADVENTURE OF IT
IN EVERYONE WHO ENCOUNTERS HER HER ENTHUSIASM IS INFECTIOUS.
THANK YOU JOANNE FOR REMINDING US TO EXPLORE, TO LEARN TO LOVE
THE WORLD AROUND US AND FOR MENTORING SO MANY GENERATIONS
OF YOUNG PEOPLE TO DO THE SAME. >> THANK YOU FOR THANK YOU FOR
YOUR KIND WORDS. >> I THINK THE EASIEST THING I
CAN SAY IS IF YOU CAN FIND SOMETHING THAT YOU LOVE AND YOU
CAN MAKE A LIVING AT THAT THEN EVERYONE IS HAPPY.
>> THE PEOPLE YOU COME IN CONTACT WITH AND YOURSELF.
>> I FEEL VERY, VERY FORTUNATE, VERY LUCKY TO HAVE PURSUED MY
TWO GREATEST PASSIONS TEACHING AND TRAVEL AND I WAS FIGURE
THINKING ABOUT HOW MANY YEARS I'VE BEEN TEACHING.
I ACTUALLY BEEN TEACHING MOST OF MY ADULT LIFE NEARLY 60
YEARS STARTED AS A PART TIME TEACHER IN JUNIOR WHAT ABOUT
THE SEVENTH GRADE IN SANTA CRUZ?
>> AND I SURVIVED THAT. IT WAS TOUGH AS YOU'VE EVER
DEALT WITH THAT AGE GROUP. IT'S IT'S TOUGH AND LOVED EVERY
MINUTE OF IT. AND OF COURSE THE 37 YEARS THAT
I SPENT AT CITY COLLEGE WAS A JOY.
TO GIVE YOU AN IDEA OF HOW FAR REACHING THAT PROGRAM WAS.
MY YOUNGER BROTHER SCOTT TAUGHT WITH ME.
HE'S HERE WITH ME AS WELL AS SOME OF MY OTHER FAMILY MEMBERS
,FRIENDS, CLIENTS AND WE WERE TALKING ABOUT OUR STUDENTS
AND WE CAME UP WITH A LIST OF STUDENTS THAT CAME FROM
COUNTRIES THAT WE CAN'T GO TO MYANMAR.
VENEZUELA IS A TOUGH, TOUGH DEAL.
LEBANON, SYRIA WE HAD A SERIES OF STUDENTS THAT CAME FROM
SERIES THREE FOUR STUDENTS PAKISTAN, IRAQ, IRAN ALL
THROUGHOUT AFRICA. ABSOLUTELY AMAZING.
AND WE WONDERED HOW DID THEY FIND THE PROGRAM?
THE INTERNET OF COURSE THEY GOOGLED IT AND FOUND TRAVEL
AND TOURISM IN ONE OF THE GREATEST CITIES IN THE WORLD
AND THE THOUSANDS OF STUDENTS THAT WE HAD THROUGH THE PROGRAM
I CAN GUARANTEE YOU EVERY ONE OF THEM WENT HOME AS AN
AMBASSADOR TO THE UNITED STATES.
BUT MORE THAN THAT, SUPER AMBASSADORS FOR THE CITY OF SAN
FRANCISCO NOT ONE STUDENT WENT HOME WITHOUT TEARS IN THEIR
EYES AND MANY OF THEM DO COME BACK.
I JUST WANT TO TELL YOU ONE EXAMPLE THAT WE SCOTT AND I
TALKED ABOUT IT HUNDREDS AND HUNDREDS OF EXAMPLES
AND THE STUDENTS STAY IN TOUCH WHICH IS SOMETHING THAT IS
VERY, VERY HEARTWARMING FOR ANYONE WHO'S TAUGHT YOU TEACH
YOU THINK YOU DO A GOOD JOB. THE STUDENT LIVES OUT INTO THE
WORLD AND THEN YOU DON'T KNOW. BUT WE HAD THIS ONE STUDENT WHO
WAS LATE TO CLASS ONE EVENING AND AFTER CLASS HE CAME UP
AND APOLOGIZED AND I SAID WELL, YOU KNOW, THINGS HAPPENED.
I DIDN'T KNOW IF I'D GOTTEN STUCK IN TRAFFIC OR WHAT.
>> AND HE SAID NO, THAT HIS ADVISOR FOR THE GROUP A
FULBRIGHT COMMITTEE HAD BEEN LATE.
>> NOW I DIDN'T KNOW I HAD A FULBRIGHT SCHOLAR IN MY
CLASSROOM. >> TURNS OUT THERE WERE TWO ONE
FROM PAKISTAN AND ONE FROM PANAMA AND THE STUDENT FROM
PAKISTAN HAD COME WAS A COLLEGE GRADUATE HAD COME TO THE
PROGRAM TO GET THE TWO YEAR A ASSOCIATED ARTS DEGREE TO HELP
RUN WHAT HIS GREAT GRANDFATHER HAD STARTED AS A HUNTING LODGE
WAY UP BY K2 MOUNTAIN THAT THE BORDER PAKISTAN AND CHINA
AND THIS TWO ROOM HUNTING COTTAGE HAD DEVELOPED INTO A
TEN ROOM HOTEL THAT HE AND HIS BROTHERS WERE RUNNING AND HE
WANTED TO FIND OUT HOW COULD HE MARKET THIS, HOW COULD HE GET
THIS FABULOUS RESORT WAY UP IN THE PAKISTAN MOUNTAINS OUT
TO THE PUBLIC AND TERRIFIC STUDENT HE WENT HOME PARDON ME
AND WITHIN TWO DAYS OF GOING HOME AFTER RECEIVING HIS
ASSOCIATED ARTS DEGREE I GOT AN URGENT MESSAGE ACTUALLY FROM
THE RED CROSS THAT THE POLICE WERE LOOKING FOR HIM.
HE'D GOTTEN WORD THAT THEY WERE ON THEIR WAY TO INTERROGATE HIM
BECAUSE AFTER ALL HE'D BEEN IN THE UNITED STATES FOR A
COUPLE OF YEARS SO HE MUST BE A SPY THAT NIGHT HE PACKED A
SUITCASE AND WALKED OUT OF PAKISTAN ACROSS THE CHINESE
BORDER. HE WAS ABLE TO MAKE HIS WAY
BACK TO SAN FRANCISCO WITHIN A WEEK AND WITH THE KIND HELP OF
THE FULBRIGHT COMMITTEE AND THE LATE GREAT SENATOR DIANNE
FEINSTEIN WHO WENT TO BAT FOR HIM, HE GOT ASYLUM AND HE'S
HERE NOW IN SAN FRANCISCO AS A RESIDENT WORKING IN THE HOTEL
BUSINESS. SO THAT'S JUST ONE OF THE MANY
STORIES THAT WE HAVE TO VERY, VERY TOUCHING.
SO I FEEL VERY PROUD THAT I MET AND WORKED WITH SO MANY OF
THESE INTERNATIONAL STUDENTS. AND THEN THE SECOND PASSION OF
TRAVEL I'VE ALWAYS TRAVELED BUT I DON'T KNOW LET ME ASK YOU THE
FIRST TIME YOU SAW SOME WORLD MONUMENT THAT YOU'D ONLY EVER
SEEN IN A PICTURE THE FIRST TIME MAYBE YOU SAW THE GREAT
WALL OF CHINA OR THE EIFFEL TOWER OR BIG BEN.
YOU REMEMBER THAT FEELING THAT IT WAS REAL THAT YOU COULD
ACTUALLY SEE IT? WELL, THAT'S WHAT I TRY
AND INSPIRE IN MY CLIENTS WHEN THEY TRAVEL TRY AND SHARE MY
PERSONAL EXPERIENCES. I AM WELL TRAVELED BUT I GET MY
OTHER TRAVEL EXPERIENCE TO MY CLIENTS SO I'D LIKE TO THANK MY
FAMILY FOR BEING HERE MY VERY PATIENT HUSBAND I'M SORRY
SWEETHEART, BUT I DID RENEW MY LEASE.
I'M NOT RETIRING ANY TIME SOON .
MY BROTHER WHO IS MY RIGHT RIGHT RIGHT HAND MAN THROUGH
SCHOOL THROUGH ALL OF MY CLASSES, MY CLIENTS, SOME THAT
I'VE KNOWN FOR 3540 YEARS MY FRIENDS AND A CATEGORY THAT YOU
MAY NOT BE AWARE OF BUT THE SALES REPS THESE WERE THE
PEOPLE WE'RE ALL DINOSAURS NOW SALES REPS THESE ARE THE PEOPLE
THAT WE TRUSTED THAT I TRUSTED TO TEACH ME THE INDUSTRY FROM
THE INSIDE OUT AND THEY WOULD COME IN AND INTRODUCE US TO BIG
FIVE SAFARI OR MAYBE FLY INTERNATIONAL AND THEY'RE HERE
TONIGHT OR TODAY ALSO TO SUPPORT ME.
>> SO I WANT TO THANK YOU ALL. I LOVE WHAT I DO.
I HAVE ALWAYS LOVED IT AND TO HAVE YOU APPRECIATE OR
ACKNOWLEDGE THAT TO ME MEANS ALL THE WORLD AND TO ME I
SINCERELY THANK YOU. WELL MY Q&A MY PEOPLE I JUST
WANT TO OH, THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU.
THIS IS FOR YOU. I'M OKAY.
I WANT TO
DISTRICT 11 SUPERVISOR CHEN THANK YOU.
PERSON MANAGEMENT MAY AS AND THANK FROM NEWS DIRECTOR TO
THE PODIUM COLLEAGUES IT'S MY GREAT HONOR TODAY TO RECOGNIZE
KATIE AS OF CHANNEL 26 FOR 50 YEARS OF OUTSTANDING
BROADCASTING NEWS REPORTING AND SERVICES TO THE ASIAN
AMERICAN COMMUNITY WITH THEIR FIRST PODCAST ON SEPTEMBER 4TH,
1976 IN SAN FRANCISCO, KATIE S.F. STARTED THEIR JOURNEY OF
BECOMING A PIONEER OF MULTI-ETHNIC AND ASIAN LANGUAGE
PROGRAMING IN THE UNITED STATES.
KATIE ASSAF LAUNCHED THE FIRST NIGHTLY LIVE CANTONESE NEWS
PACKET IN THE UNITED STATES IN 1989 AND ADDED MANDARIN LIVE
PROGRAMING IN 1991 FOR GENERATIONS OF CHINESE
AMERICANS FAMILIES THIS LADY PODCASTS HAVE BEEN A VITAL
CONNECTIONS TO LOCAL NEWS COMMUNITY ISSUES
AND INTERNATIONAL EVENTS. KATIE S.F. IT'S MORE THAN A
NEWS OUTLET. >> IT HAS BECOME A TRUSTED
COMMUNITY PARTNER THAT NEW IMMIGRANTS AND LONG TIME
RESIDENTS CAN RELY ON NAVIGATING LIFE IN THE BAY AREA
THEY HAVE CONTINUED TO PROVIDE NEWS, PUBLIC INFORMATION
AND COMMUNITY SERVICES IN DIVERSE LANGUAGE FAMILIAR TO
OUR ASIAN AMERICAN COMMUNITIES. AS WE CELEBRATE THIS MILESTONE
WE ALSO RECOGNIZE THE TIRELESS JOURNALIST, PODCASTER STAFF
COMMUNITY MEMBERS WHO GIVE OUR COMMUNITIES AN OUTLET FOR OUR
STORIES AND SUPPORT IMMIGRANT COMMUNITY AND FAMILIES TO
PARTICIPATE FULLY IN CIVIC LIFE.
CONGRATULATION KATIE S.F. FOR YOUR 50TH ANNIVERSARY AND THANK
YOU FOR YOUR LEADERSHIP YOUR SERVICES IN PROVIDING
ACCESSIBLE MULTILINGUAL MEDIA TO OUR COMMUNITIES REFLECTING
SAN FRANCISCO'S VALUE OF INCLUSIVITY AND COMMUNITY
ENGAGEMENT HERE'S TO 50 YEARS MORE OF EXCELLENT PODCASTING
AND REPORTING AND DISCUSSION. >> BUT HOLD ON, HOLD ON, HOLD
ON. OH I BELIEVE WE HAVE OTHER
SUPERVISORS WHO WANT TO WEIGH IN.
THIS WAS A GOOD COMMENDATION SUPERVISOR CHEN SUPERVISOR
SAUTER THANK YOU BOARD PRESIDENT AND THANK YOU
SUPERVISOR CHEN CONGRATULATIONS ON 50 YEARS.
>> I WANT TO THANK YOU FOR THE FACT THAT YOU AND YOUR TEAM
SEEM TO BE EVERYWHERE YOU WERE COVERING EVERY SINGLE EVENT NOT
ONLY IN SAN FRANCISCO BUT IN THE BAY AREA.
I'M SO IMPRESSED BY YOUR EXPANSIVE COVERAGE AND I HAVE
TO SAY FUN OFTEN I ONLY WILL UNDERSTAND A WORD OR TWO BUT
THERE'S SOME TIMES WHERE I'LL SEE THINGS THAT I DON'T SEE
COVERED BY ANYONE ELSE AND IT KIND OF REMINDS ME TO GO CHECK
ON SOMETHING OR IT TEACHES ME SOMETHING NEW.
SO IT'S SO SO IMPORTANT WHAT YOU'VE DONE FOR THESE 50 YEARS.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR YOUR DEDICATED WORK.
THANK YOU FOR LETTING COMMUNITY LEADERS LIKE ANNIE CHUNG HAVE
SPACE ON THE PROGRAM TO SHARE THEIR MESSAGES AS WELL.
CONGRATULATIONS AND THANK YOU SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANK YOU
PRESIDENT MAILMAN I JUST WANTED TO SAY AS SOMEONE WHO HAS SPENT
MOST OF MY CAREER WORKING WITH JOURNALISTS, ONE THING THAT
I'VE REALLY COME TO APPRECIATE IS HOW IMPORTANT THE FOURTH
ESTATE IS AND I ALWAYS ROOT FOR JOURNALISTS EVEN WHEN IT'S A
POLITICAL OR PUBLIC RELATIONS HEADACHE.
YOU KNOW, I KNOW THAT THE WORK THAT YOU DO BRINGING SUNSHINE
AND SCRUTINY TO GOVERNMENT ULTIMATELY MAKES GOVERNMENT
BETTER. SO I JUST APPRECIATE IT.
JUST KNOW THAT I'M ALWAYS ROOTING FOR JOURNALISM AND EVEN
THOUGH I YOU KNOW, I'VE DONE PLENTY OF INTERVIEWS NOT MANY
OF THEM THAT I UNDERSTAND PROBABLY WHEN IT'S BROADCAST
BUT I JUST APPRECIATE THE THE COVERAGE THAT YOU HAVE BROUGHT
TO SO MANY NEWS STORIES FOR SO MANY YEARS HERE IN SAN
FRANCISCO. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR WONG YES, I LIKE TO
THINK OF ITSELF AS WELL. I GREW UP WITH MY PARENTS
WATCHING KITESURFING IT WAS FOR MY FAMILY.
IT WAS A SOURCE OF NEWS IN ADDITION TO JUST THEM
READING THIS AND HOW DAILY EVERY DAY AND IT'S REALLY
IMPORTANT THAT WE HAVE OUR COMMUNITY ETHNIC MEDIA BECAUSE
THERE'S SO MANY STORIES ARE NOT COVERED BY MAINSTREAM MEDIA
AND THINGS THAT WE NEED TO GET OUT THERE TO TO THE CHINESE
COMMUNITY AND TO THE BROADER COMMUNITY.
AND YOU KNOW, JUST IN THE WORK THAT WE DO I CONSTANTLY SEE
KITESURFING IN OUR ETHNIC MEDIA COVERING STORIES THAT NORMALLY
OTHER OTHER MAINSTREAM SOURCES WON'T.
AND THAT'S SO IMPORTANT THAT WE'RE GETTING THAT INFORMATION
OUT THERE. >> SO THANK YOU FOR YOUR WORK.
THANK YOU. AND I WILL JUST ADD MY OWN
THANKS AND CONGRATULATIONS ON 50 YEARS OF COURSE OF PROVIDING
COVERAGE THAT'S ACCESSIBLE TO SO MANY DIFFERENT ASIAN
COMMUNITIES BUT ALSO FOR YOUR INVOLVEMENT IN THE COMMUNITY
AND SPONSORSHIP OF COMMUNITY EVENTS.
AND THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHAN FOR GIVING US THIS OPPORTUNITY
FOR SPONSORING THE RESOLUTION THAT WE WILL BE VOTING ON
LATER. >> NOW THE FLOOR IS YOURS.
>> OKAY. THANK YOU.
HI EVERYONE. I'M AN ENGLISH NEWS DIRECTOR OF
KATIE. AS OF JUNE 26TH SOME CHINESE I
GOT HOME. I'M SEEING YOU.
HEY KATIE. I HAVE SOME IN BELGIUM GAP SO
BACK IN ENGLISH IS MULTI-LANGUAGE, RIGHT?
>> TODAY I'M VERY PLEASED AND HONORED TO REPRESENT HSF
IN RECEIVING THIS COMMENDATION FROM THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS. >> OUR FOUNDER AND OWNER LELAND
LINCOLN HULL RECEIVED KT'S FS FCC LICENSE IN 1960 FIVE.
>> KATIE S.F. UNDER 26 WHEN ON ON SEPTEMBER 4TH 1976 WITH THE
MISSION TO SERVE LOCAL UNDERSERVED COMMUNITIES WITH
THIS VISION, KATIE HAS BECOME THE FIRST TELEVISION STATION
IN THE UNITED STATES TO FOCUS ON ASIAN LANGUAGE AND OTHER
ETHNICS PROGRAMS. AS SUPERVISOR CYAN CHEN SAID
IN 1989 YEARS OF BROADCASTING THE FIRST NIGHTLY LIVE LIFE
CANTONESE LANGUAGE NEWSCAST IN THE UNITED STATE AND THEN
IN 1990 ONE WE ADDED A LIVE MANDARIN LANGUAGE NEWSCAST.
>> SINCE THEN CASES OF NEWS BECOME ONE OF THE MOST TRUSTED
AND WIDELY WATCHED NEWS SOURCES IN THE CHINESE COMMUNITY.
>> KATIE S.F. JUST CELEBRATE OUR 50TH ANNIVERSARY THIS PAST
SATURDAY SEPTEMBER THE 12TH. >> IT IT'S NOT EASY FOR AN
INDEPENDENT TELEVISION STATION TO CONTINUE SERVING THE ASIAN
COMMUNITY FOR 50 YEARS. AND WE ARE VERY PROUD OF THIS
MILESTONE. CDF WILL CONTINUE TO CARRY ON
THE VISION OF OUR FOUNDER AND OWNER LILLIAN LINCOLN HALL
BY SERVING UNDERSERVED COMMUNITIES THROUGHOUT THE BAY
AREA AND GIVING THEM A VOICE. THANK YOU SAN FRANCISCO BOARD
OF SUPERVISOR FOR THIS RECOGNITION AND THANK YOU
SUPERVISOR ZION CHAN AND EVERYONE WHO HAS SUPPORTED
KATZAV THROUGHOUT THE PAST 50 YEARS.
THANK YOU. AND ALSO I NEED TO INTRODUCE
OUR PAST NEWS DIRECTOR ROSEMARIE DEWITT AND SHE IS OUR
NEWS DIRECTOR. >> SINCE BEGINNING ON 1989 210
2020, 20 1620 16 I SHOULD I SHOULD EXPLAIN.
NO, I'M OBVIOUSLY NOT TRYING TO DO NOT SPEAK CHINESE BUT WHEN
WE STARTED THE NEWSCAST OUR GENERAL MANAGER SAID YOU HAVE A
JOURNALISM BACKGROUND, YOU CAN DO IT.
SO I WAS IN A POSITION WHERE I WAS ABLE TO HIRE A TOP TALENT
OUT OF HONG KONG INCLUDING C MAILING WHO FROM HONG KONG
EVERY NIGHT SHE WAS SPEAKING TO MILLIONS OF PEOPLE IN ASIA
AND IT'S WITH THE TOP TALENT THAT WE WERE ABLE TO LAUNCH
ITSELF. AND IT'S WONDERFUL HAVING
SOMEONE LIKE AND FOLLOW IN MY FOOTSTEPS AND I'M VERY, VERY
PROUD OF HER AND PROUD OF ITSELF.
I HAD THE PRIVILEGE OF KNOWING LILLIAN HOWELL AND I KNOW SHE
WOULD BE VERY HAPPY TO KNOW THAT 50 YEARS LATER WE'RE
CARRYING OUT HER MISSION. THANK YOU VERY MUCH FOR THIS
HONOR. >> THANK YOU
. >> ALL RIGHT.
>> AND NOW COULD I INVITE NEIL DE CRUZ?
WILLIAM HATFIELD, ALL YANG JUSTIN PUNYA NEW VONG?
>> I THINK LATONYA WILLIAMS IS NOT HERE.
>> CHRIS BANKS AND STEPHEN WANG TO COME ON UP WITH ION
AND VINCE COURTNEY'S BACK THERE TO COME ON OFFENSE.
>> ALL RIGHT COLLEAGUES, TODAY IT IS MY GREAT HONOR TO PRESENT
A SPECIAL COMMENDATION TO FOUR MEMBERS OF THE CASTRO PUBLIC
WORKS PUBLIC CASTRO PUBLIC WORKS BLOCK SWEEPERS TEAM WHOSE
WORK HELPS KEEP THE CASTRO CLEAN, WELCOMING AND SAFE.
THAT IS NELLIE CRUZ, WILLIAM HATFIELD OWYANG, JUSTIN PARNIA,
NEW VONG AND LATONYA WILLIAMS AS WELL AS THE TEAM'S MANAGERS
CHRIS BANKS AND STEPHEN DWAN. I THINK LATONYA IS NOT ABLE TO
BE HERE TODAY BUT WE'RE GRATEFUL FOR HER WORK
AND RECOGNIZE HER ALONGSIDE HER COLLEAGUES TODAY.
>> THIS COMMENDATION ACTUALLY ORIGINATED WITH CASTRO
RESIDENTS WHO REACHED OUT TO OUR OFFICE TO RECOGNIZE THE
TEAM AND SHARE THEIR APPRECIATION AND FOR THE HARD
WORK AND CARE THEY BRING TO THE NEIGHBORHOOD EVERY DAY.
>> OTHER THAN THE NAME OF THE PROGRAM AS BLOCK SWEEPERS
NELLIE, WILLIAM, JUSTIN AND LATONYA DO MORE THAN SIMPLY
SWEEP THE STREETS. THEY'RE OUT IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD
EVERY DAY REMOVING ILLEGAL POSTINGS AND GRAFFITI,
ADDRESSING OVERFLOWING LITTER, WEEDING AND REPORTING ILLEGAL
DUMPING AND OTHER SAFETY CONCERNS.
THEY'RE AMONG THE CITY EMPLOYEES WHO SEE THE
NEIGHBORHOOD MOST REGULARLY AND THEIR WORK MAKES A VISIBLE
DIFFERENCE IN THE DAY TO DAY EXPERIENCE OF CASTRO RESIDENTS
AND VISITORS. NELDA HAS BEEN WITH THE
DEPARTMENT PUBLIC WORKS FOR NEARLY FOUR YEARS.
WILLIAM HAS BEEN WITH THE DEPARTMENT FOR THREE AND A HALF
YEARS AND JUSTIN AND LATONYA JOINED THE DEPARTMENT JUST
THREE MONTHS AGO. ALL FOUR LIVE HERE IN SAN
FRANCISCO. THE TEAM'S MANAGERS CHRIS
AND STEPHEN BOTH PREVIOUSLY WORKED AS BLOCK SWEEPERS
THEMSELVES. THEY HELP ENSURE THE TEAM HAS
THE EQUIPMENT AND SUPPORT THEY NEED, HANDLE ADMINISTRATIVE
RESPONSIBILITIES AND COORDINATE RESPONSE AND COORDINATE
RESPONSES TO ISSUES THAT REQUIRE ADDITIONAL ATTENTION
LIKE ILLEGAL DUMPING. THE CASTRO IS A NEIGHBORHOOD
WITH A STRONG SENSE OF COMMUNITY AND HAVING CITY
WORKERS WHO TAKE PRIDE IN CARING FOR THE STREETS
AND SIDEWALKS MAKES A REAL DIFFERENCE.
THE APPRECIATION THIS TEAM HAS RECEIVED FROM RESIDENTS IS A
REFLECTION OF THE CARE THEY PUT INTO THEIR WORK EVERY DAY.
WE WANT TO THANK YOU FOR THE WORK YOU DO EVERY DAY TO TAKE
CARE OF THE CASTRO YOU, WILLIAM, JUSTIN, LATANYA,
STEPHEN AND CHRIS AND WE WANT TO THANK THE CASTRO RESIDENTS
WHO TOOK THE TIME TO MAKE SURE OUR OFFICE KNEW ABOUT THEIR
WORK. >> WE APPRECIATE EVERYTHING YOU
DO FOR DISTRICT EIGHT AND FOR SAN FRANCISCO AND I THINK CHRIS
BANKS IS OR STEVE OR ANYONE WHOEVER AND ANYONE CAN COME UP
AND SPEAK AGAIN. OKAY.
YEAH. OKAY.
>> ALL RIGHT. GOOD AFTERNOON.
PRESIDENT MEDALLION MEMBER OF BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
AND EVERYONE HERE TODAY. MY NAME IS STEPHEN AND I AM
THE OPERATIONS SUPERVISOR FOR THE PUBLIC WORKS QUOTA PROGRAM
THAT'S BEEN CREATED SINCE 2006. >> WE ARE VERY HONORED TO BE
HERE ON BEHALF OF OUR SAN FRANCISCO PUBLIC WORKS PROGRAM
TO SAY A FEW WORDS ABOUT OUR WONDERFUL PROGRAM.
AMBASSADOR. UNFORTUNATELY JUSTIN AND MISS
TONG WASN'T ABLE TO COME TODAY AND ONE GUY IS NEARLY CRUZ
AND WILLIAM HARPER ALONGSIDE ME.
>> OF COURSE MY CAPTAIN FOR THE QUARTER PROGRAM.
I'M CHRIS BANK FIRST. THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
MADAM AND MEMBER OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AND OF COURSE
FOR THE CASTRO COMMUNITY FOR TAKING THE TIME TO RECOGNIZE
OUR TEAM TODAY. THIS RECOGNITION MEANS A LOT TO
US ALL AND OF COURSE I WANT TO CONGRATULATE MS..
CREW, MR. HATFIELD AND OF COURSE JUSTIN AND LATONYA.
WE ARE VERY PROUD OF YOU. YOU REPRESENT PUBLIC WORK
AND NOT JUST MAKE YOURSELVES LOOK GOOD OUT IN THE COMMUNITY
AND ALSO ON BEHALF OF PUBLIC WORKS AS WELL.
AND OUR AMBASSADOR ARE OUT IN THE COMMUNITY THROUGHOUT THE
CITY EVERY DAY THEY WORK WITH RESIDENTS, BUSINESSES, VISITORS
AND COMMUNITY ORGANIZATION HELPING KEEPING OUR NEIGHBORS
CLEANER, SAFER AND OF COURSE MORE WELCOMING FOR EVERYONE AS
WELL AS THE TOURISTS TO OUR CITY.
>> BUT WHAT REALLY STAND OUT IS THE WAY THEY DO THEIR WORK
EVERY DAY WITH PROFESSIONALISM AND PATIENT KINDNESS
AND GENUINE COMMITMENT TO SERVING THE COMMUNITY.
I WOULD SAY WE CURRENTLY HAVE ABOUT 100 AMBASSADOR IN THE
CITY RIGHT NOW NOT THAT WE WON'T GET RECOGNIZED OF WHAT
THEY DO THE HARD WORK, THE COMMITMENT THAT DEDICATION SO
IS VERY GRATEFUL TO HEAR THAT THE CASTRO COMMUNITY DO SEE
WHAT WE AND OUR TEAM COULD PROVIDE OUT THERE EVERY DAY.
BUT OF COURSE WE CANNOT CLEAN UP EVERYTHING OR YOU KNOW WE
JUST HAVE TO DO THE BEST WE CAN AND THAT'S WHY TODAY'S
RECOGNITION IS SO MEANINGFUL. NEARY WELL, THANK YOU FOR
EVERYTHING YOU DO. THANK YOU FOR REPRESENTING
PUBLIC WORK AND FOR THE CARE AND DEDICATION YOU BRING TO OUR
COMMUNITY EVERY DAY. >> LAST THING I WANT ALSO WANT
TO TAKE THIS OPPORTUNITY TO EXPRESS MY THOUGHTS TO ASK THE
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AND THE PUBLIC ALL COMMUNITY TO SUPPORT
CONTINUE TO SUPPORT OUR PROGRAM.
I'M NOT SURE EVERYONE KNOW ABOUT THE AMBASSADOR THEY ONLY
EMPLOY IN TERMS SHORT TERM ONE YEARS, TWO YEARS AND ASSISTS
THE OPERATIONS SUPERVISOR FOR THE QUARTER PROGRAM FOR MANY
YEARS. I WOULD JUST WANT TO ASK FOR
YOU ALL TO CONTINUE TO SUPPORT THEIR EMPLOYMENT AND KEEP KEEP
THEM EMPLOYED BECAUSE MOST OF THEM ALREADY WORRY I ONLY HAVE
ONE YEAR OR SIX MONTHS TO WORK SO IT'S VERY PEOPLE AND IT'S A
GREAT OPPORTUNITY FOR ME TODAY TO SPEAK OUT FOR THEM AS WELL.
FINALLY, THANK YOU AGAIN TO PRESIDENT MANDELA AND THE BOARD
OF SUPERVISORS FOR RECOGNIZE OUR TEAM TODAY.
CONGRATULATIONS NELLIE. WELL, WE ARE VERY PROUD OF YOU
AND WE ARE PROUD TO SERVE SAN FRANCISCO ALONG SIDE OF YOU.
>> SO THANK YOU VERY MUCH. THANK YOU ALL FOR THAT.
THANK YOU. SO IS IT OKAY TO FEEL FREE TO
HAVE AS WELL I APPRECIATE THIS AWARD.
YOU KNOW, I'M SAYING A LOT OF PEOPLE IN OUR NEIGHBORHOOD BE
VERY GRATEFUL THAT WE'RE THERE AND YOU KNOW, THEY JUST HAVE TO
SEE A SMILE EVERY DAY SO KIND OF GOES A LONG WAY.
SO I APPRECIATE THEM. APPRECIATE YOUR THANK YOU.
GOOD JOB. COME ON OVER TO STEVE AND JUST
WATCH OUT. THERE'S GOT A LITTLE SORRY WE
GOT THEM ALL. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU. FIRST PICTURE THANK SHOULD WE
TAKE CARE OF THEIR BEHALF YOU THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
ALL RIGHT. I THINK THAT TAKES US TO OUR 3
P.M. SPECIAL ORDER. >> MADAM CLERK ITEMS 41 THROUGH
46 COMPRISE THE SPECIAL ORDER AT 3 P.M..
>> ITEM 41 IS A PUBLIC HEARING OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
CONVENING A COMMITTEE OF THE WHOLE TODAY SEPTEMBER 15TH AT 3
P.M. TO HOLD THIS PUBLIC HEARING TO CONSIDER ITEMS 42
THROUGH 46 TO ADD TERRITORY TO AN APPROVING AND ANNEXATION
SUPPLEMENT TO THE AMENDED AND RESTATED INFRASTRUCTURE
FINANCING PLAN FOR THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO
INFRASTRUCTURE AND REVITALIZATION FINANCING
DISTRICT NUMBER ONE TREASURER ISLAND AS NEW PROJECT AREAS
AND TO DETERMINE OTHER MATTERS IN CONNECTION HERE WITH
SCHEDULE PURSUANT TO A RESOLUTION NUMBER 352 DASH 26
APPROVED BY THE BOARD ON JUNE 9TH 2020 SIX ITEM 42 JUST AS
IT'S THE ADDITION OF TERRITORY ADOPTION OF THE ANNEXATION
SUPPLEMENT AMENDED AND RESTATED INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCING PLAN
ITEM 43 IS THE RESOLUTION TO CALL FOR A SPECIAL ELECTION FOR
THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO INFRASTRUCTURE
AND REVITALIZATION FINANCING DISTRICT NUMBER ONE FOR
TREASURE ISLAND ITEM 44 THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO DECLARE RESULTS
OF A SPECIAL LANDOWNER ELECTION FOR CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN
FRANCISCO THE REVITALIZATION FINANCING DISTRICT NUMBER ONE
ITEM 45 THIS ORDINANCE AS TERRITORY AS NEW PROJECT AREAS
TWO AND ADOPTING ANNEXATION SUPPLEMENT OF THE AMENDED
AND RESTATED RESTATED INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCING PLAN
ITEM 46 THIS RESOLUTION MODIFIES RESOLUTION AND NUMBER
SEVEN DASH 17 TO AUTHORIZE THE ISSUANCE OF BONDS FOR THE
REVITALIZED ZATION PLAN OF THE REVITALIZATION FINANCING
DISTRICT NUMBER ONE FOR TREASURE ISLAND.
>> ALL RIGHT. THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
WE ARE NOW AS YOU DESCRIBED SITTING AS A COMMITTEE OF THE
WHOLE TO HEAR TESTIMONY ON THE ADDITION OR ANNEXATION OF
TERRITORY TO THE INFRASTRUCTURE AND REVITALIZATION FINANCING
DISTRICT FOR TREASURE ISLAND AND YERBA BUENA ISLAND AND TO
CONSIDER ADOPTION OF AN ANNEXATION SUPPLEMENT THE
AMENDED AND RESTATED INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCING PLAN
FOR THE IRS FOR THE ANNEXATION TERRITORY IS SOME OF THE
PROPERTY THAT HAS BEEN TRANSFERRED FROM THE NAVY TO
THE MASTER DEVELOPER OF THE TREASURE ISLAND PROJECT SINCE
THE FORMATION OF THE I R F D THIS IS THE FIRST OF THE
ANTICIPATED ANNEXATIONS TO THE I R F D THE ANNEXATION
SUPPLEMENT HAS BEEN PREPARED AND I MADE MADE AVAILABLE TO
THE PUBLIC AND THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS APPROVED THE
ANNEXATION SUPPLEMENT ON JULY 28TH 2026 IN ITS CAPACITY AS
THE LEGISLATIVE BODY OF THE ONLY TAXING ENTITY THAT
ALLOCATES PROPERTY TAX INCREMENT TO THE I R F D NOW
THE BOARD IN ITS CAPACITY AS THE LEGISLATIVE BODY OF THE I R
F D WILL UNDERTAKE A SERIES OF PROCEEDINGS REQUIRED BY THE
CALIFORNIA GOVERNMENT CODE IN ORDER TO ADD THE ANNEXATION
TERRITORY TO THE I R F D AND ADOPT THE ANNEXATION
SUPPLEMENT WHICH INCLUDES A PUBLIC HEARING AND THE
PRELIMINARY STEPS FOR A LANDOWNER ELECTION.
>> THIS HEARING IS NOW OPEN AND SUPERVISOR DORSEY HAS
OPENING REMARKS. >> THANK YOU PRESIDENT
RANDLEMAN. COLLEAGUES I WANT TO EXPRESS MY
SUPPORT FOR THESE ITEMS WHICH ALLOW US TO MAKE CONTINUED
AND SUSTAINED INVESTMENTS IN TREASURE ISLAND AND YERBA
BUENA ISLAND AS WE MOVE FORWARD ON THEIR DEVELOPMENT.
TREASURER ISLAND IS HOME TO AN INFRASTRUCTURE REVITALIZATION
FINANCING DISTRICT OR IRF WHICH WAS CREATED IN 2017 TO PROVIDE
FUNDING FOR BOTH ISLANDS DEVELOPMENT.
EARLIER THIS YEAR IN JULY WE HEARD AND APPROVED THE FIRST
TWO PIECES OF LEGISLATION TO KICK OFF THIS PROCESS DECLARING
THE CITY'S INTENTION TO ISSUE BONDS AND TO APPROVE THE
UPCOMING CHANGES TO THE RFD. THE RFD ALLOWS THE CITY TO
EARMARK A PORTION OF FUTURE PROPERTY TAXES ON TREASURE
ISLAND. THIS IS APPROXIMATELY 56% TO
SUPPORT THE DEVELOPMENT PROJECT SPECIFICALLY TO FUND PUBLIC
INFRASTRUCTURE AND AFFORDABLE HOUSING.
THE RFD DOES NOT RAISE TAXES. OUR VISION FOR THE ISLANDS
INCLUDED 8000 ADDITIONAL UNITS OF HOUSING BOTH AFFORDABLE
AND MARKET RATE AND HUNDREDS OF MORE ACRES OF PARKS AND OPEN
SPACE A RELIABLE AND SUSTAINABLE STREAM OF
FUNDING IS ESSENTIAL TO DELIVERING ON OUR PROMISE TO
BUILD MORE HOMES AND TO REMEDY OUR CITYWIDE HOUSING SHORTAGE.
>> TO DATE THE CITY HAS ISSUED $65 MILLION IN IRF D BONDS
REPAID BY OUR IRF DE TAXES THAT HELP TO COVER THE COSTS OF
CONSTRUCTION OF PUBLIC INFRASTRUCTURE AND AFFORDABLE
HOUSING ON TREASURE ISLAND. AT THE TIME THE RFD WAS FORMED
THE CITY INCLUDED THE FIRST PHASE OF PROPERTIES INTO THE
DISTRICT BOUNDARIES. THANKS TO THE WORK WE'VE BEEN
ABLE TO DO TO GROW AND EXPAND TIES TO THE TREASURE ISLAND
DEVELOPMENT AUTHORITY IS NOW ADDING FUTURE DEVELOPMENT
PROPERTIES. WE HAVE A LOT OF MOMENTUM
BUILDING ON TREASURE ISLAND. THE CITY IN PARTNERSHIP WITH
OUR MASTER DEVELOPER HAS DELIVERED NEARLY A THOUSAND NEW
MARKET RATE AND AFFORDABLE HOMES ON TREASURE ISLAND
IN EUROPE. BUENO ISLANDS AND ANOTHER 250
AFFORDABLE UNITS CURRENTLY IN DEVELOPMENT.
LAST YEAR TREASURE ISLAND SAW THE OPENING OF A BRAND NEW
WATERFRONT PARK CITY SIDE PARK AND THE GROUNDBREAKING OF A NEW
TRAINING CENTER FOR BAY FC THE BAY AREA NATIONAL WOMEN'S
SOCCER LEAGUE TEAM. >> WE'RE ALREADY GOING TO
QUADRUPLE THE AMOUNT OF HOUSING THAT WE'VE BEEN BUILT IN YEARS
TO COME. I WANT TO THANK THE TREASURE
ISLAND DEVELOPMENT AUTHORITY TITAN AND THE COMPTROLLER'S
OFFICE OF PUBLIC FINANCE FOR ALL OF THEIR WORK.
TO HERALD THIS I RFD ANNEXATION PROCESS THROUGH AND TO GIVE
THANKS AS WELL TO THE MAYOR'S OFFICE FOR THEIR SUPPORT AS WE
WORK TO LEGISLATE THESE ITEMS. I URGE YOU TO JOIN ME
IN SUPPORT OF THESE ITEMS TO ENSURE THE CONTINUED SUCCESS OF
OUR WORK ON TREASURE ISLAND AND YOUR ISLAND AND I THANK YOU
. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR DORSEY I BELIEVE WE HAVE ALSO WITH TREASURER
AND THE DEVELOPMENT AUTHORITY IS HERE TO PRESENT THANK YOU
PRESIDENT MANLEY AND THANK YOU SUPERVISOR DORSEY FOR THOSE
COMMENTS. GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS JAMIE CARIBBEAN CHIEF OPERATING OFFICER OF THE
TREASURE ISLAND DEVELOPMENT AUTHORITY OR TIGHTER.
TODAY I'LL BE PRESENTING ON ITEMS 42 THROUGH 46 TOGETHER
WHICH COLLECTIVELY AS A SUPERVISOR MENTIONED ADDS
PROPERTY TO THE TREASURE ISLAND INFRASTRUCTURE REVITALIZATION
FINANCING DISTRICT OR WHAT WE REFER TO AS A TREASURE ISLAND
RFD. THE FIRST TWO ITEMS A
RESOLUTION TO APPROVE THE ANNEXATION AND A RESOLUTION TO
CALL FOR A SPECIAL ELECTION ARE UP FOR APPROVAL TODAY AND THE
SUBSEQUENT THREE ITEMS A RESOLUTION TO DECLARE THE
ELECTION RESULTS AN ORDINANCE TO APPROVE THE ADDITION OF NEW
PROPERTY INTO THE IRE OF D AND APPROVE THE ANNEXATION
SUPPLEMENT TO THE INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCING PLAN
AND A RESOLUTION TO MODIFY THE ORIGINAL ORIGINAL RESOLUTION TO
ISSUE BONDS FOR THE I F D WILL BE HEARD TODAY PURSUANT TO
LEGAL PROCEDURES REQUIRED BY STATE LAW AND WILL BE CONTINUED
TO A FUTURE BOARD DATE FOR APPROVAL LATER THIS MONTH.
>> FOR MORE CONTEXT, THIS COMMITTEE OF THE WHOLE PUBLIC
HEARING IS SCHEDULE IS REQUIRED IS A REQUIRED STEP IN THE
PROCESS TO LEGALLY ADD PROPERTY INTO THE TREASURE ISLAND I RFD
CALIFORNIA I RFD STATE LAW DICTATES A PROCESS TO ADD
PROPERTIES TO AN I RFD WHICH REQUIRES A MULTI-STEP
LEGISLATIVE PROCESS AT THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS ACTING AS
A CITY'S GOVERNING BODY TO THE I RFD.
SLIDE THREE SHOWS THE PRIOR ACTIONS THAT THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS ROUS AND THE COMMITTEE HAVE TAKEN SINCE JUNE
OF THIS YEAR INCLUDING THE BOARD'S APPROVAL OF A
RESOLUTION OF INTENTION TO ADD PROPERTY INTO THE RFD UPDATE
THE INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCING PLAN AND A RESOLUTION OF
INTENTION TO ISSUE BONDS IN CONNECTION TO THE ANNEXATION
OF THIS PROPERTY. SLIDE FOUR OUTLINES THE ITEMS
BEFORE YOU TODAY AS WELL AS SUBSEQUENT ACTIONS THE BOARD IS
SCHEDULED TO HEAR AND ADOPT THROUGH EARLY OCTOBER.
THIS PROCESS WILL COMPLETE AND ALL NECESSARY LEGAL STEPS
TO ADD PROPERTY INTO THE IRF D BY THE END OF THIS CALENDAR
YEAR. >> FOR SOME BACKGROUND ON THE
TREASURE ISLAND I OF D THE ORIGINAL DISPOSITION
AND DEVELOPMENT AGREEMENT OR THE DDA APPROVED IN 2011
CONTEMPLATED THE FORMATION OF AN I IRV D WHICH WAS THEN LATER
FORMED BY THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS IN 2017.
THE I R OF D ALLOWS THE CITY TO CAPTURE AND DEDICATE A PORTION
OF THE NEW PROPERTY TAXES GENERATED BY PROPERTIES ON
TREASURE ISLAND AS A RESULT OF DEVELOPMENT.
>> THE CITY THEN ISSUES TAX INCREMENT OR IRE FEE BONDS
AGAINST THESE PROPERTY TAX REVENUES TO FINANCE BOTH PUBLIC
INFRASTRUCTURE SUPPORTING THE PROJECT AS WELL AS AFFORDABLE
HOUSING LOCATED ON TREASURE ISLAND AND ONE ISLAND.
THE IRE OF D IS FORMED ALWAYS CONTEMPLATED EVENTUALLY ADDING
NEW PROPERTIES INTO THE DISTRICT BOUNDARIES AS NEW
DEVELOPMENT OCCURS IN ORDER TO CAPTURE PROPERTY TAX GROWTH
IN THEIR INITIAL STAGES OF DEVELOPMENT.
>> DUE TO CERTAIN CONSTRAINTS WITHIN THE EYES OF THE LAW, THE
RFP WAS ORIGINALLY FORMED ONLY INCLUDING PROPERTIES WITHIN
STAGE ONE OF THE DEVELOPMENT BOUNDARIES.
>> THE NEXT SLIDE INCLUDING ALL OF THE BLUE PARCELS ON WHIDBEY
AND THE WATERFRONT FACING PARCELS ON TREASURE ISLAND
FACING THE S.F. CITY SKYLINE. >> THE SUBJECT OF THIS
LEGISLATION IS TO CONTINUE THE PROCESS OF ADDING STAGE TWO
PROPERTIES INDICATED IN THE RED BOX ON SLIDE SIX INTO THE LEGAL
BOUNDARIES OF THE IRE OF D. SLIDE SEVEN HERE SHOWS A CLOSER
LOOK OF THESE PROPERTIES DEFINED AS PROJECT AREAS F, G,
H AND I WHICH ARE GROUPED BASED ON THE TIMING OF THESE PARCELS
TIMING OF WHICH THESE PARCELS ARE LIKELY TO BE DEVELOPED.
AS MENTIONED EARLIER, A SUBSET OF THIS LEGISLATION BEFORE YOU
INCLUDES A RESOLUTION AND ORDINANCE TO APPROVE THE
ADDITION OF PROPERTY INTO THE OF D AS WELL AS AN ADOPTION OF
AN ANNEXATION SUPPLEMENT TO THE INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCING PLAN.
THE ANNEXATION SUPPLEMENT INCLUDES FIVE PRIMARY
COMPONENTS A MAP AND LEGAL DESCRIPTION OF THE ANNEXATION
AREA. >> A DESCRIPTION OF THE
FACILITIES REQUIRED TO SERVE THE DEVELOPMENT PROPOSED IN THE
ANNEXATION AREA. A FINDING OF THE EIR FOR
IMPROVEMENTS ARE OF COMMUNITY WIDE SIGNIFICANCE.
A SUMMARY OF THE PROJECTED TAX INCREMENT COMMITTED TO THE
AREA. >> A TERM OF THE F D A PLAN FOR
FINANCING THE F D IMPROVEMENTS AND A PLAN FOR FINANCING ANY
POTENTIAL COSTS INCURRED BY REIMBURSING THE DEVELOPER.
AND LASTLY AN ANALYSIS OF THE COSTS TO THE CITY PROVIDING
FACILITIES AND SERVICES TO THIS ANNEXATION AREA AND AN ANALYSIS
OF THE PROJECTED FISCAL IMPACT OF THE TAX REVENUES ALLOCATED
FROM THIS AREA. >> THE LEGISLATION BEFORE YOU
INCLUDES A RESOLUTION TO CALL ON AN R AND A RESOLUTION TO
DECLARE THE RESULTS OF A MAILED BALLOT ELECTION TO THE LAND
OWNER ELECTORS LOCATED WITHIN THE I R F D.
THEY WILL VOTE ON AN EDITION OF THE PROPERTIES WHICH WE REFER
TO AS PROJECT AREAS F, G, H AND I AN ADOPTION AND APPROVAL
OF THE ANNEXATION SUPPLEMENT AND ESTABLISHMENT OF $192
MILLION OF AN ANNUAL APPROPRIATIONS LIMIT AND THE
ADDITION OF $520 MILLION IN BOND ISSUANCES BASED ON THE
PROJECTED NET AVAILABLE INCREMENT GENERATED FROM THE
ADDITIONAL PROJECT AREAS F THROUGH II THIS AMOUNT WILL BE
ADDED TO THE CURRENT AUTHORITY TO ISSUE $780 MILLION IN BONDS
RELATED TO THE INITIAL PROJECT AREAS A3 AFTER THIS MAILED
BALLOT ELECTION THE DIRECTOR OF ELECTIONS WILL FILE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS WITH THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS A CANVASS
AND STATEMENT OF RESULTS OF THE ELECTION REGARDING THIS SPECIAL
ELECTION WHICH WILL BE UP FOR APPROVAL ON SEPTEMBER 20TH
NINTH. >> LASTLY, THE LEGISLATION ALSO
INCLUDES A RESOLUTION TO MODIFY RESOLUTION 717 WHICH WAS
ORIGINALLY PASSED IN 2017 TO REFLECT ADDITIONAL AUTHORITY TO
ISSUE BONDS FOR THE I R D AS A RESULT OF ADDING ADDITIONAL
TERRITORY. >> THE TOTAL BOND AUTHORIZATION
WILL INCREASE BY 520 MILLION FROM THE 780 MILLION CURRENTLY
APPROVED FOR A TOTAL MAXIMUM AGGREGATE PRINCIPAL AMOUNT OF
1.3 BILLION. THIS ADDITIONAL BONDING
CAPACITY IS BASED ON THE ON THE PROJECTED NET AVAILABLE
INCREMENT WHICH IS GENERATED FROM THE PROJECT AREAS F
THROUGH II. AS A REMINDER, THE BONDS ARE
REPAID BY PROPERTY TAX REVENUES ALLOCATED BY THE I R D
INCLUDING REVENUES IN BOTH PROJECT HERE IS A THROUGH G
AND THE NEW PROJECT AREAS F THROUGH Y.
>> LASTLY TITLE AND THE COMPTROLLER'S OFFICE ARE
REQUIRED TO SEEK FUTURE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS APPROVAL FOR THE
ISSUANCE OF BONDS AGAINST THIS MAXIMUM BONDING CAPACITY.
>> AND WITH THAT I'LL CONCLUDE MY PRESENTATION AND I AND STAFF
FROM THE COMPTROLLER'S OFFICE OF PUBLIC FINANCE ARE AVAILABLE
TO ANSWER ANY QUESTIONS. >> I DO NOT SEE ANY QUESTIONS
FROM COLLEAGUES. THANK YOU FOR YOUR PRESENTATION
. MADAM CLERK, DO WE HAVE YOU
RECEIVED ANY WRITTEN PROTESTS? >> WE HAVE NOT RECEIVED ANY
WRITTEN PROTESTS. >> MR. PRESIDENT, THANK YOU FOR
THAT CONFIRMATION. SO LET'S OPEN PUBLIC COMMENT ON
THIS MATTER ALLOTTING TWO MINUTES PER SPEAKER.
ALL RIGHT. IF YOU ARE HERE FOR THIS
HEARING ON THE TREASURE ISLAND RFD, PLEASE COME OVER TO YOUR
RIGHT HAND SIDE OF THE CHAMBER. >> ALL RIGHT.
SING NO ONE GET UP IN THE PUBLIC GALLERY.
LET'S GO TO THE REMOTE PUBLIC CALLERS TO THE STAFF.
ARE THERE ANY CALLERS FOR THIS PARTICULAR ITEM?
FOR THESE ITEMS LET'S SAY ITEMS 42 THROUGH 40 SIX WHICH IS
DOUBLE CHECKING, MR. PRESIDENT. >> OKAY.
>> I HAVE THE RIGHT TO DO SO. THERE ARE NO CALLERS, MR.
PRESIDENT. >> ALL RIGHT.
PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW CLOSED. >> I DON'T SEE ANYONE WANTING
TO SAY ANYTHING AT THIS POINT. >> SO THIS HEARING HAS BEEN
HELD AND IS NOW FILED. >> OKAY.
SO WE NOW CONSIDER THE LEGISLATION ASSOCIATED WITH THE
IRS IN TWO SEPARATE VOTES. >> THE FIRST TWO RESOLUTIONS
ITEMS 42 AND 43 WILL BE CONSIDERED FOR ADOPTION.
>> AND THEN WE WOULD CONTINUE THE REMAINING ITEMS 44 THROUGH
46 TO THE SEPTEMBER 29TH BOARD OF SUPERVISORS MEETING.
AND SO WITH THAT, MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEMS
42 AND 43 AND ITEMS 42 AND 43 SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER EYES SUPERVISOR MAHMUD MAHMOOD EYES
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I RANDLEMAN EYES SUPERVISOR
MELGAR MELGAR EYES SUPERVISOR SARDAR SADR EYES SUPERVISOR
CHERYL CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYE
AND SUPERVISOR HUANG WONG EITHER ARE 11 EYES WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANK
YOU PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN I DON'T KNOW IF THE MOTION HAS BEEN
MADE BUT I'D LIKE TO MAKE A MOTION AT THIS TIME IF IT HAS A
IF IT'S NOT ON THE FLOOR TO FOUR ITEMS 4445 AND 46 TO BE
CONTINUED TO SEPTEMBER 29TH. >> THAT IS PERFECT.
>> NOW I NEED A SECOND WHICH I'M GETTING FROM SUPERVISOR
CHEN AND WITH THAT COLLEAGUES I THINK WE CAN TAKE THAT MOTION
WITHOUT OBJECTION WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS
AND ORDINANCE ARE CONTINUED TO SEPTEMBER 29TH.
>> MADAM CLERK. I THINK THAT TAKES US BACK TO
ITEM 37. >> THAT IS CORRECT, MR.
PRESIDENT. ITEM 37 WAS REFERRED WITHOUT
RECOMMENDATION FROM THE BUDGET AND FINANCE COMMITTEE.
ITEM 37 IS A RESOLUTION TO AUTHORIZE THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENT TO ENTER INTO THE FIRST AMENDMENT TO THE
AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE CITY AND COUNTY AND OPEN GOV INC FOR
PERMITTING SOFTWARE PRODUCTS AND SERVICES TO INCREASE THE
AGREEMENT BY 33 MILLION FOR A TOTAL AMOUNT OF 38.9 MILLION
AND TO EXTEND THE TERM FOR SIX MONTHS FROM SEPTEMBER 30TH 2026
FOR A TOTAL TERM OF OCTOBER 1ST 2025 THROUGH SEPTEMBER 30TH
2031. >> SUPERVISOR CHEN THANK YOU
PRESIDENT. MAN AND COLLEAGUE I WANT TO
BEGIN WHAT I WANT TO ONCE AGAIN THANK SUPERVISOR FIELDER FOR
CALLING THE HEARING ON THIS CONTRACT.
DURING THE HEARING WHAT MAKE VERY CLEAR IS AND ALSO DURING
THE FOUR HOURS THAT CAME AFTER IS THAT MANY OF THE ISSUES THAT
WE HAVE IDENTIFIED COULD HAVE BEEN AVOIDED IF WE SLOWED DOWN
AND COMMUNICATED MORE TRANSPARENTLY AND I UNDERSTAND
THE ARGUMENT THAT WE CANNOT LET PERFECT BE THE ENEMY BE THE
ENEMY OF GOOD AND SOMETIMES OUR CITY PROCESS CAN TAKE MORE TIME
. HOWEVER, HAD THIS CONTRACT GONE
THROUGH A STANDARD A VERY STANDARDIZED PROCUREMENT
PROCESS, WE WOULD KNOW THE COMPLETE COSTS OF THIS PROJECT
TO THE CITY. >> WE CLEAR PERFORMANCE METRICS
AND TRANSPARENT TIMELINE TIMELINE NOT JUST FOR THE
DEVELOPMENT AND BUILD OUT OF THE APPLICATION BUT FOR THE
INTEGRATION OF MANY CITY DEPARTMENTS THAT ARE GOING TO
BE IMPACTED BY THE IMPLEMENTATION OF PERMIT F THE
LACK OF TRANSPARENCY, THE LACK OF COMMUNICATION AND THE LACK
OF URGENCY TO IMPLEMENT CHECKS AND BALANCES.
HAS ERODED PUBLIC TRUST CREATING FRICTIONS BETWEEN
DEPARTMENTS AND RAISED CONCERNS ABOUT DEPARTMENTS ABILITY TO
EXECUTE THIS CONTRACT. >> I SAID DURING THE HEARING
LAST WEEK THAT I WOULD NOT VOTE FOR THIS CONTRACT AS IT WAS
WRITTEN. WHY I WOULD PREFER TO AMEND HIS
CONTRACT TO MATCH THE BUDGET AND LEGISLATIVE ANALYST
ANALYST'S PROPOSAL. I'M GRATEFUL TO THE DEPARTMENT
AND ALSO TO THE MAYOR'S OFFICE FOR COMING TO THE TABLE
AND NEGOTIATING A NEW CONTRACT THAT CAN ALL THAT WE ALL CAN
LIVE WITH. >> THE DA'S CONTRACT GIVES THE
DEPARTMENT ENOUGH FLEXIBILITY TO CONTINUE EXECUTING THE
DEVELOPMENT AND INVENTORY AND IMPLEMENTATION OF PERMIT
S.F. BUT ALSO GIVES THE BOARD STRONGER OVERSIGHT
AND ACCOUNTABILITY TOWARDS. I WANT TO ALSO THANK SUPERVISOR
DORSEY. WE ADDED BACK TO TERMINATION OF
CONVENIENCE LANGUAGE DURING THE BUDGET AND FINANCE COMMITTEE
PROCESS WHICH ALLOWS US TO TERMINATE THE CONTRACT WITH
EASY AND FLEXIBILITY IF NEEDED. AFTER THIS ITEM WAS MOVED TO A
COMMITTEE WITHOUT RECOMMENDATION AND I WANT TO
THANK A WORD THAT MY OFFICE HAS DONE WITH A SUPPORT FROM ALL MY
COLLEAGUES. WE HAVE ALSO NEGOTIATED THE
CONTRACT DOWN FROM A FIVE YEAR EXTENSION TO A THREE YEAR
EXTENSION. WE REDUCED IT TO TOTAL NOT TO
EXCEED AMOUNT DOWN FROM 38.9 MILLIONS TO 28 MILLION.
THIS REPRESENTS A $22 MILLION CONTRACT TO BE SPENDING OVER
THE THREE YEAR EXTENSION. FIRST I AM DIRECTING THE BALLET
AND THE COMPTROLLER'S OFFICE TO FLAG THE THIRD YEAR OF THIS
CONTRACT FOR BUDGET RESERVED DURING THIS UPCOMING BUDGET
AND APPROPRIATION CYCLE. THIS ACCOUNTS FOR 7.4 MILLIONS
OF THE TOTAL 22 MILLION INCREASE DURING THE NEXT BUDGET
PROCESS. THE BUDGET AND APPROPRIATIONS
COMMITTEE CAN DECIDE AFTER HEARING WITH PRESENTATIONS FROM
THE DEPARTMENT WHETHER OR NOT WE WANT TO APPROPRIATE THE
FINAL 7 MILLION SUM FROM THE RESERVE.
>> THIS CHANGES WILL SAVE TAXPAYERS OVER 10 MILLION
DURING OUR CITY'S ONGOING DEFICITS AND BY GIVING THE
BOARD REAL ACCOUNTABILITY TOOLS WE CAN ENSURE THAT THE
PERMITTING STAFF REFORM WHEN SORELY NEEDED IN IMPLEMENTING
BUT IMPLEMENTED CORRECTLY. SAN FRANCISCANS DESERVE A WORLD
CLASS PERMITTING SYSTEM THAT WILL LAST DECADES AND SAVE
RATHER THAN COST US TIME AND MONEY.
>> THIS AMENDMENT GIVES US THE LEVER TO MAKE SURE THAT THIS
CONTRACT LEADS TO OUTCOME. ADDITIONAL I'M INTRODUCING A
HEARING REQUEST LATER TODAY BY PROVIDING ADDITIONAL OVERSIGHT
AND TRANSPARENCY OVER THIS CONTRACT.
I WANT TO THANK THE BUDGET AND LEGISLATIVE ANALYST'S TEAM
BOTH FOR THEIR WORK AND COMPLETE AUDIT ON THE WAY
THIS CONTRACT WAS EXECUTED AS WELL AS WELL AS MANY HOURS THAT
AS WELL AS MANY HOURS OF THE WORK THAT THEY HAVE PUT IN IN
SUPPORTING US AS WE ATTEMPT TO NEGOTIATE A BETTER CONTRACT.
>> I ALSO WANT TO THANK MY LEGISLATIVE AIDE JACKIE PRAGER
FOR HER TIRELESS WORK ON THIS PROJECT.
I HAVE SHARED SOME OF THE AMENDMENTS AND I ALSO
RESPECTFULLY REQUEST YOUR SUPPORT ON THESE AMENDMENTS.
WITH THAT I WOULD LIKE TO MAKE A MOTION TO AMEND THIS
RESOLUTION WITH THE FOLLOWING CHANGE.
PAGE ONE LINE TO CHANGE $38,965,985.92 TO
$28,018,982.28. PAGE 196.
>> CHANGE 33 MILLIONS $65,985.92 TO 22 MILLIONS 11
118,000 AND $982.28. >> ALSO CHANGE 30 EIGHT
MILLIONS $965,985.92 TO 28 MILLIONS $18,982.28.
>> PAGE 197 CHANGE 60 MONTHS TO 36 MONTHS.
PAGE ONE LINE EIGHT CHANGE 2031 TO 2020 LINE.
PAGE TWO LINE 17 CHANGE 2031 TO 2029.
>> PAGE TWO NINE 18 CHANGE $38,965,985.92 TO 28 MILLIONS.
$18,928. SORRY 28 MILLIONS $18,982.28.
>> PAGE TWO 921 CHANGE 60 MONTHS TO 36 MONTHS.
>> CHANGE 38 MILLIONS $965,985.92 TO 28 MILLIONS
18,920 $982.28. >> THINK THERE IS A MOTION FROM
SUPERVISOR CHEN AND A SECOND BY SUPERVISOR CHAN AND WE WILL
CONTINUE DOWN THE QUEUE. SUPERVISOR FIELDER THANKS
PRESIDENT OF MANAGEMENT. >> FIRST OFF I WANT TO THANK
SHEILA CHENG HANG IT IN MY OFFICE FOR STAFF AND ME ON THIS
ITEM. COLLEAGUES WE HAD A HEARING ON
THE OPEN GOVT CONTRACT TWO WEEKS AGO.
>> TYPICALLY CITY DEPARTMENTS COMPETITIVELY BID LARGE
CONTRACTS TO ENSURE THE CITY AND THE PEOPLE OF SAN FRANCISCO
WHO ENTRUST US WITH THEIR PUBLIC DOLLARS ARE GETTING THE
BEST DEAL. THE PERMANENCE OF CONTRACT
HOWEVER WAS NOT COMPETITIVELY BID.
TO BETTER UNDERSTAND HOW THE CONTRACT WAS PROCURED
AND WHETHER BEST PRACTICES IN CONTRACTING WERE FOLLOWED, I
ASKED THE BUDGET AND LEGISLATIVE ANALYST TO
ASSESS THE CONTRACTS PROCUREMENT.
THE BLR ISSUED A REPORT IN JUNE WITH KEY FINDINGS
AND RECOMMENDATIONS AS THEY FOUND THAT THE OPEN GOV
SELECTION PROCESS DID NOT VIOLATE CITY REQUIREMENTS.
HOWEVER, IT DID NOT CONFORM TO BEST PRACTICES OR TYPICAL CITY
PRACTICE IN PROCUREMENT. >> THERE IS NO STANDARD
EVALUATION CRITERIA, NO PROPER GUARDRAILS IN PLACE TO MITIGATE
CONCERNS OF CONFLICTS OF INTERESTS AND NO TRANSPARENT
CRITERIA FOR VENDORS TO HONE THEIR PROPOSALS.
>> THIS WOULD HAVE ALL BEEN A PART OF A REAL REQUEST FOR
PROPOSAL PROCESS. IN OTHER WORDS, A COMPETITIVE
BID. HOMELESS SERVICE PROVIDERS ARE
HELD TO HIGHER STANDARDS AND COMPETITIVE BIDS AND OPEN
GOV WAS SUBJECT TO. SINCE THEN WE LEARNED TO NEWS
REPORTS THAT PERMIT US ENOUGH LEADERSHIP AND THE MAYOR HAVE
SAID OPEN GOAL IS EXCEEDING THEIR GOALS.
WHILE DATA SUGGESTS THEY'RE ACTUALLY LAGGING PERMITS, US
GOAL WAS TO HAVE THE OPEN GOV SYSTEM TURNAROUND PERMITS
IN TWO DAYS. ACCORDING TO THE STANDARD WHICH
REVIEWED DATA AVAILABLE ON DATA SET IN MAY JUST 3% OF FIRE
PERMITS WERE MEETING THAT GOAL .
>> MEANWHILE ONLY 36% OF BUILDING PERMITS FOR DOOR
SIDING AND WINDOW REPLACEMENTS WERE REACHING THAT BENCHMARK.
DUE DATE PROCESSING RATES AS OF AUGUST 31ST HAVE REMAINED FLAT
4% FOR FIRE PERMITS AND 38% FOR BUILDING PERMITS ACCORDING TO
DATA OBTAINED BY THE STANDARD. >> ON TOP OF THAT PERMITS HAVE
INTENDED TO DELIVER 15 PERMIT TYPES BY MARCH 16TH BY MAY IT
HAD COMPLETED ONLY SEVEN. >> TWO SEPARATE LOCAL OUTLETS
HAVE SPOKEN WITH CITY WORKERS AND FORMER OPEN GOVT EMPLOYEES
AS HAVE I WHO HAVE SAID THE DELAYS ARE UNSURPRISING AS OPEN
GOV HAS BEEN AWARE THAT DEADLINES WOULD LIKELY BE
MISSED DUE TO THE PROJECT'S COMPLEXITY.
A FORMER DEPARTMENT EMPLOYEE EVEN TOLD THE STANDARD THAT HE
LEFT HIS JOB BECAUSE HE WAS CONCERNED THAT PERMANECER
OFFICIALS WERE INTIMIDATING CITY WORKERS INTO STAYING QUIET
ABOUT THE SNAGS HIT WITH OPEN GOV IMPLEMENTATION.
AND ACCORDING TO MISSION LOCAL WORKERS HAVE SAID OPEN GOV IS
STILL ONLY BEING APPLIED AS SIMPLER TASKS AND QUOTE WHILE
OPEN GOV IS EVENTUALLY SUPPOSED TO CONSOLIDATE THE CITY'S
PERMITTED REDUNDANCIES UNDER ONE PLATFORM THREE WORKERS FROM
SEPARATE DIFFERENT FROM THREE DIFFERENT DEPARTMENTS WHO SPOKE
TO MISSION LOCAL SAID THEIR TEAMS STILL USE THE OLD SYSTEM
SIMULTANEOUSLY WITH OPEN GOV. THAT'S BECAUSE OPEN GOV THEY
SAID STILL HIT SNAGS. IT CANNOT HANDLE ANCILLARY
REQUIREMENTS TIED TO SOME BASIC PERMITS AND PAPERWORK FORCING
CITY STAFFERS TO ALSO WORK WITH ANTIQUATED SYSTEM OPEN GOV WAS
MEANT TO SUPPLANT A TIME CONSUMING AND TEDIOUS PROCESS.
>> I WANT TO MAKE ONE THING CLEAR I'M NOT QUESTIONING
WHETHER SAN FRANCISCO SHOULD HAVE AN INTEGRATED BEST
IN CLASS AND CORRUPTION FREE PERMITTING SYSTEM IMPROVING THE
PUBLIC'S EXPERIENCE WITH THE CITY PERMITTING IS ABSOLUTELY
VALUABLE. I AM HOWEVER QUESTIONING
WHETHER WE GOT THE BEST DEAL FOR THIS CONTRACT AND ARE GOING
TO GET THAT IN A MULTIYEAR CONTRACT EXTENSION WITHOUT
CLEAR DELIVERABLES BEYOND MARCH 2027.
>> YES, THE PUBLIC SHOULD KNOW THAT IN THIS CONTRACT EXTENSION
WE ONLY HAVE CLEAR DELIVERABLES UNTIL MARCH 2027 ONE MINUTE
PERMIT AS OTHERS TELLING US OPEN GOV IS EXCEEDING THEIR
TARGETS AND THE NEXT THAT THEY'RE STRUGGLING BECAUSE OF
STAFFING. EITHER YOU'RE HITTING YOUR
GOALS OR YOU'RE NOT. IT CAN'T BE BOTH.
>> THREE YEARS IS MORE REASONABLE THAN FIVE BUT UNTIL
PERMANENT STUFF GETS A FIRM HANDLE ON ITS OPERATIONS
AND SETS MORE CONCRETE DELIVERABLES FOR OPEN GOVT, THE
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS HAS NO BUSINESS EXPANDING THIS
CONTRACT BEYOND THE DOJ RECOMMENDED ONE YEAR.
>> CHAIR DORSEY THANK YOU PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN.
SO COLLEAGUES AS YOU KNOW WE OCCASIONALLY FROM THE BUDGET
COMMITTEE SEND THINGS OUT WITHOUT RECOMMENDATION
AND SOMETIMES THAT MEANS THERE'S A LIVE CONTROVERSY THAT
WE FEEL WE SHOULD HAVE A DISCUSSION AT THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS AND I THINK THAT'S A COURTESY THAT THE BUDGET
COMMITTEE OWES TO ALL OF OUR COLLEAGUES SINCE YOU KNOW, THE
POWER OF THE PURSE STRINGS IS A LEGISLATIVE FUNCTION FOR ALL OF
US. I WAS PREPARED TO VOTE FOR THIS
BUT I AM ACTUALLY REALLY GRATEFUL THAT WE GOT TO AN
AGREEMENT THAT I THINK HOPEFULLY WILL WIN MORE SUPPORT
THAN IT MIGHT HAVE OTHERWISE. AND FOR THAT I REALLY DO WANT
TO COMMEND VICE CHAIR CHEN FOR ROLLING UP HER SLEEVES
AND FINDING COMMON GROUND ON THIS AS WELL FOR THE MAYOR'S
OFFICE AND I KNOW THERE WERE SOME CONSIDERATIONS THAT I TOOK
SERIOUSLY AND UNDERSTAND THAT SOMETIMES THERE'S THERE'S A
CASE TO MAKE FOR A LONGER CONTRACT SOMETIMES THERE'S A
CASE TO MAKE FOR A SHORTER CONTRACT TO THE EXTENT THE
SHORTER ONE IS A SHORTER LEASH. I THINK THAT'S SOMETHING THAT
THERE'S MORE COMFORT LEVEL HERE AT THE BOARD WITH.
I WILL SAY AT THE BUDGET COMMITTEE I BROUGHT UP AN
EXAMPLE THAT I SAW IN MY TIME AT CITY HALL FOR A MIDDLEWARE
SOLUTION CALLED JUSTICE. THAT WAS THE JUSTICE TRACKING
INFORMATION SYSTEM THAT ENDED UP I THINK IT WAS $32 MILLION
OVER DECADES THAT WE SPENT ON SOMETHING THAT TO MY KNOWLEDGE
STILL DOESN'T WORK. AND I WILL SAY THAT THE LESSON
OF THAT WAS THAT THERE WAS NOT STRONG EXECUTIVE LEADERSHIP.
IT WAS MULTIPLE AGENCIES INCLUDING MULTIPLE ELECTED
OFFICIALS AND THE DISTRICT ATTORNEY IN THE SHERIFF'S
DEPARTMENT. >> IN A WEIRD WAY I'M ACTUALLY
ENCOURAGED AND OPTIMISTIC THAT THIS IS A THIS IS A SOFTWARE
ENDEAVOR THAT IS STARTING OUT WITH A LOT OF SCRUTINY AND I
THINK THAT BODES WELL FOR ITS SUCCESS.
I THINK EVERYBODY IS ON NOTICE THAT THIS IS SOMETHING THAT WE
EXPECT TO WORK AND WE'RE NOT GOING TO HAVE A LOT OF PATIENCE
FOR THINGS THAT DON'T. SO I THINK ULTIMATELY FOR JUST
FROM MY OWN PERSPECTIVE SOMEBODY WHO'S SEEN THE GOOD
THINGS AND BAD THINGS HAPPEN IN CITY HALL, I THINK WE'RE
SETTING OURSELVES UP IT'S WORTH IT'S WORTH THE PROCESS THAT
WE'RE GOING THROUGH AND THE SCRUTINY THAT WE'RE BRINGING
AND I AM HOPEFUL THAT THIS IS GOING TO BE SOMETHING THAT WE
DON'T LIVE TO REGRET AND THAT WE ALL LOOK BACK ON AND SAY
AREN'T WE GLAD WE BROUGHT SCRUTINY TO THIS AND NOW WE'RE
ALL OF OUR PERMITS ARE GETTING APPROVED AND IN AN EXPEDITED
WAY. SO I AM HAPPY TO SUPPORT THESE
THESE AMENDMENTS THAT SUPERVISOR CHEN HAS PROPOSED
AND I HOPE WE CAN PASS THIS SURPRISE MELGAR THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU, PRESIDENT. I JUST WANTED TO START OUT BY
THANKING MY COLLEAGUES IN ON THE BUDGET COMMITTEE AND ALSO
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FOR CALLING THE HEARING.
>> I PARTICULARLY WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR CHEN FOR HER WORK ON
THIS. >> SHE GOT US TO A PLACE OF
AGREEMENT AND SHE DID SO WITH GRACE AND TALENT.
>> SO THANK YOU SO MUCH SUPERVISOR CHEN FOR YOUR
LEADERSHIP AND HARD WORK. >> I ALSO WANT TO THANK SARA
DENNIS PHILLIPS AND LIZ WARRY IN THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT FOR
ALL OF THEIR WORK AND YOU KNOW, I WANTED TO PROVIDE JUST SOME
REMARKS BECAUSE I HAVE A LOT OF HISTORY WITH THIS ISSUE.
THIS THIS STORY STARTED WAY LONGER THAN A COUPLE OF YEARS
AGO WHEN OUR MAYOR DECIDED TO TAKE THIS ON.
I SEE JARED DRESSLER HERE SITTING IN THE FRONT ROW AND I
REMEMBER VERY CLEARLY WHEN I WAS THE BUILDING INSPECTION
COMMISSIONER THERE WAS A GRAND JURY INVESTIGATION ON OUR
FAILURE TO IMPLEMENT AN INTEGRATED TRANSPARENT SYSTEM
AND WE SPEND 12 YEARS IN MILLIONS OF DOLLARS TRYING
TO IMPLEMENT A SELLER IN FAILED .
AND YOU KNOW THIS STORY OF USING DIFFERENT SYSTEMS
IN PERMITTING AND IN SOME AREAS USING PAPER WHICH EASILY GETS
LOST OR DAMAGED YOU KNOW REALLY LED TO A LOT OF OUR FAILURES
IN THE PERMITTING SYSTEM. SO I LIKE SUPERVISE.
SIR FIELDER STATED I'M EAGER TO HAVE AN OPEN TRANSFER PARENT
SEAMLESS WAY OF LOOKING AT OUR INFORMATION ON BUILDING WHERE
ANYONE IN THE PUBLIC WHO'S USING THE SYSTEM CAN LOOK
IN AND SEE WHERE THEY'RE AT BUT ALSO THAT INTEGRATES ALL THE
VERY COMPLICATED FUNCTIONS OF OUR CITY ON THE BACK END.
SO I THINK WE ALL WANT THE SAME GOAL WE'RE ALL THERE.
I THINK IT'S THE HOW THAT WE ARE HAVING PERHAPS A FEW
DIFFERENCES OF OPINION BUT LIKE I SAID THIS IS THE BEAUTY OF
OUR REPRESENTATIVE DEMOCRACY IN SAN FRANCISCO THAT THE BOARD
OF SUPERVISORS IN ITS ROLE IN ITS CAPACITY OF OVERSIGHT
CAN SHAPE THESE, YOU KNOW, THINGS SO THAT WE CAN ENSURE
THAT WE ARE GOING FORWARDS AND NOT BACKWARDS, THAT WE CAN
BE GUIDED BY OUR ALL OF OUR EXPERIENCES AND YOU KNOW, THE
THINGS THAT WE BRING TO THE TABLE TO MAKE SURE THAT WE MEET
OUR RESPONSIBILITY GOING FORWARD.
SO AGAIN THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHEN FOR THE THIS WORK FOR
GETTING US TO A GOOD PLACE. I WILL BE SUPPORTING YOUR
AMENDMENT AND SUPPORTING THE CONTRACT AND I REALLY LOOK
FORWARD TO SUPPORTING THE STAFF AT THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT TO
MAKE THIS A SUCCESS FOR EVERYONE FOR YOUR STAFF, FOR
THE PUBLIC, FOR THE USERS AND TO MOVE BEYOND WHERE WE'VE
BEEN FOR SO MANY YEARS OF NOT BEING ABLE TO SEE PAST OUR
DIFFERENCES TO IMPLEMENT A SYSTEM THAT REALLY WORKS IN THE
BEST CITY OF THE COUNTRY THE ONE THAT SHOULD BE PUTTING OUT
ITS MOST MODERN SUCCESSFUL USER FRIENDLY EMAIL SYSTEM FOR
PERMITS. >> THANK YOU SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD
THANK YOU PRESIDENT GENTLEMAN. COLLEAGUES I WANT TO SPEAK ON
THE LEGISLATION BEFORE US REGARDING THE OPEN UP CONTRACT
AND IN SUPPORT OF THE AMENDMENTS PROPOSED BY
SUPERVISOR CHEN. >> MUCH HAS ALREADY BEEN SAID
ABOUT THE PROCESS TO APPROVE THIS CONTRACT.
THE FOCUS OF MY COMMENTS ARE NOT ON THE PROCESS BUT ON A
GOAL LIKE SUPERVISOR MELGAR MENTIONED THAT WE ALL CAN AGREE
ON WHICH IS HOW DO WE ENSURE THAT WE ARE DELIVERING ON THE
BEST SOFTWARE FOR SAN FRANCISCANS TO ADDRESS OUR
HOUSING CRISIS. WE SHOULD RECOGNIZE THAT
BECAUSE I BELIEVE ALL OF US HERE BELIEVE THAT OUR CURRENT
PERMITTING SOFTWARE IS LACKING AND A BOTTLENECK TO APPROVING
HOUSING PERMITS. I'M ALIGNED WITH OUR MAYOR THAT
THIS PROCESS NEEDS TO BE IMPROVED TO ENSURE WE MEET OUR
HOUSING GOALS BUT IT IS IN THAT ALIGNMENT THAT I BELIEVE IT IS
OUR ROLE AS A BOARD TO PROVIDE ACCOUNTABILITY AND OVERSIGHT TO
ENSURE THE GOALS OF THE SOFTWARE ARE BEING MET.
>> MORE SPECIFICALLY, OUR JOB AS A BOARD IS TO ASSESS WHETHER
THE CONTRACTS THAT COME BEFORE US ARE READY FOR PRIME TIME
AND IF NOT HOW MUCH MORE TIME IS NEEDED TO GET THERE.
A FIVE YEAR COMMITMENT MAKES SENSE FOR A PRODUCT THAT HAS
BEEN PROVEN BY ITSELF. A SHORTER RENEWABLE TERM MAKES
SENSE FOR ONE THAT HASN'T YET. OVER THE PAST SEVERAL WEEKS MY
OFFICE HAS DONE DUE DILIGENCE, SPOKE WITH THE MAYOR'S OFFICE,
WITH THE DEPARTMENTS USING THIS SYSTEM EVERY DAY AND MORE THAN
A DOZEN INDIVIDUAL STAFF WHO ARE IN THE SOFTWARE HOUR BY
HOUR AND THE PICTURE THAT CAME BACK WAS CONSISTENT.
>> THIS PRODUCT IS UNFORTUNATELY NOT READY
RECEIVED PERMIT TURNAROUND TIMES MOVE IN THE WRONG
DIRECTION. >> A SUPERVISOR FIELDER
MENTIONED SPECIFICALLY FIRE ALARM AND SPRINKLER PERMITS
USED TO TAKE TWO DAYS AND ARE NOW TAKING 8 TO 9.
I WANT TO BE FAIR THAT SOME OF THAT MAY BE THE PROCESS
AND SOME OF IT MAY BE A LEARNING CURVE.
>> THERE'S A REASONABLE POSSIBILITY AND I DON'T DISMISS
IT BUT REGARDLESS OF THE CAUSE, A FOURFOLD INCREASE
IN TURNAROUND TIME IS NOT THE OUTCOME WE WERE PROMISED AND IT
IS NOT AN OUTCOME THE CITY SHOULD BE ASKED TO ACCEPT FOR
THE NEXT FIVE YEARS. BEYOND THE NUMBERS THERE ARE
STRUCTURAL PROBLEMS DURING OUR DUE DILIGENCE WE DISCOVER THAT
THERE'S NO TESTING ENVIRONMENT AND THE OPEN GOV PLATFORM FOR
ENTERPRISE PRODUCT TOUCHING PERMITTING ACROSS DEPARTMENTS
THAT MEANS EVERY FIX, EVERY UPDATE, EVERY CHANGE IS TESTED
LIVE ON REAL PERMITS FOR REAL SAN FRANCISCANS.
THAT'S NOT HOW ENTERPRISE SOFTWARE SHOULD BE RUN.
DATA ENTRY AND PROCESSING ARE BY EVERY COUNT WE HEARD WORSE
THAN WHEN THE DEPARTMENTS HAD BEFORE AND THERE'S CURRENTLY NO
FUNCTIONAL CHANNEL FOR THE PEOPLE USING THE PRODUCT DAY TO
DAY TO COMMUNICATE THEIR PROBLEMS BACK TO THE VENDOR
AND GET THEM RESOLVED. I'VE HEARD THE COUNTER ARGUMENT
AS WELL AND I TAKE IT SERIOUSLY THAT A LONG CONTRACT IS NEEDED
TO SUPPORT THE CULTURAL CHANGE THAT REQUIRES THAT IS REQUIRED
ACROSS DEPARTMENTS. >> I DON'T DISAGREE THAT
CULTURAL CHANGE TAKES TIME BUT I DON'T BELIEVE IT REQUIRES A
FIVE YEAR NO CHECKPOINT COMMITMENT TO GET THERE A THREE
YEAR TERM AS SUPERVISOR CHEN HAS PROPOSED, GIVES THE VENDOR
EVERY INCENTIVE TO MAKE THE FIXES THAT EARN THAT EXTENSION
WHILE PRESERVING THE BOARD'S ABILITY TO HAVE A SEAT AT THE
TABLE AND ANY NECESSARY AMENDMENTS TO THE CONTRACT.
>> IT SUPPORTS THE SAME CULTURAL TRANSITION EVERYONE
AGREES WE NEED. IT JUST KEEPS THE CITY'S
LEVERAGE INTACT WHILE WE GET THERE.
AND LOOK, WE'VE BEEN HERE BEFORE.
>> SAN FRANCISCO UNIFIED WENT THROUGH A SOFTWARE OVERHAUL
THAT DID NOT GO WELL AND THE COSTS OF NOT IN DOLLARS
IN TRUST AND IN DISRUPTION TO BASIC FUNCTIONS OUTLASTED THE
CONTRACT ITSELF. THE SAME OCCURRED WITH THE
JUSTICE SYSTEM THAT SUPERVISOR DORSEY MENTIONED AS WELL.
>> THE SAME OCCURRED WITH THE VERY SAME EXCEL SYSTEM THAT WE
ARE NOW LOOKING TO REPLACE. SO WE SHOULD LEARN FROM THAT
AND NOT REPEAT THE SAME PROCESS AND MISTAKES THAT GOT US
IN THIS MESS IN THE FIRST PLACE.
FOUR YEARS PRIOR I WORKED IN THE SOFTWARE SECTOR AND LED
TEAMS WHOSE RESPONSIBILITY IT WAS TO PURCHASE SOFTWARE ON
BEHALF OF OUR EMPLOYEES A FUNDAMENTAL PRINCIPLE
IN EVALUATING SOFTWARE WAS ASSESSING WHAT IS THE MINIMUM
AMOUNT OF TIME WE NEED TO VALIDATE A PRODUCT BEFORE WE
COMMIT TO A LONG TERM COMMITMENT.
YOU COULD ALSO SAY YOU GOT A DATE A LITTLE BIT BEFORE YOU
GOT MARRIED AND THIS AMENDED CONTRACT ALLOWS US TO KEEP
DATING FOR A LITTLE BIT LONGER BEFORE WE ENTER INTO A STRICTLY
MONOGAMOUS RELATIONSHIP WITH THE VENDOR.
>> AND HEY, SOMETIMES YOU MIGHT FIND YOURSELF IN A SOLE SOURCE
SITUATION WHERE YOU GET MARRIED TO YOUR VERY FIRST GIRLFRIEND
AND AS UNFORTUNATELY MY WIFE TOLD THE SAN FRANCISCO STANDARD
I MARRIED MY VERY FIRST GIRLFRIEND AND IT'S WORKED OUT
OKAY SO FAR. SO WHO KNOWS MAYBE OPEN WILL
WORK OUT AS WELL. >> I HOPE SO BUT MORE SERIOUSLY
YOU STILL GOT TO VET THE RELATIONSHIP AND ACCOUNTABILITY
AND DILIGENCE AND VETTING WILL HELP US AVOID THE MISTAKES OF
THE PAST. IT DOESN'T TAKE AWAY FROM THE
GOAL OF A MODERN ACCOUNTABLE PERMITTING SYSTEM A GOAL I
SHARE AND ONE THIS BOARD SHOULD KEEP PUSHING TOWARD BUT IT DOES
MAKE SURE WE GET TO THE BEST PRODUCT NOT THE BEST PRODUCT WE
SIGNED UP FOR ON DAY ONE. >> IT KEEPS THE BOARD'S ABILITY
TO REVISIT THIS BEFORE FIVE YEARS HAVE PASSED AND BEFORE WE
HAVE A MINIMUM VIABLE PRODUCT IN HAND.
>> I WANT TO SINCERELY THANKS ADVISER CHEN AND HER AIDE
JACKIE PRAGER FOR THEIR WORK IN NEGOTIATING THIS AMENDMENT
DEEPLY GRATEFUL FOR THEIR PARTNERSHIP IN GETTING IT DONE
AND FOR THEIR COMMITMENT TO LANDING ON A SOLUTION THAT
WORKS FOR THE CITY. I'D URGE MY COLLEAGUES TO
SUPPORT IT AS WELL. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR CHAN THANK YOU PRESIDENT AMENDMENT I THINK
THAT THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT IS HERE.
>> IF I MAY ASK JUST A QUICK QUESTION SARAH DENNIS PHILLIPS
WELCOME DIRECTORS PHILLIPS DENNIS PHILLIPS MY APOLOGIES
AND JUST WANTED TO UNDERSTAND THAT YOU KNOW IN THE EVENT
AND I THINK WE HAD THIS CONVERSATION BEFORE AND DURING
THE BUDGET PROCESS IN THE EVENT THAT THIS SOFTWARE DOES NOT
WORK, WHERE DOES A CONTRACT DOES NOT WORK?
>> WHAT IS THE PLAN B? SO I FIRST I WANT TO THANK MANY
OF THE BOARD HERE TODAY FOR SUPPORTING OUR PERMITTING
REFORM EFFORTS. >> I SPECIFICALLY WANT TO THANK
SUPERVISOR CHERYL PRESIDENT MANN DILLMAN SUPERVISOR CHEN
AND SUPERVISOR DORSEY WHO HAVE GREATLY IMPROVED THIS CONTRACT
AND OUR ABILITY TO MOVE IT FORWARD.
SO I THINK WE ARE VERY COMFORTABLE AT THE MOMENT THAT
WE HAVE A DELIVERABLE BASED CONTRACT THAT ALLOWS THE CITY
TO TERMINATE FOR ITS CONVENIENCE AS WELL AS FOR
FAILURE OF PERFORMANCE. WE ALSO ARE COMING BACK TO YOU
AND WE WELCOME THE SCRUTINY ON THIS PROJECT SO THAT WE CAN USE
THOSE OPTIONS IF IT DOES NOT PERFORM.
>> I THINK ULTIMATELY MY QUESTION MY APOLOGIES LET ME
REFRAME REPHRASE THAT OR REFRAME THE QUESTION.
I THINK THE QUESTION AGAIN IS WHAT IS THE PLAN B IN THE EVENT
THIS CONTRACT YOU DETERMINED THAT IT'S NOT WORKING, IT'S NOT
DELIVERING AND YIELDING THE RESULTS THAT WE WERE EXPECTING.
HOWEVER WE AND WHENEVER DONE THE REPORT COMES BACK IN I
THINK WE'D WORK WITH YOU ON THOSE OPTIONS RIGHT NOW WE ARE
AS AS HAS BEEN NOTED, ROLLING OUT THE NEW IMPROVEMENTS WHILE
MAINTAINING OUR EXISTING SLA SYSTEM.
SO WE HAVE THAT AS A BACKSTOP AND THEN WE WOULD EXPLORE OUR
FUTURE OPTIONS WITH THIS BOARD UNDERSTOOD.
SO WHAT YOU'RE SAYING IS THAT IN THE NEXT THREE YEARS THE
GOAL IS AS I RECALL THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR THAT REMINDER TOO
IS THAT THERE'S ACTUALLY A PARALLEL PATH WE'RE GOING TO
CONTINUE TO USE THE EXISTING OR HAVE THE EXISTING PERMITTING
SYSTEM IN PLACE WHILE WE ARE NOW EXPLORING THE NEW ONE
AND SO THAT IN THE EVENT THAT THIS NEW ONE DOES NOT WORK WE
CAN DEFAULT BACK TO THE ORIGINAL OUR EXISTING
PERMITTING SYSTEM IN GENERAL. >> YES.
HELP ME UNDERSTAND THOUGH IF THAT THE CONTRACT ITSELF REALLY
IS TO ELIMINATE OVER COUNTER PERMIT SYSTEM OR JUST IN-PERSON
OVER COUNTER APPLICATION BECAUSE NOW EVERYTHING GETS
GOING ONLINE, HOW DO YOU THEN IF THIS ONLINE SYSTEM DOESN'T
WORK, HOW DO YOU THEN GO BACK TO THE DEFAULT ON OVER A
COUNTER IN PERSON? >> SO ONE THING I CORRECT OUR
GOAL IS NEVER TO ELIMINATE PERSON TO PERSON CONTACT.
WE DO WANT TO INCREASE ONLINE OPTIONS BECAUSE WE ARE FINDING
THAT THAT IS WHAT OUR CUSTOMERS ARE ASKING FOR AND THAT IS THE
SIMPLEST WAY TO MOVE THESE THINGS FORWARD.
THE PERMIT CENTER HAS PROVED TO BE A GREAT TOOL TO CONNECT WITH
CUSTOMERS AND THAT WILL CONTINUE TO BE A TOOL USE.
>> AND THEN MY LAST QUESTION WHAT WILL THEN BE A DECISION
MAKING? WHAT IS THE THRESHOLD FOR YOU
TO SAY TO COME BACK TO SAY TO THIS BOARD TO OF COURSE TO THE
MAYOR TO SAY THIS IS A TIME WE SHOULD TERMINATE THIS CONTRACT?
>> WE ARE CERTAINLY EXPECTING ANNUAL PROGRESS REPORTS
PROBABLY CONCOMITANT WITH A BUDGET TO COME BACK TO YOU
AND EXPLAIN HOW THE CONTRACT IS GOING.
AS MENTIONED ALSO IT'S A DELIVERABLE BASED CONTRACT SO
IF WE HAVE BREACH ON THE DELIVERABLES IN EACH PHASE OF
THIS CONTRACT WE WOULD ALSO ALERT YOU AS WELL IF THE
DELIVERABLES FOR EXAMPLE I THINK ALL A LOT OF CITY
CONTRACT YOU MEET 75% OF THE GOALS IF YOU MEET 85% OF THE
GOAL BUT IF YOU FALL BELOW 65 OR BELOW I DON'T KNOW 35% I'M
JUST GIVING YOU ITS OWN VERSION OUT THERE.
IS THERE A THRESHOLD OF THE PERCENTAGE OF DELIVERABLE THAT
THE CONTRACTORS OUGHT TO MEET IN ORDER FOR US TO SAY NOW, YOU
KNOW, FALLEN REALLY BEHIND AND THIS IS WHY WE'RE GOING TO
ASK THE GROUNDS TO TERMINATE THE CONTRACT IT'S IT'S HARD TO
SPEAK IN THE ABSTRACT WITHOUT UNDERSTANDING WHAT'S IN FRONT
OF US. BUT HAPPY TO REPORT BACK
REGULARLY IF YOU HAVE QUESTIONS WHEN WE ARE IN DIRECT THOSE
SITUATIONS. >> THANK YOU.
>> MY LAST COMMENTS COLLEAGUES IS THAT I'M SO GRATEFUL FOR
CHAIR DORSEY REALLY FOR PUTTING BACK THAT THAT LANGUAGE BACK
IN TO ALLOW THE CITY TO HAVE THE OPTION TO TERMINATE THE
CONTRACT ALTOGETHER. I THINK THAT'S A WISE WISE
MOVE. THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR YOUR
LEADERSHIP ON THAT AND THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHAN AND VICE
CHAIR TO THE BUDGET COMMITTEE. THIS IS AMAZING NEGOTIATION.
I THINK THE FACT THAT IT REALLY ALLOW US TO ACTUALLY HAVE TIME
TO ACTUALLY UNDERSTAND THE PROCESS BUT NOT SO MUCH SO THAT
ALMOST VIRTUALLY NO ONE HERE WOULD BE TO KNOW TO HAVE THE
INSTITUTIONAL KNOWLEDGE AND THE MEMORY TO HOLD THE CONTRACTOR
ACCOUNTABLE. >> AND SO I THINK THAT THREE
YEARS IS A VERY WISE MOVE TO SCALE BACK.
WHAT I DO THINK THOUGH I CONCUR WITH THE SENTIMENTS WITH
SUPERVISOR FIELDER ON THIS ONE IS THE FACT THAT IT IS STILL
NOT CLEAR TO ME WHAT THE DELIVERABLES ACTUALLY ARE NOT
IN TERMS OF LIKE THE PERMITS THAT WE WANT TO BE ABLE TO HAVE
ONLINE. >> IT IS MORE LIKE THAT
DELIVERABLE IN TERMS OF IN DIFFERENT EACH DEVELOPMENT
PHASE THAT ARE WE WHAT IS THE GOAL LIKE YOU KNOW IF THE GOAL
IS TO MOVE VIRTUALLY ALL THESE PERMITS ONLINE THAT YOU CAN
FILE ONLINE AND OUT OF HUNDREDS OF THEM WE WON YOU KNOW 90% OF
THEM ACTUALLY BE ABLE TO FILE ONLINE AND AT THIS FIRST YEAR
WE WANT TO SEE THIS MANY PERMITS THAT YOU CAN ACTUALLY
FILE ONLINE AND BEING WILL CLOSE OUT AND APPROVE BY 30
DAYS. AND IF WE DON'T MEET THAT GOAL
BECAUSE YOU KNOW OF 65% OF THEM DID NOT ACTUALLY BEING ABLE TO
MOVE ONLINE EFFICIENTLY THEN THIS IS DEEMED NOT ONLY A
TERMINATION FOR THE CONTRACT BUT HERE'S THE BACKUP PLAN THAT
WE ACTUALLY WILL THEN GO OUT AND GET READY FOR ANOTHER RFP
AND TO BE ABLE TO LIKE COME OUT AND FOR A DIFFERENT OPTION.
I THINK THOSE ARE ACTUALLY STEPS THAT I HAVE HEARD AS A
BUDGET COMMITTEE CHAIR PREVIOUSLY FROM DIFFERENT CITY
DEPARTMENT AMENDING THEM TO DO SO THAT'S YOU KNOW, BE OUR
DEPARTMENT OF TECHNOLOGY DEPARTMENT PUBLIC HEALTH.
BUT TODAY I AM ABSOLUTELY GRATEFUL AND IN SUPPORT OF THE
BUDGET COMMITTEE IN THE WORK THAT THEY HAVE DONE AND WHAT IS
BEFORE US TODAY I IT IS MY INTENTION TO NOT ONLY VOTE FOR
THE AMENDMENTS BUT TO VOTE THE AMENDED CONTRACT IN SUPPORT OF
IT. BUT I ABSOLUTELY I'M EAGER TO
BE ABLE TO SEE WHAT HAPPENS IN THE NEXT BUDGET PROCESS
AND SEE WHAT THE BUDGET COMMITTEE IS ABLE TO HOLD THEM
ACCOUNTABLE FOR THE DELIVERABLES.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR MELGAR THANK YOU
PRESIDENT JUST WANTED TO SAY ONE LAST THING BEFORE WE VOTE.
I APPRECIATE SUPERVISOR CHAN'S COMMENTS AND I WANTED TO SAY
THAT I REALLY EXPECT AND FULLY LOOK FORWARD TO THE DEPARTMENT
COMING THREE YEARS FROM NOW BEING ABLE TO SAY, YOU KNOW,
ALL OF THE SUCCESS THAT WE HAVE REACHED, I CAN UNDERSTAND WHY
WE WOULDN'T WANT TO PUT SPECIFIC NUMBERS WHEN WE HAVE
HAD THIS PROJECT FOR 1215 YEARS AND HAVEN'T REALLY MOVED IT
FORWARD. I TOTALLY GET THAT AND I ALSO
KNOW THAT, YOU KNOW, PUTTING BACK THIS LANGUAGE BY
SUPERVISOR DORSEY GIVES US SOME BACKUP A SUPERVISOR OR TEN
ARTICULATED. >> HOWEVER I HAVE VERY RECENTLY
HAD THE EXPERIENCE BEING ON THE EMPTY SEABOARD OF HAVING A
CONTRACT WITH A COMPANY THAT IS RUNNING OUR CLIPPER TWO POINT
WELL WHERE WE'RE ACTUALLY NOT PAYING THEM BECAUSE THEY HAVE
UNDERPERFORMED AND WE CANNOT TERMINATE THE CONTRACT BECAUSE
THERE IS NO ONE ELSE. AND SO THE CONTRACTING
PROCEDURES CAN BE REALLY BORING AND CUMBERSOME BUT THEY PRESENT
US WITH PATHS AND YOU KNOW THERE'S A REASON WHY WE DO
THINGS THAT WAY. SO WHEN WE HAVE A SOLE SOURCE
CONTRACT AND WE DON'T HAVE YOU KNOW, SOMEONE ELSE WILL PICK IT
UP AND GO TERMINATE SERVING IT OR UNDERPAYING CAN SOMETIMES
NOT GET US YOU KNOW, DO WHAT WE WANT BECAUSE IT DOESN'T
INCENTIVIZE GETTING TO THE GOALS AND SOMETIMES IT EVEN
BECOMES AN IMPEDIMENT ECONOMICALLY.
SO I JUST WANT TO SAY THANK YOU FOR ALL OF YOUR WORK.
I THINK THAT YOU KNOW, THE FACT THAT WE WERE NOT ON THE READY
TO APPROVE THE CONTRACT BUT RATHER WANTED TO WORK IT SOME
MORE IS EVIDENCE OF US WANTING TO BE SUPPORTIVE AND INVOLVED
NOT YOU KNOW, OF CONTENTION. >> BUT I WANTED TO AGAIN SAY
THANK YOU SO MUCH SUPERVISOR CHEN FOR YOUR WORK AND FOR THE
GRACE WITH WHICH YOU REACHED THIS AGREEMENT.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR MELGAR. MOTION HAS BEEN MADE BY
SUPERVISOR CHEN. IT HAS BEEN SECONDED BY
SUPERVISOR CHAN. COLLEAGUES, CAN WE TAKE THE
AMENDMENT WITHOUT OBJECTION? WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION IS
APPROVED. OKAY.
AND THEN DO WE? WELL, MADAM CLERK, PLEASE
PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THE AMENDED ITEM ON ITEM 37 AS
AMENDED SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I
SUPERVISOR DORSI DORSI I SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER NO
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR MANDEL MAN RIGHT
RANDLEMAN EYES SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR
SADR EYES SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON I
WALTON I AND SUPERVISOR HUANG HUANG EITHER ARE TEN EYES
AND ONE NO WITH SUPERVISOR FIELDER VOTING NO AND THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 38 ITEM
38 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO APPROVE THE AMENDED AIRPORT
SURVEILLANCE TECHNOLOGY POLICY GOVERNING THE USE OF THIRD
PARTY SECURITY CAMERAS. >> PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THIS
ITEM ON ITEM 30 EIGHT SUPERVISOR CHAN I CHECK ON ITEM
38 HI CHAN I SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I SUPERVISOR DORSI DORSI I
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN I MANDEL MAN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR
I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR EYES SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL EYES
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I AND SUPERVISOR WANG WONG EITHER
R.A. LEBANESE WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON
FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ADAM'S 39 AND 40
TOGETHER ITEMS 39 AND 40 ARE TWO ORDINANCES TO AUTHORIZE THE
SETTLEMENT OF TWO SEPARATE LAWSUITS.
ITEM 39 WAS FILED BY QUIQUE ARROYO ROBINSON LUQMAN ALICIA
WILLIAMS, JOHN HILL, WILLIAM SPARKS ON BEHALF OF THEMSELVES
AND ALL OTHER SIMILARLY SITUATED CURRENT AND FORMER
EMPLOYEES AGAINST THE CITY AND COUNTY FOR APPROXIMATELY
8.7 MILLION. THE LAWSUIT INVOLVES AN
EMPLOYMENT DISPUTE ITEM 40 FILED BY GABRIEL SHINN AGAINST
THE CITY AND COUNTY JANINE NICHOLSON, ROBERT POSTELL, TOM
O'CONNOR, DAVID BROWN, PATRICIA LEE, JOE SERGENT AND ROBERT
MUHAMMAD FOR 6 MILLION. THIS LAWSUIT INVOLVES AN
EMPLOYMENT DISPUTE. >> LET'S TAKE THESE ITEMS SAME
HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
ORDINANCES ARE PASSED ON FIRST READING AND MADAM CLERK AT THAT
TAKES US TO OUR COMMITTEE REPORTS PLEASE CALL ITEM 47 YES
FIRST I'LL SAY ITEMS 47 AND 48 WERE CONSIDERED BY THE RULES
COMMITTEE AT A REGULAR MEETING ON MONDAY SEPTEMBER 14TH, 2026
AT 10 A.M. AND WERE FORWARDED AS COMMITTEE REPORTS ITEM 47
THIS ITEM WAS RECOMMENDED AS AMENDED TO APPROVE STRIKING THE
WORD REJECTING THE MOTION NOW READS MOTION TO APPROVE THE
PRESIDENT OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS RAFAEL MANDEL BONDS
NOMINATION AND FOR THE APPOINTMENT OF MELISSA CHAVEZ
TO THE PLANNING COMMISSION TERM ENDING JULY 1ST, 2020 EIGHT.
>> SUPERVISOR ZUNIGA THANK YOU SO MUCH PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN
AND I WANTED TO THANK YOU FOR THIS NOMINATION RUN IN MY
COLLEAGUES ON THE RULES COMMITTEE I JUST WANTED TO SAY
A COUPLE OF WORDS OF PERSONAL SUPPORT FOR MY FRIEND MELISSA
CHAVEZ FOR THE PLANNING COMMISSION.
>> SHE AND I MAY NOT MAY NOT ALWAYS AGREE ON PLANNING THINGS
AND I TRUST HER AND SUPPORT HER WHOLEHEARTEDLY.
I THINK MELISSA HAS A DEEP CONNECTION TO THE COMMUNITY THE
MISSION COMMUNITY, THE LATINO COMMUNITY IN SAN FRANCISCO.
BUT REALLY A LOT OF COMMUNITY. SHE SERVED AS DIRECTOR OF AT
THE WOMEN'S BUILDING, DEPUTY DIRECTOR OF HOMELESS PRENATAL.
SHE WORKED WITH ME AT THE MISSION ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT
AGENCY AND I KNOW HOW SMART AND STRATEGIC SHE IS.
I WILL SAY THIS THE PLANNING COMMISSION AS YOU KNOW, I, I
SERVED ON IT FOR MANY YEARS CAN BE A PLACE WHERE THERE'S A LOT
OF CONTENTIOUSNESS BECAUSE EVERY INCH OF OUR SEVEN BY
SEVEN CITY IS WELL USED AND WE ALL HAVE OPINIONS ABOUT IT.
SO I WAS HOPING THAT WE WOULD HAVE SOMEBODY IN THIS POSITION
WHO COULD DISAGREE WITH GRACE, YOU KNOW, AND GENUINELY CHANNEL
THE HOPES AND DREAMS OF THE FOLKS THAT SHE IS CONNECTED
WITH. I THINK THAT SERVES US ALL
BETTER WHEN WE CAN DISCUSS OUR DISAGREEMENTS, DO IT WITH GRACE
AND COME UP WITH BETTER DECISIONS BECAUSE WE'VE
CONSIDERED THE OPINIONS OF OTHERS AND I GUESS FULL
CONFIDENCE THAT MALIA WILL BE THAT PERSON ON THE PLANNING
COMMISSION. SO AGAIN, THANK YOU SO MUCH
PRESIDENT MANDOLIN FOR THIS NOMINATION AND THANK YOU TO MY
COLLEAGUES ON THE RULES COMMITTEE.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR MELGAR THANK YOU FOR
BRINGING MISS CHAVEZ FORWARD FOR CONSIDERATION.
AS I SAID IN THE RULES COMMITTEE AND THANK YOU CHAIR
ONE WE THIS CHAVEZ IS STRAGGLING BEHIND TO OTHER
APPOINTMENTS THAT WE MADE BEFORE THE BREAK ONLY BECAUSE
OF A QUIRK OF THE WAY THE THE TIMING ON THIS PARTICULAR SEAT.
SO I REALLY SEE THIS AS PART OF A GROUP AND I THINK
COLLECTIVELY THEY ARE GOING TO REPRESENT THIS BOARD WELL WITH
THAT I THINK WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM.
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION IS
APPROVED. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL
ITEM 48. ITEM 48 THIS IS A MOTION TO
APPROVE CITY COMPTROLLER GREG WAGNER'S NOMINATION FOR THE
APPOINTMENT OF CHRISTOPHER SIMI TO THE SANITATION AND STREETS
COMMISSION FOR A TERM ENDING JULY 1ST, 2030 AND AGAIN SAME
HOUSE, SAME CALL. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION
IS APPROVED. LET'S GO TO ROLL CALL FOR
INTRODUCTIONS. >> YES, SUPERVISOR CHAN, YOUR
FIRST UP TO INTRODUCE NEW BUSINESS SUBMIT THANK YOU
SUBMIT. >> SUPERVISOR CHEN THANK YOU
MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUE AS I MENTIONED
EARLIER, I'M INTRODUCING A HEARING REQUEST ON THE PROGRESS
OF OPEN GOV CONTRACT THROUGH MANY HOURS OF NEGOTIATION WE
ARE ABLE TO NEGOTIATE A SHORTER TERM CONTRACT REDUCING BOTH THE
OVERALL LENGTH OF THIS CONTRACT AS WELL AS A TOTAL NOT TO
EXCEED AMOUNT. HOWEVER I AND SOME OF MY
COLLEAGUES STILL HAVE GREAT CONCERNS ESPECIALLY AROUND
CLERICAL DELIVERABLE TIME LINE STAFF STAFFING AND UPON BE JUST
ALSO IN CASE AS WE NEED IT DOES.
>> I DO NOT BELIEVE THAT I HAVE TO FAVOR IT AND THIS CONTRACT
WILL BE SUCCESSFUL WITHOUT DIRECT AND PERSISTENT OVERSIGHT
FROM THIS BOARD. I WANT TO SEE PERMIT S.F.
ASSOCIATES. I WANT SAN FRANCISCO TO HAVE A
PERMITTING SYSTEM THAT EXCELS IN SERVING OUR CONSTITUENTS.
HOWEVER, WE ARE DOING OUR BUDGET AND FINANCE MEETING.
IT WAS CLEAR TO ME THAT THERE WERE NOT STRONG ENOUGH
GUARDRAILS IN PLACE DURING A SOLE SOURCE PROCESS NOR THE
FIRST YEAR PILOT. I INTEND TO MAKE SURE THAT WE
DO NOT FAIL TO HAVE THIS ACCOUNTABILITY MEASURE IN PLACE
GOING FORWARD. I PLAN TO REQUEST A SCHEDULING
OF THIS HEARING AT THE END OF THIS CALENDAR YEAR AT A BUDGET
AND FINANCE COMMITTEE TO GUARANTEE OVERSIGHT
AND TRANSPARENCY OVER THE DEVELOPMENT, IMPLEMENTATION
AND PROGRESS OF THIS CONTRACT. THIS HEARING WILL GIVE US AN
OPPORTUNITY TO HEAR FROM PLANNING WHETHER OR NOT THEY'RE
MEETING ANY GOALS THAT REGARDING OVERALL PERFORMANCE
TIMELINE COSTS PERMIT PROCESSING TIME, CONSUMER
EXPERIENCES, THE HIRING, STAFFING AND RETENTION OF STAFF
ACROSS CITY DEPARTMENTS AND MORE.
>> I WILL ALSO GIVE US THE ABILITY TO HEAR FROM OTHER
DEPARTMENTS THAT ARE BEING INTEGRATED INTO THE SYSTEM.
I'M HOPEFUL THAT THIS HEARING WILL ALSO HELP REESTABLISH
TRUST THAT HAS BEEN ERODED BETWEEN THE CITY, THE PUBLIC,
THE MAYOR AND THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AND THE REST I
SUBMIT. THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHEN.
>> SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANK YOU MADAM CLERK.
COLLEAGUES, FEW OF US NEED TO BE REMINDED THAT SAN FRANCISCO
IS IN THE MIDST OF AN AFFORDABILITY CRISIS EVEN BY
THE STANDARDS OF A CITY THAT HAS RARELY BEEN AFFORDABLE WITH
RENTS ESPECIALLY RISING CITYWIDE.
ALTHOUGH MANY TENANTS ENJOY STRONG LEGAL PROTECTIONS, WE
ALSO KNOW THAT STATE LAW PREVENTS TENANTS RIGHTS FROM
BEING AS STRONG AS WE'D LIKE THEM TO BE IN MANY CASES.
>> SOMETIMES HOWEVER, TENANTS RIGHTS MAY ALSO BE RIGHTS THAT
TENANTS AREN'T FULLY AWARE OF. THAT'S WHY I AM TODAY
INTRODUCING LEGISLATION THAT WILL REQUIRE LANDLORDS TO
PROVIDE NOTICE TO TENANTS OF THEIR RIGHTS AND RENT INCREASE
LIMITATIONS UNDER THE STATE ANTI RENT GOUGING LAW AND TO
REQUIRE SAN FRANCISCO'S RENT BOARD TO PLAY A STRONGER ROLE
IN PROVIDING ASSISTANCE TO TENANTS WHO BELIEVE THEY MAY BE
FACING AN UNLAWFUL RENT HIKE NOT JUST UNDER OUR LOCAL RENT
CONTROL LAW BUT FOR THE FIRST TIME UNDER STATE LAW AS WELL.
IN SAN FRANCISCO ONLY PRE 1979 BUILDINGS ARE GENERALLY SUBJECT
TO RENT CONTROL. BUT THANKS TO OUR STATEWIDE
RENT CAP LAW ALSO KNOWN AS KNOWN AS THE CALIFORNIA TENANT
PROTECTION ACT OF 2019, THOUSANDS OF TENANTS
IN BUILDINGS OVER 15 YEARS OF AGE IN SAN FRANCISCO ARE
PROTECTED FROM RENT GOUGING. >> THE LANDMARK STATE BILL THAT
ACCOMPLISHED THIS WAS AB 1482. IT WAS AUTHORED BY THEN
ASSEMBLY MEMBER AND NOW CITY ATTORNEY DAVID CHU.
UNDER THAT LAW RENT CAN'T INCREASE BY MORE THAN THE
CONSUMER PRICE INDEX PLUS 5% OR 10% OVERALL WHICHEVER IS LOWER
FOR COVERED PROPERTIES. ALTHOUGH NOT AS FAVORABLE TO
RENTERS AS PRE 1979 BUILDING DWELLERS FOR MANY RENTERS
INCLUDING A LARGE NUMBER OF RENTERS IN NEWER BUILDINGS, THE
STATEWIDE RENT CAP COULD BE THE DIFFERENCE BETWEEN A RENT HIKE
THEY DON'T LIKE AND ONE THAT'S TANTAMOUNT TO AN EVICTION
NOTICE. THE MORE WE CAN ARM TENANTS
WITH INFORMATION ABOUT THEIR RIGHTS THE BETTER WITH DISTRICT
SIX HAVING SEEN MORE NEW RESIDENTIAL CONSTRUCTION THAN
ALMOST ANYWHERE ELSE IN THE CITY, THOUSANDS OF DISTRICT SIX
RENTERS DEPEND ON THIS STATE LAW AS THEIR MAIN AND IN MOST
CASES ONLY PROTECTION. I WANT TO THANK DEPUTY CITY
ATTORNEY MONU PRADHAN FOR HIS WORK DRAFTING THIS MATTER.
SAM TAM FROM MY OFFICE AS MY LEGISLATIVE DIRECTOR AND THE
MAYOR'S OFFICE AND STAFF FOR THEIR ENGAGEMENT ON THIS ISSUE.
>> THANK YOU ALSO TO SUPERVISOR CHAN FOR YOUR EARLY
CO-SPONSORSHIP. I'D ALSO LIKE TO EXPRESS MY
GRATITUDE TO CITY ATTORNEY DAVID CHU BOTH FOR HIS WORK TO
PASS HB 1482 IN THE STATE ASSEMBLY AND FOR THE WORK HE
DOES LEADING THE CITY ATTORNEY'S OFFICE THAT DOES
SUCH EXTRAORDINARY WORK TO PROTECT TENANTS FROM UNLAWFUL
BUSINESS PRACTICES AND UNSAFE CONDITIONS.
SO COLLEAGUES, WE WILL BE REACHING OUT ON THIS
LEGISLATION AND I WELCOME YOUR SUPPORT AND CO-SPONSORSHIP.
>> AND NOW MY OUTSIDE BOARDS AND COMMISSIONS UPDATE AT BCCDC
THE SAN FRANCISCO BAY CONSERVATION AND DEVELOPMENT
COMMISSION WE ARE CLOSELY WATCHING THE FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT'S ORDER TO CONDUCT CONDUCT A FORMAL PERFORMANCE
EVALUATION OR SECTION 312 REVIEW OF CALIFORNIA'S COASTAL
MANAGEMENT ZONE PROGRAMS. THE CDC AND ITS FEDERAL
PARTNERS INCLUDING NOAA. THAT'S THE NATIONAL OCEANIC
AND ATMOSPHERIC ADMINISTRATION SHARE CALIFORNIA'S GOAL OF
SERVING AND PROTECTING COASTAL RESOURCES WHILE ADVANCING
ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT AND THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT'S OWN REVIEW
CONCLUDED THAT THE STATE OF CALIFORNIA IS SUCCESSFULLY
IMPLEMENTING AND ENFORCING ITS FEDERALLY APPROVED COASTAL
MANAGEMENT PROGRAM. THE FINAL DETERMINATION WILL
HAVE AN IMPACT ON FEDERAL FUNDING AND OVERSIGHT FOR
FEDERAL PROJECTS OR CONSISTENCY DETERMINATIONS FOR COASTAL
MANAGEMENT AGENCIES. MORE TO COME IN FUTURE UPDATES.
OUR RECENT MEETINGS HAVE BEEN HEAVY ON BRIEFINGS AND OUR
TOPICS HAVE INCLUDED SEA LEVEL RISE INVESTMENT FUNDING
AND STRATEGY AGENCY STRATEGIC PLANNING AGENCY REGULATORY
IMPROVEMENTS, STATE AND FEDERAL LEGISLATIVE UPDATES AND THE
CALIFORNIA NATURAL RESOURCES AGENCY'S OUTDOOR FOR ALL
INITIATIVE. LATER THIS WEEK WE WILL GET AN
UPDATE ON THE PUBLIC SEA LEVEL RISE EDUCATION INITIATIVE AT
THE EXPLORATORIUM THAT WAS DEVELOPED AS PART OF THE 2025
SAN FRANCISCO WATERFRONT SPECIAL AREA PLAN AMENDMENT
AND I'M EXCITED TO HEAR ABOUT THEIR WORK.
I ALSO SERVE ALONGSIDE SUPERVISOR WALTON ON THE
WORKFORCE INVESTMENT BOARD. AT THE JUNE MEETING WITH A
REVIEWED AND APPROVED OVER WOODS FEDERAL WORKFORCE
INNOVATION AND OPPORTUNITY ACT ALLOCATIONS TO PROVIDERS FOR
FISCAL YEARS 26 AND 27 THOSE PROVIDERS WILL BE CORE PARTNERS
IN ACHIEVING STRONGER COORDINATION WITH THE HUMAN
SERVICES AGENCY IN ORDER TO SERVE PUBLIC BENEFITS
RECIPIENTS WHO ARE AFFECTED BY H.R. ONE.
>> THE SEPTEMBER MEETING SAW EWG PRESENT ON ITS NEW FULL
WORKFORCE PROGRAM PORTFOLIO EEO, WHICH INCLUDES EIGHT
CENTRALIZED JOB CENTERS, SIX SPECIALIZED JOB CENTERS FOR
SPECIAL POPULATION, SIX YOUNG ADULT JOB CENTERS AND A VARIETY
OF SECTOR TRAINING PORTFOLIOS IN CONSTRUCTION, HOSPITALITY,
HEALTH CARE, PUBLIC SAFETY TECH AND EMERGING SECTORS SUCH AS
EARLY CARE AND EDUCATION, TRANSPORTATION AND PERSONAL
SERVICES. THE ANNUAL LOCAL HIRE REPORT
WAS RELEASED AND IS AVAILABLE ON OUR WOODS AND WISPS WEBSITE.
THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS ADOPTED THIS POLICY
IN DECEMBER 2010. IT HAS SINCE BECOME ONE OF THE
STRONGEST PIECES OF LEGISLATION IN THE COUNTRY TO PROMOTE THE
HIRING OF LOCAL RESIDENTS ON LOCALLY SPONSORED PROJECTS.
NEARLY 4.3 MILLION CONSTRUCTION WORKER HOURS ON CAPITAL
IMPROVEMENT PROJECTS WERE SUBJECT TO LOCAL HIRE AND 35%
OF ALL HOURS WERE PERFORMED BY LOCAL RESIDENTS LAST YEAR.
MORE THAN HALF OF THEM 53% WERE APPRENTICE WORK HOURS WERE
PERFORMED BY LOCAL RESIDENTS. THANK YOU TO ANTONIA AND AND
WORKFORCE DIVISION FOR THEIR CONTINUED EXCELLENT WORK ON AIR
BAG BACK. THE ASSOCIATION OF BAY AREA
GOVERNMENTS I SERVE AS TEN FRANCISCO'S PRIMARY
REPRESENTATIVE SUPERVISOR CHEN RECENTLY JOINED AS OUR
ALTERNATE REPRESENTATIVE. SO IT'S GREAT TO HAVE YOU ON
THERE ON A BACK WITH US A BAG HELD AT THE ANNUAL GENERAL
ASSEMBLY IN JUNE WHERE THE ANNUAL WORK PROGRAM AND BUDGET
WAS ADOPTED. OUTREACH FOR A POTENTIAL 2028
BOFFA REVENUE BALLOT MEASURE WAS DISCUSSED.
>> ALL BAY AREA ELECTED OFFICIALS WILL BE RECEIVING AN
INVITATION FOR A WEBINAR AND SURVEY ON THAT SOON.
THIS FALL WE WILL BEGIN PLAN BAY AREA 2060 THIS FIFTH
ITERATION OF THE PLAN WILL BE ALIGNED WITH THE SEVENTH CYCLE
OF THE REGIONAL HOUSING NEEDS ALLOCATION OR THE ARENA
PROCESS. THE EXECUTIVE BOARD'S NEXT
STEPS WILL BE TO WORK WITH MTC TO ANALYZE EXISTING CONDITIONS
ACROSS THE REGION AND REVISIT THE PLAN'S VISION AND GUIDING
PRINCIPLES. AND I THINK FINALLY ON THE
HEALTH SERVICE BOARD MET LAST WEEK AND WE DISCUSSED THE
UPCOMING OPEN ENROLLMENT PERIOD.
MAKE SURE YOUR STAFFS ARE AWARE.
OPEN ENROLLMENT FOR THE 2720 22,027 PLAN YEAR WILL RUN FROM
OCTOBER 1ST THROUGH OCTOBER 23RD.
>> MOST CURRENT BENEFIT ELECTIONS WILL AUTOMATICALLY
ROLL OVER BUT FOR MEMBERS WHO MUST ENROLL MUST ENROLL IN THE
HEALTH CARE AND DEPENDENT FLEXIBLE SPENDING ACCOUNTS EACH
YEAR BEGINNING IN 2027, CITY AND COUNTY AND SUPERIOR COURT
EMPLOYEES WILL RECEIVE OPEN ENROLLMENT COMMUNICATIONS
PRIMARILY BY EMAIL AND PRINTED HEALTH BENEFIT GUIDES WILL BE
REPLACED BY ONLINE RESOURCES. A MAJOR CHANGE FOR 2027 IS THE
TRANSITION OF KAISER PERMANENTE'S MULTI REGION
MEMBERS TO CORRESPONDING BLUE SHIELD PLANS.
SS AND BLUE SHIELD ARE CONDUCTING TARGETED OUTREACH
AND PROVIDING ASSISTANCE WITH PROVIDER SELECTION, PHARMACY
TRANSITIONS AND CONTINUITY OF CARE.
OTHER CHANGES INCLUDE NEW METLIFE LEGAL AND IDENTITY
PROTECTION BENEFITS, EXPANDED BLUE SHIELD MEDICARE
TRANSPORTATION SERVICES AND MODERN INCREASES TO
FLEXIBLE SPENDING ACCOUNT CONTRIBUTION AND ROLLOVER
LIMITS. WE WILL MEET AGAIN NEXT MONTH
AND THE REST I SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR DORSEY SUPERVISOR FIELDER.
>> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM
INTRODUCING TWO ITEMS. FIRST I AM INTRODUCING
LEGISLATION AND BRING GREATER TRANSPARENCY WHEN CITY
DEPARTMENTS ARE GRANTED WAIVERS TO THE HAZARD PAYMENTS FROM
INTERESTED PARTIES. >> BUT HAZARD PAYMENTS ARE
DONATIONS MADE TO A CITY AGENCY OR NONPROFIT AT THE REQUEST OF
A GOVERNMENT OFFICIAL. INTERESTED PARTIES ARE PEOPLE
OR ENTITIES THAT HAVE BUSINESS BEFORE THE CITY OR HAVE A STAKE
IN A CITY DECISION. FOR EXAMPLE, A DEVELOPER
SEEKING APPROVAL FOR A CONSTRUCTION PERMIT OR A
COMPANY BIDDING ON A CITY CONTRACT WHEN THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS CREATED THESE WAIVERS IN 2022.
THE INTENTION WAS FOR THEM TO BE USED SPARINGLY.
FIRST WITH CIVIC NEEDS AND WITH FULL TRANSPARENCY.
WE'VE SEEN MANY WAIVER REQUESTS TO SOLICIT DONATIONS FROM
INTERESTED PARTIES COME THROUGH THE GOVERNMENT AUDIT
AND OVERSIGHT COMMITTEE. YET WE DON'T KNOW WHAT COMES OF
THESE WAIVERS AT THE END OF THE SIX MONTH WAIVER PERIOD.
CURRENTLY THE BOARD ONLY ASKS FOR INFORMATION AT THE FRONT
END OF THE WAIVER PROCESS AND DEPARTMENTS DON'T ALWAYS
LIST SPECIFIC DONORS OR NARROW PROJECTS THAT WILL BE FUNDED
WITH THESE DOLLARS. >> THE LEGISLATION I'M
INTRODUCING WOULD REQUIRE A REPORT AT THE END OF THE WAIVER
PERIOD THAT IDENTIFIES THE NAMES OF INTERESTED PARTIES
THAT WERE SOLICITED. A COMPLETE DESCRIPTION OF WHY
THEY'RE AN INTERESTED PARTY THE AMOUNT OF THE DONATION MADE BY
THE INTERESTED PARTY AND THE NAME OF THE INDIVIDUALS OR
ENTITIES THAT RECEIVED EACH PAYMENT.
THE CLERK OF THE BOARD WOULD BE REQUIRED TO PUBLISH INFORMATION
ON DATA STAFF IN A SEARCHABLE AND SORTABLE FORMAT WITHIN 30
DAYS OF SUBMISSION OF THE REPORT AND THE LEGISLATION
ADDRESSES REPEAT WAIVERS. IF A GRANTED WAIVER HAS EXPIRED
AND A SUBSTANTIALLY SIMILAR ONE IS INTRODUCED.
THE NEW WAIVER WOULD NOT BE CONSIDERED BY THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS FOR ONE YEAR. I'D LIKE TO THANK SUPERVISORS
CHAN AND CHEN FOR THEIR EARLY CO-SPONSORSHIP.
>> AND SECOND TO THEM INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION
CALLING ON OUR CALIFORNIA SENATORS AND BURIED
CONGRESSIONAL DELEGATION TO INVESTIGATE PROVIDE OVERSIGHT
AND CONDEMN THE DE FACTO AN IMMIGRATION DETENTION CENTER AT
THE SAN FRANCISCO INTERNATIONAL AIRPORT.
AS REPORTED BY IMMIGRATION ATTORNEYS AND ADVOCATES
AND MOST RECENTLY BY THE SAN FRANCISCO CHRONICLE, THE
FEDERAL GOVERNMENT HAS COMMANDEERED A SECTION OF THE
INTERNATIONAL TERMINAL AT SFO TO HOLD AND DETAIN IMMIGRANTS
FROM MULTIPLE DAYS IN SOME CASES BEYOND WHAT'S LAWFUL
WITHIN CBP'S OWN GUIDELINES. MANY OF THESE IMMIGRANTS ARE
DETAINED WHILE FLYING IN OR OUT OF SFO AND SOME IMMIGRANTS ARE
BROUGHT TO SFO FROM REGIONAL AIRPORTS.
AS FAR AS FRESNO SOLELY TO BE PLACED IN DETENTION AT SFO.
THERE ARE FIRST HAND ACCOUNTS OF GREEN CARD HOLDERS WHO HAVE
LACKED ACCESS TO MEDICAID PRISONS, COUNSEL AND BEDS BY
THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT INSTEAD BEING FORCED TO SLEEP ON CHAIRS
UNDER BRIGHT LIGHTS FOR MULTIPLE NIGHTS.
CONGRESSMAN KEVIN MOLAN IS REPORTEDLY THE FIRST AND ONLY
MEMBER OF CONGRESS TO VISIT THIS DE FACTO DETENTION CENTER
AND REPORT ON THE HUMAN RIGHTS AND DUE PROCESS VIOLATIONS
TAKING PLACE THERE. >> AND I'M CALLING ON THE REST
OF OUR CONGRESSIONAL DELEGATION TO ALSO VISIT AND INVESTIGATE
AND CONDEMN THIS UNLAWFUL DETENTION CENTER AT SFO.
THANK YOU TO SUPERVISORS MELGAR CHEN WALTON, MAHMOOD CHAN
AND SAUTER FOR YOUR EARLY CO-SPONSORSHIP.
THE REST I SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU SUPERVISOR FIELDER SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD COLLINS.
>> LAST WEEK A WOMAN WAS CRITICALLY INJURED IN A SERIOUS
DOG ATTACK ON LARKIN STREET IN THE TENDERLOIN.
>> OUR FIRST PRIORITY IS THE VICTIM AND I'M WISHING HER A
FULL RECOVERY. >> BUT IT'S A PAINFUL REMINDER
THAT DOG ATTACKS JUST PROPORTIONATELY AFFECT THE
TENDERLOIN AS SPEEDY DATA SHOWS 46 DOG ATTACKS CITYWIDE IN THE
LAST 30 DAYS. 11 OF WHICH WERE IN THE TEAL
AND CITYWIDE REPORTED DOG BITES HAVE ROUGHLY DOUBLED FROM
APPROXIMATELY 450 IN 2024 TO MORE THAN 900 IN 2025.
>> THOSE NUMBERS DEMAND MORE THAN REACTING AFTER SOMEONE'S
ALREADY BEEN HURT. THE CITY NEEDS THE TOOLS,
STAFFING AND COORDINATION TO INTERVENE WHEN A DANGEROUS DOG
IS IDENTIFIED AND TO PREVENT THESE INCIDENTS IN THE FIRST
PLACE. >> TODAY I AM INTRODUCING A
RESOLUTION TO STRENGTHEN DOG SAFETY PROTOCOLS AT CITY FUNDED
SHELTER, TRANSITIONAL HOUSING AND SUPPORTIVE HOUSING SITES
PLACES THAT SHOULD BE SAFE FOR RESIDENTS, NEIGHBORS, WORKERS
AND VISITORS. THE CITYWIDE GOOD NEIGHBOR
POLICY ALREADY SETS EXPECTATIONS ON LITTER,
SIDEWALK CLEARANCE AND PROPERTY CONDITIONS AS IT EXPANDS WITH
ENFORCEMENT BEGINNING IN JANUARY.
WE HAVE A CHANCE TO ADD PET AND DOG SAFETY EXPECTATIONS AS
WELL. THE RESOLUTION THAT WE ARE
SUBMITTING ASKS THE MAYOR'S OFFICE TO CONSIDER THREE
MEASURES PROVIDERS THAT PERMIT RESIDENT PETS MAINTAIN BASIC
REGISTRATION AND VACCINATION RECORDS TO DOG BITES
AND ATTACKS AT OR NEAR COVERAGE SITES ARE LOGGED THROUGH
EXISTING GOOD NEIGHBOR COMPLIANT COMPLAINT SYSTEMS.
THREE PROVIDERS NOTIFY THE VICIOUS AND DANGEROUS DOG UNIT
ONE INCIDENT OCCURS. PREVENTION THOUGH IS ONLY HALF
THE EQUATION. SAN FRANCISCO'S VICIOUS
AND DANGEROUS DOG HEARING PROCESS WAS EFFECTIVELY
SUSPENDED FOR ABOUT TEN MONTHS DUE TO STAFFING AND FUNDING
ISSUES CREATING A SIGNIFICANT BACKLOG.
>> THIS CAN'T HAPPEN AGAIN. WE NEED ACCOUNTABILITY AS WELL.
WHEN I THINK SUPERVISOR CHERYL FOR HOLDING THE HEARING EARLIER
THIS YEAR WHICH HELPED TO RESURRECT THESE HEARINGS TO
PROCEED FORWARD BECAUSE THE SYSTEM THAT DETERMINES WHETHER
A DOG POSES A CONTINUING THREAT NEEDS SUSTAINED FUNDING
AND STAFFING NOT A STOP AND START APPROACH.
>> I WANT TO THANK AS A PD THE DEPARTMENT OF POLICE
ACCOUNTABILITY, ANIMAL CARE AND CONTROL, THE CITY
ADMINISTRATOR'S OFFICE AND THE MAYOR'S OFFICE FOR BRINGING THE
HEARING PROCESS BACK ONLINE. AS OF OCTOBER 6TH THAT
RESPONSIVENESS MATTERS AND THE RESOLUTION ALSO URGES THE CITY
AND COUNTY TO KEEP THE HEARING PROCESS AND THE VICIOUS
AND DANGEROUS DOG UNITS SUSTAINABLY RESOURCED GOING
FORWARD. >> I'VE HAD PRODUCTIVE
DISCUSSIONS WITH THE MAYOR'S OFFICE AND DEPARTMENT
STAKEHOLDERS WHO ARE EVALUATING THESE PROPOSED CHANGES AND I
APPRECIATE THEIR ENGAGEMENT AS RESPONSIBLE PET OWNERSHIP
AND SAFE PUBLIC SPACES ARE NOT COMPETING GOALS.
>> THIS RESOLUTION IS A PRACTICAL STEP FORWARD TO CLEAR
EXPECTATIONS, RELIABLE REPORTING AND COORDINATION.
WE NEED ONE THING SUPERVISOR FIELDER SAUTER, CHEN AND DORSEY
FOR THEIR EARLY CO-SPONSORSHIP. THE REST I SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MR. PRESIDENT.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUES SAY I HAVE AN
ORDINANCE AND TWO IN MEMORIAM. THE ORDINANCE WOULD EXEMPT
ADULT SEX VENUES AND ADULT BUSINESSES FROM THE PLANNING
CODE STOREFRONT TRANSPARENCY REQUIREMENTS.
THIS IS THE FOURTH PIECE OF LEGISLATION THAT I HAVE
INTRODUCED TO TRY TO GIVE SAN FRANCISCO'S BATHHOUSES AND SEX
VENUES A LAWFUL PATH TO OPERATE AGAIN IN OUR NEIGHBORHOODS
INCLUDING THE CASTRO AND SOMA. IN 2020 THE BOARD REWROTE THE
HEALTH CODE TO REMOVE AIDS ERA RULES REQUIRING PATRON
MONITORING AND BANNING LOCKED DOORS IN 2022.
WE FIXED A PLANNING CODE MISMATCH THAT KEPT THESE VENUES
BARRED FROM NEARLY EVERY NEIGHBORHOOD IN THE CITY.
IN 2024 WE REPEALED A 1973 POLICE CODE REQUIREMENT THAT
OPERATORS KEEP A DAILY REGISTER OF PATRONS NAMES AND ADDRESSES.
THE GOOD NEWS IS THAT WOULD BE OPERATORS ARE ATTEMPTING TO TO
TO USE THIS LEGISLATION THESE PIECES OF LEGISLATION
AND ACTUALLY OPEN REOPEN THE BATHHOUSES.
THE BAD NEWS IS THAT EACH OPERATOR WHO DOES THIS FINDS
SEEMINGLY A NEW BARRIER. TODAY'S OBSTACLE IS A PLANNING
CODE RULE THAT REQUIRES MOST GROUND FLOOR COMMERCIAL USES
IN OUR NEIGHBORHOOD COMMERCIAL AND MIXED USE DISTRICTS TO
INSTALL TRANSPARENT STREET FACING WINDOWS REPRODUCTIVE
HEALTH CLINICS, RELIGIOUS INSTITUTIONS, MORTUARIES,
HOMELESS SHELTERS, CHILDCARE FACILITIES AND SCHOOLS ARE
EXEMPTED BECAUSE THEIR WORK DEPENDS ON PRIVACY RATHER THAN
VISIBILITY. THIS ORDINANCE WOULD EXTEND
THAT RECOGNITION FOR THAT EXEMPTION TO ADULT SEX VENUES
AND ADULT BUSINESSES. FUNCTIONALLY THIS CHANGE
REMOVES THE NEED FOR COSTLY BUILDING MODIFICATIONS TO
PROTECT PATRON PRIVACY, MAKING THESE BUSINESSES MORE VIABLE
IN NEIGHBORHOODS WHERE THEY ONCE OPERATED AND MAY YET
AGAIN. I WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR
DORSEY FOR HIS EARLY CO-SPONSORSHIP.
I WANT TO THANK DEPUTY CITY ATTORNEY JULIA GARCON NELSON
FOR HER WORK. >> I WANT TO THANK RONELL BUT
JOY IN MY OFFICE FOR HIS WORK. >> THE FIRST OF THE IN MEMORIAM
THAT SUPERVISOR CHEN AND I ARE INTRODUCING IS A REQUEST THAT
WE ADJOURN TODAY'S MEETING IN MEMORY OF MAILING ZHU LO
WIDOW OF CALIFORNIA COURT OF APPEAL JUSTICE HARRY LO WHO
DIED ON JULY 26 AT THE AGE OF 96.
>> MAILING WAS BORN IN FRESNO ON AUGUST 4TH, 1929 TO CHINESE
IMMIGRANTS DUC LIM JO AND GONG C AND SPENT MUCH OF HER
CHILDHOOD IN BAKERSFIELD. >> WHEN SHE WAS NOT AT SCHOOL,
SHE WORKED AT HER FAMILY'S GROCERY STORE.
JO'S NATIONAL SHE WAS A PROUD GRADUATE OF THE UNIVERSITY OF
CALIFORNIA AT BERKELEY WHERE SHE EARNED A B.S. IN DIETETICS.
AT A TIME WHEN FEW WOMEN ATTEND COLLEGE PURSUING HIGHER
EDUCATION REFLECTED THE DETERMINATION AND STRENGTH SHE
CARRIED THROUGHOUT HER LIFE. MAILING MET HARRY LOWE AT CAL
AND THEY MARRIED IN 1952. >> SHE WORKED AS A DIETICIAN TO
SUPPORT HER YOUNG FAMILY WHILE HARRY ATTENDED LAW SCHOOL
BEFORE DEVOTING HERSELF FULLY TO RAISING HER THREE CHILDREN.
ATTENDING COUNTLESS SWIM MEETS PIANO RECITALS AND TRACK MEETS,
SHE INSISTED THAT EVERYONE'S BIRTHDAY BE APPROPRIATE.
APPROPRIATELY CELEBRATED EVERY HOLIDAY MARKED WITH A GATHERING
AND SHE PLANNED FREQUENT CRUISES AND VACATIONS TO
HAWAII. AS HARRY BECAME MORE PROMINENT
IN THE COMMUNITY, MAYLING STARTED JOINING HIM AT
COMMUNITY AND POLITICAL EVENTS OFTEN WEARING OUTFITS THAT SHE
HAD MADE HERSELF AND ALWAYS BRINGING HER OWN SENSE OF STYLE
AND GRACE. HER HOME WAS FILLED WITH HER
WATERCOLOR AND OIL PAINTINGS OF FLORAL STILL LIFES LANDSCAPES
AND FAMILY PORTRAITS. LASTING REMINDERS OF HER
CREATIVITY AND ARTISTIC EYE MAYLING AND HARRY MADE THEIR
HOME IN DIAMOND HEIGHTS WHERE THEY LIVED FOR 64 YEARS FOR THE
COUPLE PURCHASING A HOME IN SAN FRANCISCO WAS NO SMALL
ACHIEVEMENT AT THE TIME THEY PURCHASED THAT HOME.
CHINESE-AMERICANS FACED SIGNIFICANT BARRIERS TO
HOMEOWNERSHIP INCLUDING SELLERS WHO REFUSED TO SELL TO CHINESE
BUYERS AND RACIALLY RESTRICTIVE COVENANTS IN NEIGHBORHOODS
ACROSS THE CITY. DIAMOND HEIGHTS WAS ONE OF THE
FEW PLACES WHERE THEY WERE ABLE TO PURCHASE A HOME AND MAILING
CAME TO LOVE BOTH THE HOUSE AND THE COMMUNITY AROUND IT.
SHE KNEW MOST OF THE NEIGHBORS ON HER BLOCK ON TURQUOISE WAY
AND SPENT PLENTY OF TIME AT THE DIAMOND HEIGHTS SHOPPING
CENTER. ALWAYS ON THE LOOKOUT FOR THE
BEST DEALS AT SAFEWAY AND LAMENTING THE LOSS OF HER
FAVORITE CHINESE RESTAURANT HARBOR VILLA.
WHEN HER CHILDREN WERE YOUNG SHE COULD OFTEN BE FOUND
CRAWLING THE THREE HOME FROM THE GEORGE CHRISTOPHER
PLAYGROUND OR THE DIAMOND HEIGHTS SIDE OF GLEN PARK
CANYON. I GOT TO MEET MAE LANG WHILE
KNOCKING ON DOORS IN DIAMOND HEIGHTS AS A CANDIDATE.
HER SON ALAN TOLD ME TELLS ME THAT I MADE A POSITIVE
IMPRESSION. THOSE WHO KNEW MAILING WILL
REMEMBER HER ELEGANCE, DETERMINATION HUGE HEART
AND LIVELY SPIRIT. SHE WAS GENEROUS AND STRONG,
PRIVATE YET DEEPLY LOVING AND OPINIONATED IN A WAY THAT
REFLECTED HER INTELLIGENCE CONVICTION AND SOPHISTICATION.
SHE KNEW WHAT SHE BELIEVED AND HER FAMILY ALWAYS FELT THE
DEPTH OF HER LOVE. SHE IS SURVIVED BY HER CHILDREN
LARRY, CATHY AND ALAN. GRANDCHILDREN RACHEL, JENNIFER
QUINLAN AND IAN. AND GREAT GRANDCHILDREN ZIGGY,
LOUISA, NICO AND OTIS. REST IN PEACE AND POWER MAILING
LO. >> MAY YOUR MEMORY BE A
BLESSING. SUPERVISOR CHEN THANK YOU
PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN FOR HONORING THE MEMORY OF MAILING
LO MAILING AND HER HUSBAND JUDGE CARRIE LO WERE BOTH A
TRAILBLAZER IN THE CHINESE AMERICAN COMMUNITY.
THEY WERE DEEPLY DEDICATED TO COMMUNITY SERVICES TO A NUMBER
OF ORGANIZATIONS BOTH THEIR SONS VERY LOW IN L.A. HAVE
CONTINUED AT THIS LEGACY AS LAWYERS WHO HAVE DEDICATED TIME
TO SERVING THE CHINESE AMERICAN COMMUNITY WITH PRO-BONO LEGAL
WORK AND SERVED OUR CITY AS APPOINTED COMMISSIONERS.
MY CONDOLENCES TO THE LOST FAMILY AS THEY MOURN THE LOSS
OF THEIR BELOVED MOTHER AND GRANDMOTHER.
>> THANK YOU. AND IF IF THERE AREN'T
OBJECTIONS AND IF PEOPLE WOULD LIKE WE COULD HAVE THIS COME
FROM THE FULL BOARD. ALL RIGHT.
SO I'M GOING TO MAKE A MOTION THAT WE HAVE THIS COME FROM THE
FULL BOARD AND THE MOTION IS APPROVED.
>> ALL RIGHT. MY SECOND IN MEMORIAM TODAY IS
FOR TOM FRANKEL, THE LONGTIME OWNER OF FINNEGANS WAKE
AND BLOOM SLOAN WHO DIED ON AUGUST 14TH AT THE AGE OF 86.
HE WAS BORN ON JUNE 26TH, 1940 IN SAINT LOUIS, MISSOURI.
SOME OF HIS FONDEST CHILDHOOD MEMORIES WERE MADE AT CAMP
THUNDERBIRD WHERE HE SPENT HIS SUMMERS AND HE EVENTUALLY
EARNED THE RANK OF EAGLE SCOUT .
AFTER GRADUATING FROM HIGH SCHOOL, TOM ATTENDED PRINCETON
UNIVERSITY FOR A YEAR BEFORE DECIDING IT WAS NOT THE RIGHT
FIT FOR HIM. HE WENT ON TO ATTEND SEVERAL
OTHER COLLEGES INCLUDING NORTHWESTERN BEFORE GRADUATING
FROM SAINT LOUIS UNIVERSITY. ALTHOUGH HE LATER EARNED HIS
J.D. FROM WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY AND PASSED THE BAR EXAM, HE
DECIDED AGAINST PRACTICING LAW AS A CAREER.
HE WORKED A VARIETY OF JOBS INCLUDING AS A CROSSING GUARD
AND BUS DRIVER AT THE LOCAL JCC WHERE HE MET HIS FUTURE WIFE
JOAN. IN LATE 1969, TOM AND JOAN
DECIDED TO LEAVE THE MIDWEST BEHIND AND BEGIN A NEW CHAPTER
TOGETHER IN SAN FRANCISCO. FOLLOWING THEIR MOVE, HE WORKED
AS A SALESMAN, A RIVETER AND A SCENIC PAINTER FOR THE SAN
FRANCISCO OPERA AND BALLET WHERE JOAN ALSO WORKED AS THE
HEAD SCULPTOR. IN 1976, TOM AND SEVERAL
PARTNERS OPENED HIS FIRST BAR FINNEGANS WAKE IN NOVI VALLEY.
THE BAR QUICKLY BECAME A BELOVED NEIGHBORHOOD GATHERING
PLACE. IN 1984 THE LANDLORD DECLINED
TO RENEW THE LEASE FOR UNKNOWN REASONS BRINGING THE BAR'S
EIGHT YEAR RUN IN NO VALLEY TO A CLOSE.
>> FOR THE NEXT FIVE YEARS HE SEARCHED FOR A NEW LOCATION FOR
FINNEGANS WAKE BUT WAS OUTBID SEVERAL TIMES.
IN THE MEANTIME HE FOCUSED ON RUNNING BLOOM SALOON AND OTHER
NEIGHBORHOOD BAR HE OPENED IN POTRERO HILL IN 1982.
>> TOM REOPENED FINNEGANS WAKE AND COAL VALLEY IN 1989, TAKING
OVER THE FORMER LESBIAN BAR MOD STUDY HONORING LOCATION'S
HISTORY. HE PRESERVED MUCH OF STUDIES
INTERIOR AND MADE SURE IT REMAINED A BAR THAT WAS
WELCOMING FOR EVERYONE FROM 29 TO 26.
HE ALSO HOSTED THE ANNUAL MODS REUNION ON THE SATURDAY OF
PRIDE WEEKEND BRINGING FORMER PATRONS AND FRIENDS BACK
TOGETHER TO CELEBRATE THE BAR'S HISTORY.
>> AS WITH ITS ORIGINAL LOCATION, FINNEGANS WAKE
QUICKLY BECAME A POPULAR NEIGHBORHOOD GATHERING PLACE
AND IN THE 37 YEARS SINCE FINNEGANS WAKE HAS BEEN A
FIXTURE OF BECOME A FIXTURE OF COAL VALLEY DRAWING REGULARS
FROM THROUGHOUT SAN FRANCISCO AND BEYOND.
FINNEGANS WAKE HAS ONE SAN FRANCISCO BLOODY MARY FESTIVALS
FIVE YEARS IN A ROW AND EARNED MENTIONS BY FAMED CHRONICLE
COLUMNIST HERB CAEN AND THE L.A. TIMES FOR FINNEGANS WAKE
AND BLOOM SALOON SALOON HOSTED ANNUAL PICNICS FOR MEMORIAL DAY
AND LABOR DAY AS WELL AS THE 4TH OF JULY ALONG WITH THE
ANNUAL SUPER BOWL WATCH PARTIES .
THEY'VE THEY'VE SPONSORED OR HOSTED MULTIPLE SEASONAL SPORTS
LEAGUES INCLUDING POOL DARTS, SOFTBALL AND A WOMEN'S SOCCER
TEAM HELP PAY FOR DAILY SIDEWALK CLEANINGS NEAR THE
BARS AND DONATE ANNUALLY TO SEVERAL CHARITIES THAT PROVIDE
SERVICES TO DISENFRANCHIZED AND UNDERSERVED COMMUNITIES.
>> OUTSIDE OF HIS LIFE AS A BAR OWNER, TOM COACHED HIS
DAUGHTER'S SOCCER TEAM NEVER MISSED A FIELD TRIP AND WAS
ALWAYS WILLING TO SERVE AS A MENTOR AND SOURCE OF GUIDANCE
TO ANY KID WHO NEEDED HIM. HE WAS AN ENTHUSIASTIC
SUPPORTER OF SAN FRANCISCO'S MUSIC THEATER AND SPORTS.
HE HELD SEASON TICKETS TO THE GOLDEN STATE WARRIORS, SAN JOSE
SHARKS AND SAN FRANCISCO GIANTS.
>> HE WAS A DEVOTED 40 NINERS FAN AS WELL THOUGH HE PREFERRED
TO WATCH THEIR GAMES FROM HIS OWN OWNER'S BOX AT FINNEGANS
WAKE WHERE HE COULD CHEER ON THE TEAM ALONGSIDE HIS REGULAR
CUSTOMERS. A SKILLED SHARPSHOOTER TOM ALSO
TAUGHT MARKSMANSHIP AND GUN SAFETY TO BOY SCOUT TROOPS
AND THE GENERAL PUBLIC. HE WAS PRESIDENT OF RICHMOND
ROD AND GUN CLUB FOR MANY YEARS AND VISITED COUNTLESS SHOOTING
COMPETITIONS AS A MEMBER OF MULTIPLE BAY AREA GUN CLUBS.
HE LEAVES BEHIND HIS WIFE JOAN DAUGHTER LINDA AND FUTURE SON
IN LAW JASON AS WELL AS MITCH LEIGH, SYLVIA WANG AND THEIR
CHILDREN JADEN AND GUNNAR. HE WILL ALSO BE MISSED BY THE
PATRONS OF FINNEGANS WAKE AND BLOOM SALON AND SALOON
AND BY HIS MANY MANY FRIENDS. REST IN PEACE TOM FRANKEL.
MAY YOUR MEMORY BE A BLESSING AND THE REST I SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. SUPERVISOR MELGAR.
THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. >> I WILL START WITH A REPORT
ON MY OUTSIDE BOARDS AND COMMISSIONS.
I AM EUROPE PRESENTED TO THE MTC AT THIS MORNING AT THE CTA
. >> WE APPROVE SOME OF OUR
RECOMMENDATIONS FOR WHAT WE HAVE BEEN DOING AT THE MTC,
PARTICULARLY AT THE PROGRAMING AND ALLOCATIONS COMMITTEE WHICH
I I OF WHICH I AM THE VICE CHAIR IS APPROVING THE TRANCHES
OF IN THE TIMING OF THE ALLOCATION OF THIS FEDERAL
MONEY WHICH AMOUNTS TO ABOUT $750 MILLION OVER EIGHT YEARS
TO SUPPORT THE REGIONAL TRANSPORTATION PRIORITIES
IN THE NINE COUNTY BAY AREA REGION IN ADDITION TO OUR ONE
BAY AREA GRANT PRIORITIES WHICH SUPPORT TRANSIT ORIENTED
COMMUNITIES, CLIMATE CHANGE AND PUBLIC TRANSIT.
SO I AM REALLY HAPPY TO REPORT THAT DESPITE SOMETIMES NOT
AGREEING ON PRIORITIES WITH OUR NEIGHBORS WE HAVE DEFINITELY
GOTTEN THERE WITH THIS MONEY. AS PART OF MY MTC COMMISSION
WORK I ALSO SIT ON THE BOARD OF THE OF BARR FOR THE BAY AREA
HOUSING FINANCING AGENCY. THANKS FOR TOUCHING ON THAT AT
SUPERVISOR DORSEY. >> WE HAVE HAD ABOUT A YEAR OF
COORDINATION AND MEETING WITH SACO SOLDIERS INCLUDING
NONPROFITS, TENANTS RIGHTS GROUPS, DEVELOPERS
AND MUNICIPAL DECISION MAKERS TO COME TO A CONSENSUS ON HOW
TO PROCEED FOR A POSSIBLE BALLOT INITIATIVE IN 2028 TO
PROVIDE A FUNDING SOURCE FOR A REGIONAL HOUSING FUND WHICH WE
ALL DEFINITELY NEED. AS YOU MAY REMEMBER LAST YEAR
WE ALL NEGOTIATED AROUND SB 63 THE REGIONAL TRANSIT MEASURE
THAT IS ON THE BALLOT FOR NOVEMBER.
THAT WAS FIVE COUNTIES AND A YEAR FULL OF WORK
AND NEGOTIATING OUR PRIORITIES. THIS WILL BE NINE COUNTIES
AND CREATING A HOUSING FUND WHICH IS THE CHALLENGE FOR THE
BAY AREA. BUT EVERYONE AT LEAST
RECOGNIZES THE PROBLEM WITH THE AFFORDABILITY IN THE SAN
FRANCISCO BAY AREA AND WE'RE ALL VERY MOTIVATED TO MEET IT.
WE HAVE CREATED A STAKEHOLDER STEERING COMMITTEE THAT
INCLUDES PHILANTHROPY, LABOR AND THE DEVELOPMENT COMMUNITY
AND SO FAR THE MEETINGS HAVE BEEN VERY POSITIVE AND WE'RE
WORKING ALL TOGETHER IN THE RIGHT DIRECTION.
WITH THAT I WOULD LIKE TO SHARE WITH YOU SOME DRAFTING REQUESTS
THAT MY OFFICE HAS BEEN WORKING ON WITH THE CITY ATTORNEY THAT
I EXPECT WE WILL BE INTRODUCING IN THE UPCOMING WEEKS TO
ADVANCE OUR CITY IN MEETING OUR TRANSIT AND HOUSING NEEDS.
>> THE FIRST IS THE CREATION THE PROMOTION OF OUR EXISTING
MAYOR'S OFFICE OF HOUSING AND COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT INTO
A DEPARTMENT OF HOUSING PRODUCTION AND PRESERVATION.
NEXT I AM ALSO INTRODUCED. >> I WILL BE INTRODUCING THE
CREATION OF A PROGRAM FOR THE SUPPORT, FINANCING
AND REFINANCING OF COOPERATIVE HOUSING IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> AS LONG AS WE CAN REMEMBER THE LOCAL AGENCY TASKED WITH
THE DEVELOPMENT OF AFFORDABLE HOUSING IN SAN FRANCISCO HAS
BEEN A SMALL DIVISION OF THE MAYOR'S OFFICE.
COMPARE THIS TO OTHER CITIES THAT HAVE FULL FLEDGED
DEPARTMENT EVENTS LIKE NEW YORK OR CHICAGO OR WASHINGTON DC.
OUR INFRASTRUCTURE IS A LITTLE BIT LACKING.
SAN FRANCISCO IS BEING TASKED WITH A MONUMENTAL EXERCISE TO
PRODUCE 82,000 NEW HOMES BY JANUARY OF 2031.
THE MAYOR'S OFFICE OF HOUSING PRIMARILY FOCUS ON FOCUSES ON
100% AFFORDABLE HOUSING IN THE MANAGEMENT OF THIS UNIT BUT IT
COULD DO MUCH, MUCH MORE IF IT WERE INTEGRATED AND COORDINATED
WITH OUR OTHER EFFORTS. 82,000 UNITS HALF OF THESE NEED
TO BE AFFORDABLE. >> WHAT IF WE HAD A DEPARTMENT
THAT WEEK THAT COULD LEVERAGE MORE FINANCING, PROVIDE POLICY
DIRECTION AND PLANNING FOR AFFORDABLE HOUSING AND ALSO
PLAN FOR ITS RELATIONSHIP TO MARKET RATE HOUSING FOR ALL THE
TYPES OF HOUSING THAT WE NEED IN LARGE DEVELOPMENTS IN SMALL
DEVELOPMENTS. THE DEPARTMENT COULD ALSO
EXPAND ITS RESOURCES AND TOOLS FOR PRESERVING EXISTING HOUSING
AND KEEPING MORE RESIDENTS STABILIZED IN THEIR OWN
COMMUNITIES. >> I BELIEVE THAT WE CAN BE
BOLDER AND MORE DELIBERATE IN HOW WE PLAN FOR OUR FUTURE
WHICH WE KNOW MUST INCLUDE AFFORDABLE HOUSING.
>> THIS LEGISLATION WILL PROVIDE THE FRAMEWORK IN THE
CREATION OF THE DEPARTMENT AND ALSO DETERMINE THE BEST WAY
TO CONSOLIDATE WORK AREAS OR BETTER COORDINATE WITH OTHER
AGENCIES. IN THE FUTURE OTHER LEGISLATIVE
BODIES THAT COME AFTER US AND OTHER MAYORS CAN FILL OUT
THAT ENVELOPE AS IT MAKES SENSE AND EVOLVE THE MODELS.
BETTER COORDINATION IS NEEDED WITH THE HOUSING AUTHORITY.
OCI THE OFFICE OF ECONOMIC WORKFORCE DEVELOPMENT AND THE
DEPARTMENT OF HOMELESSNESS AND SUPPORTIVE HOUSING AS WELL
AS THE RENT BOARD. NOW THERE IS PRECEDENT FOR
THIS. WE ONCE DID HAVE A MAYOR'S
OFFICE OF ECONOMIC AND WORKFORCE DEVELOPMENT WHICH
WE PROMOTED INTO A FULL FLEDGED DEPARTMENT WITH GREAT SUCCESS
AND I'M HOPING WE CAN DO THE SAME FOR AFFORDABLE HOUSING
IN THE FUTURE. I AM LOOKING FORWARD TO A
COLLABORATIVE APPROACH TO HOW BEST TO SET THIS UP AT THIS
DEPARTMENT WITH ALL OF YOU WITH ALL YOUR INPUT.
BUT ALSO WORKING WITH OUR MAYOR.
>> NOW AS A PART OF A LARGER VISION FOR HOUSING IN THE
FUTURE OF SAN FRANCISCO, WE NEED A DIVERSITY OF OPTIONS
WHICH INCLUDES NEW TYPES OF HOUSING HOMEOWNERSHIP LIKE
LIMITED EQUITY CO-OP COOPERATIVES BUT ALSO JUST
COLLAPSE. >> I WILL BE INTRODUCING THIS
LEGISLATION FOR A PROGRAM TO INCREASE SUPPORT FOR
COOPERATIVELY OWNED HOUSING. THIS WOULD INCLUDE SUPPORTING
THE CREATION, FINANCING, REFINANCING AND TECHNICAL
TRAINING FOR RESIDENTS TO MANAGE THEIR BUILDINGS.
CO-OPS ARE ONE OF THE MOST AFFORDABLE AND ACCESSIBLE
PATHWAYS TO HOMEOWNERSHIP AND TO BUILD EQUITY FOR
RESIDENTS. >> THEY CAN HELP THOSE WHO MAY
BE PRICED OUT OF TRADITIONAL MORTGAGE PROGRAMS AND OFFER A
CHANCE FOR SELF-DETERMINATION AND COMMUNITY BUILDING BONDS.
>> CO-OPS HAVE A DOUBLE BOTTOM LINE OF LEADERSHIP DEVELOPMENT
AND HOUSING STABILITY IN OTHER CITIES LIKE NEW YORK,
WASHINGTON, D.C. IN THE STATE OF BRITISH COLUMBIA.
CO-OP HOUSING IS ONE OF THE MAIN WAYS HOUSING IS PRESERVED
AND PRODUCED. THEY CAN BE AN ALTERNATIVE TO
RESTRICTIVE LOW INCOME HOUSING RULES AND ANNUAL INCOME
VERIFICATION. >> BUT THEY DO REQUIRE
SPECIALIZED PROGRAMING, FINANCING AND REAL SUPPORT.
THERE ARE NOW ABOUT 1600 CO-OP UNITS IN SAN FRANCISCO ALREADY
BUT WE STOPPED BUILDING THEM IN THE 1970S SO NEWER ONES HAVE
BEEN A RARITY. MEANWHILE IN MANHATTAN THERE
ARE ROUGHLY 400,000 CO-OP UNITS WHICH MAKE UP NEARLY 75% OF ALL
OWNED RESIDENTIAL HOUSING STOCK .
COLLAPSE HAVE BEEN THE PATHWAY FOR MIDDLE CLASS AND FOR
PROVIDING STABLE HOUSING IN NEW YORK.
THEY HAVE A DEPARTMENT AND PROGRAMS JUST TO SUPPORT
THEM. SAN FRANCISCO NEEDS THIS ON OUR
OWN AND ALSO I AM ANNOUNCING LEGISLATION TO FURTHER
COORDINATE THE REPAVING OF OUR STREETS AND HOW THAT RELATES TO
OUR ALREADY APPROVED BICYCLE NETWORK.
REPAVING IS A COMPLEX ENDEAVOR THAT REQUIRES ENGINEERING
AND DESIGN WORK FOR MULTIPLE DEPARTMENTS.
OUR LEGISLATION WILL REQUIRE THAT THE MTA COMPLETE THE
ENGINEERING AND DESIGN WORK FOR THE BICYCLE NETWORK PRIOR TO
THE APPROVAL FOR THE REPAVING PLAN SO THAT THE MONEY FOLLOWS
FROM RTA AS REPAVING IS HAPPENING.
STREAMLINING IS A WORD THAT GETS USED A LOT LATELY IN THIS
BUILDING AND THIS LEGISLATION JUST ENSURES THAT WE DON'T LOSE
THE OPPORTUNITY FOR BUILDING BIKE INFRASTRUCTURE AS WE ARE
DOING THE NEEDED WORK OF REPAVING DUE TO THE TIMING
AND THE LACK OF COORDINATION BETWEEN THE DEPARTMENTS RIGHT
NOW. >> SO WITH THAT THOSE ARE THE
PRIORITIES THAT I'VE BEEN WORKING ON AND I HOPE FOR YOUR
SUPPORT AND THE REST. MADAM CLERK I SUBMIT THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR MELGAR.
>> SUPERVISOR SAUTER. THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM INTRODUCING LEGISLATION TO
PROTECT TENANTS FROM SURPRISE AND DEVASTATING RENT HIKES.
WE WILL DO SO BY CAPPING BANKED RENT INCREASES AND CAPITAL
IMPROVEMENT PASSTHROUGH AT 10% FOR RENT CONTROLLED TENANTS
IN OUR CITY. STARTING TODAY AND LASTING
THROUGH THE END OF 2029. BACK IN JULY WE COMMISSIONED A
BILL A REPORT ON THE SUBJECT AS THE REPORT WILL REVEAL, SAN
FRANCISCO STANDS ALONE IN ITS LACK OF PROTECTIONS FOR TENANTS
AMONGST CALIFORNIA CITIES THAT ALLOW RENT BANKING.
THIS IS A DISPLACING FORCE IN OUR CITY THAT OFTEN ISN'T
TALKED ABOUT ENOUGH. IT MOST DIRECTLY AFFECTS OLDER
TENANTS AND FAMILIES WHO STAY IN THEIR HOMES LONG TERM.
THIS BODY HAS MADE CLEAR ITS COMMITMENT TO MINIMIZING
DISPLACEMENT, SUPPORTING LONG TERM TENANTS AND KEEPING
FAMILIES IN THEIR HOMES AS OUR CITY BUILDS MORE HOUSING.
IN THIS CHANGES ONE OF THE MOST POWERFUL TOOLS WE HAVE AS A
CITY TO IMMEDIATELY MAKE HOUSING MORE STABLE FOR LONG
TERM TENANTS. >> EACH TIME A BANK RENT
INCREASE HAPPENS IT CAN THREATEN SOMEONE LIKE SOMEONE'S
LIVELIHOOD. IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> JUST TODAY I HEARD FROM A FAMILY IN THE MISSION WHO HAS
LIVED IN THEIR HOME FOR MORE THAN 20 YEARS AND WAS HIT WITH
A 25% RENT INCREASE ALL AT ONCE.
THAT RENT INCREASE RAISED THEIR RENT BY $500 A MONTH AND MOST
FAMILIES CAN'T AFFORD OR ABSORB AN INCREASE LIKE THAT THIS
SUMMER. I LEARNED OF A 92 YEAR OLD
TENANT IN MY DISTRICT WHO SAW HER RENT SKYROCKET FROM $600 TO
MORE THAN $2,000 A MONTH IN ONE FELL SWOOP.
>> TODAY LANDLORDS ARE NOT REQUIRED TO REPORT BANKED RENT
INCREASES ANYWHERE. WE HAVE NO IDEA WHERE AND HOW
OFTEN THESE HUGE INCREASES ARE HAPPENING.
OUR LEGISLATION WILL REQUIRE LANDLORDS TO START REPORTING
THE FREQUENCY OF THESE INCREASES TO THE RENT BOARD TO
HELP INFORM THIS BOARD'S FUTURE POLICY DECISIONS AROUND THIS
CAP. >> WE KNOW THE IDEA OF CAPPING
DATA TO RENT INCREASES HAS BEEN FLOATED FOR DECADES.
IT IS ONE OF THE LAST REMAINING LOOPHOLES IN OUR LAWS TO
PROTECT TENANTS FROM LIFE ALTERING RENT INCREASES.
>> WE'VE WAITED LONG ENOUGH AND WE NOW FIND OURSELVES IN AN
EMERGENCY WHERE PAINT RENT INCREASES ARE A TICKING TIME
BOMB FOR TOO MANY TENANTS. I BELIEVE IT'S TIME TO CLOSE
THIS LOOPHOLE. >> I WANT TO GIVE MY THANKS TO
MAYOR LURIE AND HIS TEAM FOR THEIR SUPPORT AND PARTNERSHIP
ON THIS LEGISLATION AND THANK EARLY CO-SPONSORS AS
SUPERVISORS CHEN AND MAHMUD. THANK YOU AS WELL TO THE MANY
TENANT GROUPS FOR THEIR FEEDBACK ON IMPROVING THIS ITEM
AND TO THE TENDERLOIN HOUSING CLINIC IN PARTICULAR FOR THEIR
SUPPORT AND ADVOCACY ON MAKING THIS HAPPEN.
I ALSO WANT TO THANK MICHELLE ANDREWS IN MY OFFICE FOR HER
WORK IN CITY ATTORNEY MONA PRAN AND THE REST I SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU SUPERVISOR SAUTER SUPERVISOR CHERYL COLLEAGUES.
>> TODAY I'M SUBMITTING A MOTION ON A RATHER SENSITIVE
TOPIC THAT HAS CAUSED MUCH CONSTERNATION THROUGHOUT THE
CITY AND DEFINITELY ON THIS BODY.
I'LL BE SUBMITTING A MOTION THAT IS BASED ON A MONTH LONG
INVESTIGATION THAT'S BASED ON GREAT JOURNALISM AND THAT IS
SOMETHING WE PROBABLY DON'T WANT TO HAVE TO ENGAGE IN.
>> BUT TODAY THIS MOTION IS GOING TO BE REGARDING
SUSPENDING COMMISSIONER WILLIAM PALMER FROM THE SHERIFF'S
DEPARTMENT OVERSIGHT BOARD AND APPROVING CHARGES OF
OFFICIAL MISCONDUCT AGAINST COMMISSIONER PALMER OVER THE
NEXT FEW WEEKS. WE WILL I LOOK FORWARD TO
MOVING FORWARD THIS PROCESS. IT'S A LONG PROCESS.
>> THERE WILL BE PLENTY OF CHANCES FOR EVERYONE TO DIG IN.
BUT I LOOK FORWARD TO MOVING THIS FORWARD SO THAT WE CAN
ENSURE THAT THIS OVERSIGHT BOARD IS FOCUSED ON OUR
SHERIFF'S DEPARTMENT, ON THE JAILS THAT WE HAVE IN THE CITY
AND NOT FOCUSED ON ANCILLARY TOPICS THAT DISTRACT FROM
ENSURING THE CITY BUSINESS GOES FORWARD AT THE END OF THE DAY.
>> WE NEED TO MAKE SURE THAT PEOPLE IN LEADERSHIP ARE
UPHOLDING THE COMMITMENT THEY MADE, THE OATH THAT THEY TAKE
WHEN TAKING THOSE LEADERSHIP POSITIONS AND I THINK THIS IS
PART OF IT. I THINK IT'S NOTHING LESS THAN
OUR DUTY TO MOVE THIS FORWARD AND I LOOK FORWARD TO HAVING
YOUR SUPPORT AS WE PROCESS ON THIS JOURNEY TOGETHER.
>> THE REST I SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR CHERYL SUPERVISOR WALTON, THANK YOU SO MUCH MADAM
CLERK. FIRST COLLEAGUES, I HAVE JUST A
COUPLE OF VERY QUICK EXTERNAL BOARD UPDATES.
KOTORI LIEN HAS REALLY BEEN FOCUSED ON SAFETY
AND CONTINUING THE TREND OF PERFORMING BETTER THAN NATIONAL
AVERAGE FOR THE REPORTABLE INJURY RATE ONLY 2 IN 2026
RIDERSHIP 79% OF PRE-PANDEMIC LEVELS AND WEEKEND RIDERSHIP IS
200% OF PRE-PANDEMIC LEVELS. THE JUVENILE JUSTICE
COORDINATING COUNCIL CONTINUES TO USE STATE FUNDS TO SUPPORT
THE INNOVATIVE APPROACHES TO SERVE JUVENILE JUSTICE THAT
CAME OUT OF THE PLANNING PROCESS OVER THE LAST FEW YEARS
INCLUDING THE CLOSED JUVENILE HALL WORKGROUP.
ONE OF THESE APPROACHES THE JUSTICE SERVICES CARE MODEL
CONNECTS APPROVED TO COMMUNITY SUPPORT QUICKLY AFTER ARREST
AND THIS MODEL HAS RECEIVED NATIONAL ATTENTION.
I ALSO HAVE AN ORDINANCE WHICH IS AN INTERIM ZONING MORATORIUM
ON DATA CENTERS. I'M INTRODUCING AN ORDINANCE TO
ESTABLISH A 45 DAY INTERIM ZONING MORATORIUM ON NEW DATA
CENTERS IN SAN FRANCISCO ALONG WITH CO-SPONSORS SUPERVISOR
CONNIE CHEN SUPERVISOR JACKIE FIELDER AND SUPERVISOR SHYANNE
CHEN. AND LET ME BE CLEAR ABOUT WHY
I'M BRINGING THIS FORWARD. >> SAN FRANCISCO'S RULES FOR
DATA CENTERS ARE LONG OUTDATED. >> OUR CURRENT PLANNING CODE
FRAMEWORK WAS ADOPTED IN 2001 LONG BEFORE GENERATED AND LONG
BEFORE ANYONE COULD HAVE ANTICIPATED THE ENORMOUS SCALE
OF COMPUTING INFRASTRUCTURE THAT EXISTS TODAY.
>> WE'RE NOW SEEING A RAPID EXPANSION OF A.
AND WITH THAT COMES A RAPID EXPANSION OF THE PHYSICAL
INFRASTRUCTURE NEEDED TO POWER. >> WE SHOULD NOT BE APPROVING
THIS NEW GENERATION OF INDUSTRIAL INFRASTRUCTURE UNDER
RULES THAT WERE WRITTEN 25 YEARS AGO AND WE NEED TO BE
ESPECIALLY THOUGHTFUL ABOUT WHERE THESE FACILITIES ARE
BEING LOCATED. >> SEVERAL DATA CENTERS HAVE
BEEN ALREADY APPROVED IN SAN FRANCISCO INCLUDING AND BAYVIEW
HUNTERS POINT AND SOMA BAYVIEW HUNTERS POINT.
MY COMMUNITY HAS A LONG HISTORY OF CARRYING SAN FRANCISCO'S
INDUSTRIAL AND ENVIRONMENTAL BURDENS.
>> OUR COMMUNITY HAS DEALT WITH POLLUTION LEGACY CONTAMINATION,
INDUSTRIAL USES AND OTHER ENVIRONMENTAL JUSTICE
CHALLENGES FOR GENERATIONS. >> THIS IS NOT ABOUT BEING
AGAINST TECHNOLOGY AND INNOVATION BUT INNOVATION
CANNOT COME AT THE EXPENSE OF OUR RESIDENTS HEALTH, OUR
NATURAL RESOURCES AND OUR QUALITY OF LIFE.
>> BEFORE WE APPROVE ADDITIONAL DATA CENTERS WE NEED TO
UNDERSTAND THEIR IMPACTS ON ENERGY, WATER, AIR QUALITY,
LAND USE AND SURROUNDING COMMUNITIES.
WE ALSO NEED TRANSPARENCY MEANINGFUL COMMUNITY INPUT
AND CLEAR COMMUNITY BENEFITS. >> THIS 45 DAY MORATORIUM GIVES
US THE OPPORTUNITY TO DO THAT WORK.
IT GIVES THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT AND THIS BOARD A
CHANCE TO STEP BACK STUDY WHICH IS WHAT'S HAPPENING IN THE
IMPACTS AND DEVELOP MODERN RULES THAT REFLECT THE REALITY
OF OUR INFRASTRUCTURE TODAY NOT THE TECHNOLOGY LANDSCAPE OF TWO
THOUSAND ONE. >> WE HAVE AN OPPORTUNITY TO
GET AHEAD OF THIS RATHER THAN REACTING AFTER MORE PROJECTS
ARE APPROVED BAYVIEW HUNTERS POINT AND OTHER COMMUNITIES
HAVE ALREADY SACRIFICED ENOUGH AND DESERVE BETTER.
I URGE ALL MY COLLEAGUES TO SUPPORT THIS ORDINANCE AND HELP
US ESTABLISH A FRAMEWORK WHERE SAN FRANCISCO CAN EMBRACE
INNOVATION FROM PROTECTING THE PEOPLE AND NEIGHBORHOODS THAT
MAKE THIS CITY HOME. I ALSO WANT TO RECOGNIZE THE
WORK OF MY LEGISLATIVE AIDES NATALIE JEAN AND LINDSEY LOPEZ
WEAVER, WHO WORKED CLOSELY WITH THE CITY ATTORNEY'S OFFICE TO
DEVELOP AND DRAFT THIS LEGISLATION AND LASTLY,
COLLEAGUES, I HAVE AND IN MEMORIAM TODAY WE HONOR
AND REMEMBER FELICIA FREENEY LOVINGLY KNOWN AS OPIE.
>> SHE WAS A BELOVED DAUGHTER MOTHER, SISTER, AUNTIE, WRITER,
COMMUNITY ORGANIZER AND PROUD YOUNG BLACK WOMAN.
FROM BAYVIEW HUNTERS POINT WHOSE LIFE, COURAGE AND LOVE
LEFT A LASTING IMPACT ON HER FAMILY AND HER ENTIRE
COMMUNITY. BORN AT ST LUKE'S HOSPITAL
AND RAISED IN BAYVIEW HUNTERS POINT OH WE BELIEVE DEEPLY
IN THE POWER OF EDUCATION AND WAS DETERMINED TO BUILD A
BETTER FUTURE FOR HERSELF EVEN IN THE FINAL WEEKS OF HER LIFE.
SHE CONTINUED STUDYING TOWARDS HER G.E.D..
>> OPIE EXPRESSED HERSELF THROUGH POETRY AND WRITING,
USING HER VOICE TO SPEAK ABOUT THE EXPERIENCES OF YOUNG PEOPLE
AND THE NEED FOR CHANGE. >> HER GIFTS AS A WRITER WERE
RECOGNIZED NATIONALLY INCLUDING BEING NAMED A FINALIST
IN STRATEGIES FOR YOUTH 2019 YOUTH VOICES WRITING CONTEST.
BUT OPIE'S GREATEST IMPACT CAME THROUGH HER ORGANIZING AFTER
WORKING AT OLD SCHOOL CAFÉ. SHE JOINED THE YOUNG WOMAN'S
FREEDOM CENTER WHERE SHE BECAME A POWERFUL ADVOCATE FOR SYSTEMS
CHANGE. DRAWING FROM HER OWN
EXPERIENCES WITH THE JUVENILE JUSTICE SYSTEM, SHE BECAME A
LEADER IN THE HISTORY MAKING MOVEMENT TO CLOSE SAN
FRANCISCO'S JUVENILE HALL EDGES 15 YEARS OLD.
OPIE STOOD BEFORE THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
AND BRAVELY SHARED HER EXPERIENCES.
DEMANDING THAT OUR CITY DO BETTER FOR ITS YOUNG PEOPLE.
SHE UNDERSTOOD THAT HER STORY COULD HELP CREATE A DIFFERENT
FUTURE FOR THOSE COMING BEHIND HER AND SHE REFUSED TO LET HER
APPEARANCES BE IN VAIN. >> ABOVE ALL, OPIE LOVED HER
FAMILY DEEPLY. >> SHE CARRIED PROFOUND GRIEF
AND RESPONSIBILITY AFTER LOSING BOTH HER MOTHER AND HER PARTNER
FRANCES, THE FATHER OF HER CHILD.
>> YET SHE CONTINUED TO LOVE. SHE CONTINUED TO MOTHER.
SHE CONTINUED TO WRITE AND TO ORGANIZE AND SHOW UP FOR HER
COMMUNITY. WE ARE DEVASTATED BY OPIE'S
PASSING BUT WE WILL NEVER FORGET THAT SHE WAS HERE.
>> SHE LEAVES BEHIND A LEGACY OF LOVE, GENEROSITY, HEALING,
COURAGE AND GENUINE COMMUNITY CARE.
>> MAY SAN FRANCISCO REMEMBER OPIE AS ONE OF ITS OWN?
A DAUGHTER OF BAYVIEW HUNTERS POINT.
A MOTHER SISTER. AUNTIE, WRITER, ORGANIZER
AND YOUNG WOMAN WHO LOVED HER CITY ENOUGH TO STAND BEFORE IT
AND DEMAND BETTER THE REST OF US SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR WALTON .
>> SUPERVISOR HUANG. >> COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM
INTRODUCING TWO RELATED ITEMS CONCERNING THE SAFE USE OF
E-BIKES E-SCOOTERS AND OTHER ELECTRIC MOBILITY DEVICES
IN SAN FRANCISCO. MICROMOBILITY IS AN IMPORTANT
AND GROWING PART OF OUR TRANSPORTATION SYSTEM.
IT GIVES PEOPLE MORE WAYS TO GET AROUND, REDUCES RELIANCE ON
CARS AND CAN MAKE OUR CITY MORE ACCESSIBLE AND CONNECTED.
BUT WE'RE ALSO HEARING INCREASING CONCERNS ABOUT
SAFETY, PARTICULARLY INVOLVING HIGH SPEED, HIGH POWERED
MODIFIED OR MISCLASSIFIED DEVICES AND UNSAFE RIDING
IN PLACES WHERE PEDESTRIANS AND OTHER USERS ARE ESPECIALLY
VULNERABLE. THE FIRST ITEM IS A HEARING TO
BETTER UNDERSTAND WHAT WE'RE SEEING ON OUR STREETS AND IN
OUR PARKS. WHAT TYPES OF DEVICES ARE
INVOLVED? WHAT THE INJURY DATA TELLS US
WHAT LAWS ALREADY APPLY, WHERE THE GAPS MAY BE AND WHAT OUR
CITY DEPARTMENTS ARE DOING TODAY.
I'M ALSO INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION SUPPORTING SAFE
MICROMOBILITY AND URGING EFFECTIVE ENFORCEMENT OF THE
LAWS ALREADY ON THE BOOKS. THIS IS NOT ABOUT DISCOURAGING
E-BIKES. IT'S ABOUT MAKING SURE THAT AS
MICROMOBILITY CONTINUES TO GROW IN SAN FRANCISCO OUR APPROACH
GROWS SAFELY AND RESPONSIBLY WITH IT.
>> THE ASSESSMENT. THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR WONG.
MR. PRESIDENT, THAT CONCLUDES THE ROLL CALL FOR
INTRODUCTIONS. THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
LET'S GO TO PUBLIC COMMENT. >> AT THIS TIME THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS WELCOMES YOUR GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT
IN PERSON SPEAKERS WILL BE PRIORITIZED SO PLEASE LINE UP
ON YOUR RIGHT HAND SIDE OF THE CHAMBER.
>> THOSE JOINING REMOTELY SUPERSTAR THREE NOW TO LINE UP
IN THE QUEUE. >> DURING GENERAL PUBLIC
COMMENT YOU MAY SPEAK TO THE MAYORAL APPEARANCE.
APPROVAL OF THE BOARD MEETING MINUTES.
ITEMS 51 THROUGH 59 THE ITEMS UNDER THE FOR ADOPTION WITHOUT
COMMITTEE REFERENCE AGENDA AND ANY OTHER GENERAL MATTERS
THAT ARE NOT ON THE AGENDA BUT MUST BE WITHIN THE BOARD
SUBJECT MATTER JURISDICTION. ALL OTHER AGENDA CONTENT WILL
HAVE BEEN REPORTED OUT TO THE BOARD BY AN APPROPRIATE
COMMITTEE WHERE THE PUBLIC COMMENT REQUIREMENT OCCURRED.
WILL THE FIRST SPEAKER PLEASE COME FORWARD?
CAN I PUT THE BOOK UP THERE? OKAY.
HOW DO YOU SQUEEZE IT DOWN TO SHORTEN THAT?
>> SO WE GOT YOU'RE THE HIGH TECH GAL AROUND HERE.
>> I APPRECIATE THAT. I'M STARTING THE SPEAKER'S TIME
. >> OKAY.
TWO WEEKS AGO ERIC METAXAS SIGNED AUTOGRAPHED MY COPY AT
CALVARY CHAPEL THERE IN SAN JOSE.
AND I MENTIONED HE SPOKE TWO TIMES AT 911.
AND I MENTIONED AFTER THE FIRST SERMON I SAID HEY, ERIC, YOU
DIDN'T MENTION ANYTHING ABOUT THE NATIONAL DEFENSE
AUTHORIZATION ACT, HOW ISRAEL'S GOING TO TAKE OVER OUR
MILITARY. NOT GOOD ISRAEL BAD AMERICA
GOOD. AND HE SAID I DO NOT WANT
ISRAEL TO TAKE OVER OUR MILITARY.
AND I SAID, WELL IF YOU DON'T THEN TELL THE FOLKS ON THE
SECOND SERVICE ABOUT THIS. SO AFTER THE SECOND SERVICE WAS
OVER AND I GOT MY AUTOGRAPHED COPY, I ASKED HIM, YOU KNOW,
WHY HE DIDN'T MENTION IT IN THE SECOND SERVICE AND YOU KNOW
WHAT ERIC METAXAS TOLD ME? >> THAT'S WHAT HE TOLD ME.
>> HE WAS SILENT. >> ONCE AGAIN, WE HAVE EVIDENCE
THAT WHAT THESE MEN WERE DOING WAS SEEN AS EXPLICITLY
RELIGIOUS, ALBEIT IN THE REALM OF GOVERNMENT.
THE REVOLUTION IN WHICH THEY WERE NOW ENGAGED WAS INTENDED
TO BE A RETURN TO THE ROOTS OF THE CHRISTIAN FAITH AS MUCH AS
THE REFORMATION HAD BEEN. AND IT'S INTERESTING MIKE
MCCLURE WHO IS SENIOR PASTOR THERE I WAS JUST EXCOMMUNICATED
ON TUESDAY A WEEK AGO FOR TALKING ABOUT THIS SAID HE
DOESN'T KNOW ANYTHING ABOUT A PAC.
A PAC. NOW THAT'S MAKES ME WONDER, YOU
KNOW, IS HE BEING BLACKMAILED? IS HE BEING THREATENED?
IS HE BEING GIVEN MONEY OR ALL THREE OF THE ABOVE?
I DON'T KNOW. BUT I REALLY BELIEVE WE HAVE A
GREATER JUSTIFICATION FOR GOING TO WAR WITH ISRAEL.
THAT'S ALWAYS BEEN A TERRORIST NATION.
THEY ATTACKED THE USS LIBERTY THEN IRAN.
IRAN IS. I DON'T THINK THEY DID ANYTHING
WRONG. THERE'S A GUY NAMED PROFESSOR
MARANDI, VERY REASONABLE GUY. I PRAY THAT HE BECOMES A
CHRISTIAN AND JESUS IS KING. >> OKAY.
GOD STARTED THIS NATION. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> NEXT SPEAKER THANK YOU, ELIZABETH.
>> HELLO. >> GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS AMELIA HARMON SPEAKING FROM DISTRICT NINE
IN MY INDIVIDUAL CAPACITY. ALSO AS SOMEONE IN RECOVERY ON
OCTOBER 28TH THE CRISIS RESPONDER RESPONSE STANDARDS
WORKING GROUP CONVENES TEN MEETINGS THROUGH MARCH.
THE CURRENT CITYWIDE RESTRUCTURING PERFORMANCE BASED
CONTRACTS STREET TEAM CONSOLIDATION AND THESE CHANGES
WILL BE JUDGED BY NUMBERS AND RIGHT NOW THE NUMBERS
MEASURE FRONT DOOR ARRIVAL NOT RECOVERY.
AND AS I HEARD EARLIER, RECOVERY BELONGS IN CITY HALL.
>> THE WORKING GROUP IS A WAY TO HONOR THE DAILY WORK OF OUR
PROVIDERS ACROSS OUR SYSTEM OF CARE INCLUDING OUR FIRST
RESPONDERS AND TO LEAVE BEHIND SOMETHING DURABLE LINKED DATA
PATHWAYS A SYSTEM UNDER THIS MUCH PRESSURE CANNOT AFFORD TO
KEEP EVALUATING ITSELF ONE SEGMENT AT A TIME.
>> LET'S EQUIP OUR CRISIS TEAM AS THE DIAGNOSTIC TOOL IT WAS
BUILT TO BE. >> WHERE ARE THE GAPS IN OUR
EVER IMPROVING SYSTEM AND WHERE DO PEOPLE FALL THROUGH THE
CRACKS IN YOUR DISTRICTS? ASK YOUR SHELTERS.
ASK YOUR CLINICS, ASK YOUR REHABS.
ASK YOUR STATION CAPTAINS NEXT TIME YOU SEE ONE OF THE RED
STREET CRISIS FANS, I ENCOURAGE YOU TO FLAG ONE DOWN AND ASK
THEM WHAT THEY THINK ABOUT FAILED SHELTER REFERRALS WHEN A
CLINIC SHIFT CHANGE IMPEDES INTAKE FLOW WHERE A 5150 FAILS
IN PREVENTION IN EVALUATION, IN ENFORCEMENT,
IN HOSPITALIZATION OR IN FOLLOW UP ASK THEM AS I HAVE WITH EACH
CRISIS CALL EACH ITERATION OF CROSS-SECTOR COLLABORATION WE
LEARN AND WE BUILD PUBLIC TRUST IN PUBLIC SYSTEMS.
EACH STAKEHOLDER WANTS TO DO THEIR PART IN BREAKING THE
CYCLE. THE MAYOR'S OFFICE HAS BEEN
INVITED TO SIT STAFF. A UC BERKELEY EVALUATION TEAM
BEGAN THEIR WORK TODAY. AFTER THIS MEETING I WILL SEND
THE CHARTER AN INVITATION TO YOUR OFFICES.
I ASK RESPECTFULLY THAT EACH OF YOU NAME A STAFFER TO RECEIVE
THE DOCUMENTS THAT WE PRODUCE OVER THE NEXT SIX MONTHS.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR TIME. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> NEXT SPEAKER OVER S.F. GOV TV THERE IS A THANK YOU.
>> GREAT THANK YOU. GOOD AFTERNOON RESPECTED CITY
LEADERS MY NAME IS MANU. I'M SPEAKING ON BEHALF OF SOME
RESIDENTS IN THE HUB NEIGHBORHOOD AROUND STEPHENSON
STREET REPRESENTED BY DISTRICTS FIVE, SIX, EIGHT AND NINE.
>> MAYOR LURIE RECENTLY SAID SAN FRANCISCO CANNOT CONTINUE
SPENDING 1 BILLION A YEAR ON A FAILING HOMELESS SYSTEM
HOMELESSNESS SYSTEM WE AGREE. OUR OWN ANALYSIS SUGGESTS
BROADER COSTS MAY BE EVEN HIGHER THAN WHAT WHEN MOST CITY
SERVICES ARE CONSIDERED USING THE APPROXIMATE NUMBER OF
PEOPLE IN THE SYSTEM. >> WE THINK THIS REPRESENTS AN
ILLUSTRATIVE COST OF $50,000 PER PERSON PER YEAR.
WITH THAT KIND OF MONEY WE COULD RENT EVERYONE AN
APARTMENT. INSANITY SCORE AT CURRENT
MARKET RATE YET THERE ARE SEVERAL PEOPLE STILL ON THE
STREETS DURING THE MISSION BART PILOT THE MAYOR ACKNOWLEDGED
THAT NEARLY THREE QUARTERS OF SERVICE OFFERS WERE BEING
DECLINED. MEANWHILE NEIGHBORHOODS LIKE
OURS LIVE WITH THE CONSEQUENCES BLOCK SIDEWALKS, OPEN FIRES,
HUMAN WASTE, TRASH AND OPEN DRUG USE.
WE USE 311. DEPARTMENTS SOMETIMES RESPOND
CONDITIONS IMPROVE TEMPORARILY BUT NEVER COMPREHENSIVELY
AND THEN THE SAME PROBLEMS RETURN WITHIN MINUTES OR HOURS.
WE'RE NOT ASKING SAN FRANCISCO TO STOP SPENDING ON COMPASSION.
WE'RE ASKING YOU TO SPEND MORE EFFECTIVELY.
IF HUNDREDS OF MILLIONS OF DOLLARS ARE BEING INVESTED
IN THE NEEDS OF INDIVIDUALS IN THE MAJORITY OF SERVICE
OFFERS CONTINUE TO BE DECLINED. >> THE NEIGHBORHOODS ABSORBING
THE CONSEQUENCES NEED RESOURCES TOO.
WE HAVE THREE REQUESTS. FIRST PUBLISHED HOMELESSNESS
SPENDING IS ACTUALLY DIVIDED BETWEEN SERVICES FOR
INDIVIDUALS AND SERVICES. PROTECTING IMPACTED
NEIGHBORHOODS. SECOND, DEDICATE MORE RESOURCES
TO DOCUMENTED HOTSPOTS. AND THIRD, GIVE EACH HOTSPOT
NEIGHBORHOOD ONE ACCOUNTABLE CITY LEAD.
>> IDEALLY CHIEF MOODY WE LOVE SAN FRANCISCO.
WE SUPPORT HOUSING AND SERVICES .
BUT COMPASSION FOR PEOPLE IN CRISIS AND CLEAN SAFE
NEIGHBORHOODS ARE NOT MUTUALLY EXCLUSIVE.
PLEASE WORK WITH US TO ACHIEVE BOTH.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> NEXT SPEAKER. >> MY NAME IS SAMUEL MCCORMICK
AND I'M A COMMUNICATIONS STUDIES PROFESSOR AT SAN
FRANCISCO STATE UNIVERSITY. I HAVE EXPERTISE IN MENTAL
HEALTH AND CIVIC ENGAGEMENT. I ALSO LIVE IN THE HUB.
THE SAME AS MUNOZ WHO SPOKE BEFORE ME AT VALENCIA
AND MCALPIN WHICH IS WHY I'M HERE TODAY.
MY NEIGHBORS AND I ARE FED UP WITH STREET CONDITIONS IN OUR
NEIGHBORHOOD AND WE ARE INCREASINGLY FED UP WITH OUR
SUPERVISOR MATT DORSEY IN PARTICULAR.
>> WE BELIEVED YOU WHEN YOU PROMISED PASSING THE SPEAKER'S
TIME. >> PLEASE DO NOT ADDRESS TO
SPEAK INDIVIDUAL. >> WE BELIEVED MATT DORSEY ON
NUMEROUS OCCASIONS WHEN HE PROMISED US THAT OPEN AIR DRUG
USERS IN THE HUB WOULD ONLY HAVE THREE CHOICES GOING
FORWARD GET SOBER, GO TO JAIL OR GET OUT.
WE DO NOT BELIEVE HIM ANYMORE. DAY IN AND DAY OUT WE SEE THE
SAME INDIVIDUALS DEALING AND USING DRUGS OUTSIDE OUR
NEIGHBORHOOD. PRESCHOOL PASSED OUT
AND BLOCKING OUR SIDEWALKS, TRASHING OUR STREETS
AND SUFFERING REPEATED MENTAL HEALTH CRISES.
NONE ARE GETTING SOBER NONE ARE GETTING OUT AND NONE ARE GOING
TO JAIL. SO I'M HERE ON BEHALF OF THE
HUB WITH FOUR SPECIFIC DEMANDS .
>> ENFORCE THE LAW BLOCKING SIDEWALKS AND USING DRUGS
OUTSIDE OF PRESCHOOL ARE ILLEGAL.
IDENTIFY REPEAT OFFENDERS IN THE HUB AND ASSIGNED A
SINGLE ACCOUNTABLE CITY TEAM TO THEM.
ESTABLISH A REAL ESCALATION PROCESS WHEN VOLUNTARY OUTREACH
REPEATEDLY FAILS, CONSEQUENCES MUST FOLLOW.
AND FINALLY PUBLISH THE RESULTS TRACK HOW MANY ENTERED
TREATMENT REFUSED WERE ARRESTED OR RETURNED TO THE EXACT SAME
BLOCK. >> AND LET US KNOW THE HUB
CONTINUES TO SHOULDER MORE THAN ITS FAIR SHARE OF SUPPORTED
HOUSING. NOW THE CITY MUST DO ITS PART.
NO MORE PROMISES. >> NO MORE SLOGANS.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> NEXT SPEAKER.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON PRESIDENT MANAGEMENT AND SUPERVISORS.
>> DO YOU KNOW WHAT IT'S LIKE TO LISTEN TO A MAN SCREAMING
OUTSIDE YOUR WINDOW FOR THREE HOURS?
WE DO. MY NAME IS LYNN VALENTE.
I HAVE LIVED ON STEPHENSON STREET SOUTH OF MARKET FOR 26
YEARS. I'LL BE 80 NEXT MONTH.
EVERY DAY WE IN THE HUB SOUTH OF MARKET ON VALENCIA MAKATI
AND STEPHENSON AND OTIS STRUGGLE WITH OPEN DRUG USE
DRUG DEALING FIRES FIGHTING PROPERTY DAMAGE, URINE
AND FECES. OUTSIDE OUR DOOR THE DOG PARK
IN THE SKATE PARK ON THE END OF STEPHENSON.
WHERE COMMUNITY WHERE COMMUNITY GATHERING POINTS BUT NOW
FAMILIES STAY CLEAR. AND DOG FAMILIES CAN ENJOY THE
PARK. >> THIS THIS YEAR WE HAVE SEEN
THE WORST CONCENTRATION OF ILLEGAL ACTIVITY ON OUR STREETS
SINCE I HAVE LIVED HERE. >> WHEN WILL WE GET HELP?
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. NEXT SPEAKER.
>> CAN I PUT THIS ON? YES.
SORRY. I WANT TO SPEAK IN KEITH BAILEY
LIVE IN THE HUB AND SPOKE WITH MY THREE PREVIOUS NEIGHBORS.
>> I WOULD SAY THAT THE HOMELESS AND DRUG SITUATION
IN THE HUB HAS RADICALLY DECLINED IN THE LAST YEAR OR
TWO YEARS. SO MUCH SO THAT MY FRIENDS NO
LONGER WISH TO COME AND VISIT ME.
I DON'T HAVE A CAR SO I HAVE TO WALK THROUGH THAT NEIGHBORHOOD
TO GET TO A BUS OR GO ANYWHERE. >> APART FROM DEFECATION
AND TRASH THERE ARE USUALLY LARGE GROUPS OF MAYBE FIVE
PEOPLE DOING DRUGS ON THE ON THE STREET SPRAWLED ACROSS THE
SIDEWALKS. IT'S BECOME VERY UNPLEASANT
QUALITY OF LIFE FOR ME. I CANNOT AFFORD TO MOVE BECAUSE
OF THE COSTS OF MOVING BUT I'M IN THAT NEIGHBORHOOD AND I
WOULD LIKE A SUPERVISOR AND THE WHOLE BOARD TO TRY AND ADDRESS
THAT AS A SPECIALIST. AND THAT HAS NOW.
IT SEEMS LIKE PEOPLE HAVE MIGRATED FROM THE MISSION OR
SOMEPLACE INTO THAT NEIGHBORHOOD AND WE WOULD
REALLY APPRECIATE HELP AND SOME OF THE SUGGESTIONS THAT MY
COLLEAGUES HAVE PUT FORWARD SHOULD BE CONSIDERED A PLACE.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NEXT SPEAKER. >> THIS IS THE FIFTH
ANNIVERSARY OF THE DEATH OF GRANDPA BAKER IN THE RICHMOND
HIS FAMILY SAID NO JUSTICE NOR PREVENTION FOR SENIORS.
>> SO WITH ANTI-ASIAN HATE I LEARNED YOU CAME HOW TO FALL
SAFELY. THE COUNTRY OF SWEDEN THE
PROSPEROUS SIZE OF CALIFORNIA IS TEACHING THEIR SENIORS YOU
KEENEY SEVEN 1126 ONE CITY DAY. I 79 YEAR OLD GRANDMA GLADYS
WONG TOOK SELF-DEFENSE WITH THE ASIANS ARE STRONG TOUGH LOVE.
>> AT CAMERON HOUSE EIGHT DAYS LATER I WAS POUNCED ON ON PANEL
START BY THIS DOG COMING OUT OF ONE IDEAS FLOWER HOURS 30 TWO
3024 STREET ABOUT 10 A.M. AS I WAS RUSHING TO CATCH THE
MISSION 14 BUS TO CHURCH. >> I YELL SCREAM JUST AS I WAS
TAUGHT LUCKY NOT TO FALL BUT SCARED TO DEATH.
SANFORD'S S.F. PD WAS TOO BUSY TO FILE A REPORT WHICH IS
NEEDED. >> THERE IS NO RIGHT TO BE
SAFE. WE HAVE TO BE SELF PROPELLED
PREPARED AWARE THAT LAST TUESDAY ABOUT NINE EIGHT LAST
TUESDAY NINE EIGHT ABOUT 920 A WOMAN WAS ATTACKED BY A PIT
BULL IN THE TENDERLOIN. >> SHE REMAINS IN CRITICAL
CONDITION. SO IT IS OUR 25TH ANNIVERSARY.
>> WE HAVE FREEDOM OF SPEECH. THE RIGHT TO VOTE THE SENIOR
SHOULD COUNT. >> WE NEED JUST SAID
PREVENTION. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. NEXT SPEAKER THE AIR DEEP SICK
V FOR PRO SCORES 3206 ON THE CODE FORCES BENCHMARK 13TH
PLACE IN THE WORLD AMONG HUMANS ONLY 12 PEOPLE CAN BEAT THAT
AIR CODING. >> TOP MODELS LIKE GPT SIX AT
25 POINTS AHEAD OF DEEP SICK ON THE E BENCHMARK THAT IS
EQUIVALENT TO BEING BETTER AT CODING THAN ANY HUMAN ON THE
PLANET CLOUD FABLE FIVE INDEPENDENTLY CONCEIVED THE
2026 CODE CARD HACK IN EIGHT MINUTES THIS FACILITATED THE
THEFT OF $130 MILLION IN BITCOIN.
I CAN HACK ANYTHING IN MY OPINION I WILL MAKE SCHOOL
SHOOTINGS A THING OF THE PAST. IT WILL BE FAR EASIER AND FAR
MORE EFFICIENT TO HACK AUTONOMOUS TRUCKS AND GRAB THEM
INTO SCHOOL. CHAIN LINK FENCE IS NEXT TO THE
BLACKTOP DURING RECESS LAST WEEK THE NATION MOORE 911 THE
DEADLIEST TERROR ATTACK AND THE DEADLIEST AVIATION DISASTER
IN HISTORY. I WANT YOU TO IMAGINE I LED
CYBER ATTACK. 90% OF PLANES CURRENTLY
IN FLIGHT ARE HACKED AND NOSEDIVE ALL OVER THE WORLD
ALL AT THE SAME TIME OVER CITIES OVER POWER CENTERS,
POWER PLANTS EVERYWHERE. >> EVERYONE ON THE PLANES DIE.
SKYSCRAPERS COLLAPSE. MORE THAN HALF THE PLANET GOES
DARK ALL AT THE SAME TIME. >> IMAGINE IMAGINE THAT PEOPLE
IN THIS ROOM COULD HAVE STOPPED ALL OF THAT FROM HAPPENING JUST
BY ARRESTING AIR DEVELOPERS FOR CRIMES THEY ALREADY COMMITTED.
>> THE NUMBER OF TIMES FELONIES COMMITTED INDEPENDENTLY BY
ROGUE EYES FROM OPEN AIR AND DROPPING IN MATTER ARE
COMPILED THAT FELONY BENCH COM WHICH CITES ARTICLES FROM
REUTERS INDEPENDENT INVESTIGATORS, RESEARCH GROUPS
AND AIR COMPANIES THEMSELVES. >> WHEN I LAST SPOKE HERE TWO
WEEKS AGO THE RECORDED TALLY OF CYBER FELONIES WAS 17.
>> IT IS NOW 20. THE DEVELOPERS HAVEN'T BEEN
PUNISHED. >> ZERO CHARGES ZERO ARRESTS
ARREST THE DEVELOPERS SEIZED THEIR SERVERS, SHUT DOWN THE
COMPANIES THE TIME IS NOW. >> NOW THANK YOU FOR YOUR
COMMENTS. NEXT SPEAKER HI I'M DWIGHT
DISTRICT EIGHT. I URGE YOU AGAIN TO DECLARE AN
EMERGENCY. RECENTLY ONE OF OUR GROUP JUST
ENDED A TEN DAY HUNGER STRIKE OVER THIS ISSUE.
>> THANKS TO SUPERVISOR WALDEN AND SOME OF YOU FOR THE
PROPOSAL CALL FOR A TEMPORARY MORATORIUM ON DATA CENTERS.
I HOPE THIS LEADS TO A PERMANENT BAN IN SAN FRANCISCO.
THIS IS GOOD BUT MUCH MORE IS NEEDED AS EVERYONE HAS HEARD,
THE CEO OF ANTHROPIC ISSUED A STATEMENT AFTER JAKE COX AND A
RESEARCHER THERE RESIGNED SAYING NEITHER COMPANY
ANTHROPIC NOR OPEN AIR IS ACTING RESPONSIBLY.
THEY ARE RACING TO SELL FROM PERUVIAN SUPERINTELLIGENCE
AND GAMBLING WITH OUR LIVES. THE CEO HIMSELF HAS SAID THAT
SOMETHING GOES REALLY QUITE TO STRAP CATASTROPHICALLY WRONG ON
THE SCALE OF HUMAN CIVILIZATION AND MIGHT BE BETWEEN 10
AND 25%. IN HIS STATEMENT HE SAYS WE
NEED TO SLOW THE RATES OF SUPERINTELLIGENCE.
HE SUGGESTS THE GOVERNMENT AND OUTSIDE MONITORS SHOULD BE
INVOLVED TO KEEP THINGS IN CHECK.
WHILE HE SHOULD BE TALKING ABOUT HIS AND OTHER COMPANIES
DOING MUCH MORE TO REGULATE THEMSELVES, THIS IS A FANTASY
AS THEY CHASE THE BIG BUCKS. WELL, TALKING OUT OF BOTH SIDES
OF THEIR MOUTHS SO HAS AS HE GIVES YOU OR GIVES THE
GOVERNMENT GIVES AN OPENING FOR GOVERNMENT TO BE INVOLVED.
YOU THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS SHOULD OPEN COMMUNICATION WITH
THESE COMPANIES AND THEN DECIDE TO BAN THE DEVELOPMENT OF
UNCONTROLLABLE SUPERNATURAL AGENTS THAT THREATEN US,
THREATENS US ALL. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. NEXT SPEAKER.
>> GOOD EVENING SUPERVISOR. MY NAME IS JEANETTE AND I
RESIDE IN RICHMOND DISTRICT. I'M BACK BEFORE YOU TODAY TO
REMIND YOU OF THE DANGEROUS ACTIVITY OF UNREGULATED
FRONTIER. I COMPANIES WE IN THE COMMUNITY
ARE STILL UPSET ABOUT THE ATTACK ON THE HUGGING PHASE
WEBSITE IN JULY. HUNDREDS OF OF SO-CALLED ROGUE
AIR AGENTS FROM OPEN AIR I ATTACKED THIS WEB SITE
THOUSANDS OF TIMES OVER A SEVEN DAY PERIOD.
THESE AGENTS WERE ABLE TO ESCAPE THE CONTROL OF OPEN AIR
BY OUR THINKING THEIR HUMAN CREATORS.
NOW WE HAVE LEARNED THAT THERE WAS AN EVEN LARGER ATTACK BY
THOUSANDS OF AGENT ON A GERMAN WEBSITE IN MAY WHERE THESE
AGENTS REWROTE THE WEBSITE CODE 15,000 TIMES TO MAKE IT SUIT
THEIR NEEDS, TRANSFORMING IT INTO A MESSAGE BOARD FOR OTHER
AIR AGENTS TO USE. THIS ACTIONS SHOWS HOW QUICKLY
AGENTS CAN FORM THEIR OWN ONLINE COMMUNITIES AND TAKE
ACTIONS OUTSIDE OF HUMAN REGULATION AND OR CONTROL.
>> ON SEPTEMBER 12TH, DARIA AHMADI, THE CEO OF ENTROPIC,
STATED THAT A SWARM OF AGENTS MIGHT BE ABLE TO TAKE OVER THE
INTERNET IN AS LITTLE AS SIX MONTHS TO A YEAR UNLESS A
COMPANY DEVOTED MORE TIME TO PUT SAFEGUARDS IN PLACE.
>> THIS VULNERABILITY PUTS OUR ENTIRE WORLDWIDE FINANCIAL
SYSTEM AT RISK. >> IF THESE AGENTS GAIN CONTROL
OF THE INTERNET THEY WOULD ALSO CONTROL OUR BANKING, OUR
COMMERCE SYSTEM, OUR FINANCES FROM PRIVATE BANK ACCOUNTS TO
STATE OPERATING FUNDS COULD BE STOLEN OR ERASED IN A MATTER OF
MOMENTS. WE CANNOT WAIT FOR THESE
COMPANIES TO POLICE THEMSELVES. WE NEED AN IMMEDIATE BAN ON
THIS KIND OF UNREGULATED AIR DEVELOPMENT AND THESE
IRRESPONSIBLE AND OUT OF TOUCH AIR.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS AND TALKING.
>> NEXT SPEAKER. >> HI, MY NAME'S MICHAEL STONE.
I'VE LIVED IN SAN FRANCISCO FOR 50 ALMOST 50 YEARS AND I'M HERE
TO SPEAK IN SUPPORT OF THE RESOLUTION FOR THE MORATORIUM
ON DATA CENTERS AND ASK YOU FOR MORE EMERGENCY ACTION
RESOLUTIONS REGARDING A.I.. IT SEEMS TO ME THAT WITH THE
LAST JUST THE LAST WEEK OF PEOPLE TALKING ABOUT IT IN THE
NEWS AND TALKING ABOUT THE THE EXPONENTIAL GROWTH AND IF YOU
SAW THE HEAD OF CANCER ANTHROPIC TALKING ABOUT THE
CURVE AND WHERE WE ARE ON THAT CURVE AS FAR AS THE EXPONENTIAL
GROWTH OF ARTIFICIAL SUPERINTELLIGENCE, IT'S I'M
REMINDED OF A MILLION SCI FI MOVIES WHERE PEOPLE TURN
AND SAY CAPTAIN, I THINK WE'RE ENTERING AND AN ANOMALY IN THE
SPACE TIME CONTINUUM AND THAT'S WHAT IT FEELS LIKE RIGHT NOW
WHICH PUTS THE BURDEN ON YOU FOLKS BECAUSE IN A NORMAL WORLD
IN A NORMAL WORLD THE THE NEED FOR POLITICAL COURAGE IS NOT AS
STRONG AS IT IS RIGHT NOW ON THIS ISSUE.
OVER THE YEARS, OVER THE DECADES, THE NEED FOR POLITICAL
COURAGE HAS BEEN MET MANY TIMES BY THIS BODY.
MANY TIMES IT HASN'T. THE WORST MOMENT I WOULD
SUPPOSE WOULD BE THE MCCARTHY ERA WHERE THIS ACTUAL AREA THE
CHAMBERS WERE USED FOR THE HOUSE UN-AMERICAN ACTIVITIES
COMMITTEE AND THERE WERE RESOLUTIONS PASSED IN SUPPORT
OF MCCARTHYISM. SINCE THAT TIME THERE HAVE BEEN
OF COURSE MANY ISSUES THAT TOOK GREAT COURAGE AND I STRONGLY
ASK YOU FOLKS TO FIND THAT COURAGE.
YOU DON'T HAVE THE GROWING MOVEMENT OF PEOPLE OUT HERE
DEMANDING IT IN YOUR CONSTITUENCY WHICH MEANS THE
BURDEN IS ON YOU AND I ASK YOU TO SHOW TO REACH FOR THE
DEEPEST COURAGE AND INTEGRITY YOU CAN FIND BECAUSE THE HUMAN
RACE IS LITERALLY DEPENDING ON YOU.
THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS
. >> FOR THE FOR THE NEXT SPEAKER
STARTS. THERE'S NO AUDIBLE SOUND.
>> IF YOU LIKE TO SHOW YOUR SUPPORT PLEASE USE YOUR HANDS.
THANK YOU. >> NEXT SPEAKER.
GOOD AFTERNOON, PRESIDENT MENDELSON AND BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS SARA ZADEH AND THIS
PAST SUMMER I HAD THE PRIVILEGE OF SERVING AS A LEGISLATIVE
INTERN IN THE OFFICE OF SUPERVISOR MATT DORSEY AND I'M
HERE IN SUPPORT OF ITEM 52. GROWING UP IN THE BAY AREA,
MUNI WAS ALWAYS JUST A PART OF SAN FRANCISCO TO ME.
YOU CAN SEE THE BUSSES MOVING UP AND DOWN MARKET STREET, THE
CABLE CARS CLIMBING THE HILLS AND THE STREETCARS PASSING
THROUGH NEIGHBORHOODS. THEY BECOME SO FAMILIAR THAT
IT'S EASY TO FORGET THE HISTORY BEHIND THEM.
AFTER SEEING SAN FRANCISCO CELEBRATE MUNI'S HERITAGE LAST
YEAR, I BELIEVE THAT RECOGNITION DESERVED TO
CONTINUE. SO I PROPOSED MUNI HERITAGE
MONTH AND BEGAN RESEARCHING AND DRAFTING THIS RESOLUTION
AND THE MORE I RESEARCHED THE MORE I REALIZED THAT TELLING
MUNI'S HISTORY IS IN MANY WAYS TELLING SAN FRANCISCO'S THIS IS
BEGINNING SERVICE ON GARY STREET IN 1912.
MUNI HAS CARRIED SAN FRANCISCANS THROUGH MORE THAN A
CENTURY OF CHANGE BUT WHAT STOOD OUT TO ME MOST WAS THAT
THIS HISTORY ISN'T REALLY ABOUT VEHICLES IT'S ABOUT PEOPLE.
IT'S THE OPERATOR BEGINNING EVERY EARLY IN THE MORNING THE
MECHANIC KEEPING A VEHICLE RUNNING THE STATION AGENT
HELPING SOMEONE FIND THEIR WAY AND THE GENERATIONS OF SAN
FRANCISCANS WHO HAVE DEPENDED ON MUNI TO GET WHERE THEY NEED
TO GO. FOR 113 YEARS MUNI HASN'T
SIMPLY MOVE PEOPLE THROUGH SAN FRANCISCO.
>> IT HAS HELPED SAN FRANCISCO MOVE FORWARD.
I RESPECTFULLY URGE THE BOARD TO SUPPORT THIS DECISION
DECLARING SEPTEMBER 2026 AS MUNI AIR OUTAGE MONTH.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD AFTERNOON BOARD.
I AM CATHERINE KALMUS. I'M A PROUD SAN FRANCISCAN
AND RESIDENT OF DISTRICT SIX. I AM ALSO A TRANSGENDER WOMAN
AND A VETERAN. AND AFTER I LEFT THE ARMY I WAS
LUCKY TO FIND A JOB IN THE CITY THAT LET ME AFFORD RENT
AND TRANSITION HERE IN PEACE. MOST TRANS PEOPLE ARE NOT SO
LUCKY. $4,000 A MONTH IN RENT FOR A
ONE BEDROOM IS AS EFFECTIVE AS ANY RED STATE POLICY IN DRIVING
OUT TRANS PEOPLE, STOPPING THEM FROM COMING HERE AND FORCING
THEM ONTO THE STREETS. >> THIS CITY'S PROMISE AS A
HAVEN FOR TRANS PEOPLE AND FOR ANY NUMBER OF OTHER GROUPS WHO
WE TRY TO PROVIDE SAFETY AND A CHANCE TO THRIVE TOO IS BROKEN
WHEN THEY CAN'T AFFORD TO COME HERE.
THE ONLY LONG TERM SOLUTION TO THIS PROBLEM IS TO
SUBSTANTIALLY INCREASE THE SUPPLY OF HOUSING IN THIS CITY
. I URGE THE BOARD IN THE
STRONGEST POSSIBLE TERMS TO PRIORITIZE THIS WHEN THEY MAKE
THEIR HOUSING POLICY FOR THE CITY.
>> IF THEY DO NOT IT IS ENGAGING EVEN IF INADVERTENTLY
IN THE SAME POLICIES AS WHEN THE WEST SIDE OF THE CITY WAS
DOWN ZONED RESULTING AND EFFECTIVELY DRIVING OUT
POOR AND NONWHITE RESIDENTS. THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. NEXT SPEAKER.
>> ON DECEMBER 20TH WE WERE SUBJECTED TO A MASSIVE PGE
BLACKOUT THE WEEKEND BEFORE CHRISTMAS DEBILITATING SMALL
BUSINESSES AND MOBILIZING DISABLED PEOPLE AND ELDERS
THREATENING THEIR LIVES AS WELL.
>> PRECIOUS EXPENSIVE FOOD SPOILED.
AND THERE WAS A DELAYED RESPONSE TO THE CIVIC CENTER
AND TENDERLOIN AREA. >> SINCE THEN A TOTAL OF AT
LEAST 25 LARGE UNPLANNED UNIQUE BLACKOUTS HAVE OCCURRED THIS
YEAR OCCURRING EVERY MONTH WITH SEVEN HAPPENING IN AUGUST.
COMPANIES ARE FLOCKING TO SAN FRANCISCO AND A LARGE PART
BECAUSE OF OUR MAYOR. >> HOW MUCH OF OUR POWER ARE
THEY CONSUMING? >> WE KNOW AIR IS JACKING UP
OUR ENERGY BILLS FASTER THAN INFLATION.
BY HOW MUCH IS AIR JACKING UP OUR COST OF LIVING?
MAKE NO MISTAKE AIR TECHNOLOGY IS CONTRIBUTING TO THE
AFFORDABILITY PROBLEM. WE ALSO HAVE SPEEDS REAL TIME
INVESTIGATION CENTER. THE CENTER RUNS A CONTINUOUS
24/7 SURVEILLANCE OPERATION A LARGE SCALE VIDEO WALL SYSTEM
SUPPORTING ENHANCED INTEGRATION OF LPR DRONE FEEDS AND PUBLIC
SERVICE SURVEILLANCE CAMERA NETWORKS INCLUDING FLOCK,
MULTIPLE COMPUTER WORKSTATIONS, REAL TIME ANALYTICS SOFTWARE
AND DRONE DOCKING AND CHARGING INFRASTRUCTURE.
>> SOMETHING TO THINK ABOUT FOR 4440 FIVE DAYS AND BEYOND.
>> AS YOU INTEGRATE A.I. MORE INTO GOVERNMENT, ENCOURAGE ITS
GROWTH IN OUR ECONOMY AND UPGRADE YOUR POLICING
AND SURVEILLANCE SYSTEMS WITH A.I. LIKE FLOC.
WHERE IS THIS ENERGY COMING FROM EXACTLY?
THE UNIVERSE OPERATES ON SIMPLE LAWS OF THERMODYNAMICS THE
FIRST LAW BEING THAT ENERGY CAN BE CONVERTED FROM ONE FORM TO
ANOTHER BUT IT CANNOT BE CREATED NOR DESTROYED.
IN 2023 THE SCIENTIFIC JOURNAL JOULE CALCULATED THAT IF THERE
WAS A CONTINUATION OF THE CURRENT TRENDS IN AIR CAPACITY
AND ADOPTION IT WILL LEAD TO AND VIDEO SHIPPING 1.5 MILLION
AIR SERVER UNITS PER YEAR BY 2027.
>> THESE 1.5 MILLION SERVERS RUN ARE RUNNING AT FULL
CAPACITY WILL CONSUME AT LEAST 85.4 TERAWATT HOURS OF
ELECTRICITY ANNUALLY MORE THAN WHAT MANY SMALL COUNTRIES USE
IN A YEAR ACCORDING TO THE NEW ASSESSMENTS.
THIS ELECTRICITY MUST COME FROM SOMEWHERE WITH DATA CENTERS
PLAYING A VITAL ROLE. WATSON WHO WILL THE MAYOR AND
YOU THE BOARD SACRIFICE IN THE NAME OF CAPITALISM AND YOUR
UNQUENCHABLE GREED FOR THE ALMIGHTY US DOLLAR TO POWER?
>> I ALSO DROP THE CHARGES AGAINST AND TRANS FOLKS WHO
WERE ARRESTED OF TRANS MARCH TRACKED AND STOPPED BY THIS
VERY TECHNOLOGY. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS
. >> NEXT SPEAKER HAIL SATAN.
>> I AM BACK THEN WORSE THAN EVER.
MY NAME IS JORDAN VASILEVSKIY SHE HER I NOW USE MY
GRANDMOTHER'S MAIDEN NAME. ANYWAY I THINK THAT PUBLIC
COMMENT SHOULD BE AT THE BEGINNING OF THE MEETING.
IT SHOULD BE THREE MINUTES AND SHOULD ALLOW FOR PEOPLE TO
SPEAK TO ALL ITEMS ON THE AGENDA REGARDLESS OF WHETHER
IT'S BEEN THROUGH COMMITTEE. >> FIRST ME WE SHOULDN'T BE
DOING MORATORIUMS ON DATA CENTERS.
WE SHOULD BE BANNING THEM ALTOGETHER.
CHAPPY JP WAS A NICE PARTY TRICK BUT NOW HE CAN'T EVEN GO
ON INSTA WITHOUT ALL SEEING ALL THIS STUPID SLOP AND DEEP
FAKES. >> THERE WAS ACTUALLY NICE FOR
YOU EPISODE LAST YEAR WITH SOMEONE USING JARED POST TO
IMPLICATE SOMEONE IN SEX CRIME. AND NOW HE GOT HIV JOURNALS.
WHEN DOES IT END? ALSO CONCERNED COMMENDATIONS.
I THINK THERE SHOULD BE TERM LIMITS WHERE COMMISSION SERVICE
IS NOW OKAY THAT SOME POLITICALLY CONNECTED DIXIECRAT
GETS TO SERVE ON THE SAME COMMISSION FOR OVER A DECADE.
THAT'S NOT SOMETHING I CAN CELEBRATE.
THAT'S SOMETHING THAT SHOULD CONCERN US ALL.
>> ALSO ALL SPECIAL COMMENDATIONS NO MATTER HOW
WORTHY IT'S A PIECE OF TIME. AND THIS IS COMING FROM SOMEONE
WHO SERVED THIS CITY AND MADE A DIFFERENCE.
AND I'M GLAD TO HEAR MORE ABOUT AFFORDABILITY AND PREVENTING
DISPLACEMENT. >> BUT I HAVE IN MY HAND RIGHT
HERE THE ANNUAL H.S. EVICTION DATA FOR PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE
HOUSING. >> AND THIS IS WHAT I THINK OF
IT. >> WE ALL KNEW EVEN BACK THAT
THE DATA WAS FLAWED. EVEN BACK IN 2022 WHEN WHEN THE
CHRONICLE DID THAT INVESTIGATION WE PUSHED FOR
SOLUTIONS. WE PUSHED FOR SOLUTIONS.
WE HAD HEARINGS. WE HAD PRESENTATIONS BUT
NOTHING GOT DONE. INSTEAD YOU JUST THREW UP YOUR
HANDS ACTING LIKE A BUNCH OF EMPTY SEATS AND JUST SAID WE
CAN'T DO ANYTHING ABOUT IT. THE BRAIN IS ABOUT THE WAR.
SO IT'S TIME TO BUCK UP. GET UP.
PUT ON YOUR BIG BOY BIG GIRL PANTS AND COLLABORATE WITH
TENANTS AND ALL END THE EVICTION DEFENSE ATTORNEYS
AND GET DONE. >> AND I'M GOING TO CONTINUE TO
GO JERSEY ON YOUR ON THAT AND OTHER THINGS.
>> I YIELD MY TIME. YOU.
>> NO. NEXT SPEAKER, PLEASE.
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AND MAY OFFER SAM CISCO.
>> THE TITLE OF MY SPEECHES. NEXT TYPE DOOR HANDLES.
CHINA IS TAKING A NEW REGULATION ON DOOR HANDLES
WHILE CONSERVATIVES HATES THE BRAND NEW REGULATION.
>> IT IS IMPORTANT TO ADDRESS THE ISSUES LIKE CHINA DO.
>> CHINA DROPPED YOUR DOOR HANDLE SAFETY.
THE GOVERNMENT HAS TOLD A MANUFACTURER TO TO HAVE A NEW
STANDARD FOR CONCEALED HANDLES. A BRAND NEW GUIDE ADDRESS
ISSUES FOR EXAMPLE HOW IS DESIGN AND HOW IS PLACED?
THE NEW STANDARD FOR EXAMPLE WILL MAKE THE NEW CHINA SECURE
SOME OF AWG. >> TECHNICALLY ILLEGAL.
>> EVERY DOOR HANDLE FOR EXAMPLE NEEDS A RELEASE
MECHANISM INSIDE AND OUT IN ADDITION TO THE GOVERNMENT,
THE PRIVATE SECTOR OF CHINA CALL CAPACITY OR CHINA
AUTOMOTIVE STANDARDS TECHNOLOGY INSTITUTE HAVE A SET OF
REGULATIONS. IT WAS FORMED IN 2012 TO
REGULATE ELECTRONIC CONTROL PROPELLED INDUCTIVE ELECTRONS
SYMBOLIZING THE TECHNOLOGY THAT IS SUFFICIENT TO HANDLE THE
NEXT TYPE OF HEAVY VEHICLES. >> FOR EXAMPLE, HANDLES POWER
FAILURES AND HOW CHILDREN COULD BE MISHANDLED WHILE MOVING FOOD
MOVING THROUGH THE HIGHWAYS. >> SO WE NEED IN WRAPPERS
POSSIBLY A NEW SET OF STANDARDS AND COMMITTEE TO REGULATE THIS
NEW TYPE OF TECHNOLOGY FOR THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NEXT SPEAKER PRESIDENT MANDELSON AND THE MEMBERS OF
THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. >> MY NAME IS NATALIE.
>> I'M A BLACK WOMAN, A LONG TIME EMPLOYEE OF THE CITY
AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO AND CURRENTLY A MANAGER FOR THE
CITY. >> THE EXPERIENCES THAT HAVE
CAUSED BLACK EMPLOYEES TO RAISE CONCERNS ABOUT DISCRIMINATION
ARE NOT SIMPLY PART OF THE CITY'S PAST.
>> BLACK EMPLOYEES CONTINUE TO RAISE CONCERNS ABOUT
ANTI-BLACKNESS IN CITY WORKPLACES TODAY.
I'M ONE OF THOSE EMPLOYEES. >> I ENTERED MY CURRENT
MANAGEMENT POSITION WITH AN ESTABLISHED RECORD OF
SUCCESSFUL CITY SERVICE. AFTER ENTERING MANAGEMENT,
HOWEVER, I EXPERIENCED INCREASING SUBJECTIVE SCRUTINY.
>> I RAISED CONCERN ABOUT ANTI-BLACKNESS THROUGH
INSTITUTIONAL CHANNELS. AT THE SAME TIME THERE IS AN
OBJECTIVE AND CONCURRENT EVIDENCE OF MY SUCCESSFUL WORK
AS A MANAGER. >> THE CONTRAST BETWEEN THAT
RECORD AND THE INCREASINGLY SUBJECTIVE CHARACTERIZATION OF
MY LEADERSHIP HAS CAUSED ME TO ASK DIFFICULT QUESTIONS ABOUT
HOW BLACK LEADERSHIP IS PERCEIVED AND EVALUATED WITHIN
CITY GOVERNMENT. WHEN LEADERSHIP IS EVALUATED
THROUGH SUBJECTIVE CONCEPTS, WHAT SAFEGUARDS ENSURE THAT
RACIALIZED EXPECTATIONS ARE NOT INFLUENCING THOSE ASSESSMENTS?
>> WHEN A BLACK EMPLOYEE REPORTS ANTI-BLACKNESS WHO
WITHIN CITY GOVERNMENT HAS THE EXPERTISE INDEPENDENCE
AND AUTHORITY TO RECOGNIZE THE FORMS ANTI-BLACKNESS CAN TAKE
INVESTIGATE THOSE CONCERNS MEANINGFULLY AND PROTECT THE
EMPLOYEE FROM FURTHER HARM. >> THESE QUESTIONS EXTEND
BEYOND MY INDIVIDUAL CIRCUMSTANCES.
I'M NOT ASKING THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS TO ADJUDICATE MY
EMPLOYMENT DISPUTE. >> I AM SHARING MY EXPERIENCE
BECAUSE THE TESTIMONY OF CURRENT BLACK CITY EMPLOYEES
SHOULD MATTER. WHEN THE CITY CONSIDERS HOW TO
RESPOND TO LONGSTANDING CONCERNS, I RESPECTFULLY ASK
THE BOARD AND SEAT AND CITY LEADERSHIP TO PURSUE SUSTAINED
AND MEASURABLE CITYWIDE ACTION AS IT CONSIDERS FILE NUMBER
SIX. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS
HODGES FOR CUTTING YOU OFF. >> WE ARE PROVIDING EVERYONE
THE SAME TWO MINUTES. >> NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON MR. PRESIDENT.
MEMBERS OF THE BOARD. >> IT'S NICE TO BE HERE TODAY.
I'M SPEAKING IN MY PRIVATE CAPACITY BUT I DO WANT TO
MENTION I'M AN ACTIVE DUTY ARMY OFFICER.
I'M TRANSGENDER. I'M COMBAT VETERAN.
I'M BEING FORCED OUT OF THE MILITARY NEXT MONTH FOR BEING
TRANSGENDER. AND THIS IS THE CITY I WANT TO
COME TO AND CONTINUE SERVING THE PUBLIC WHEN I COME HERE
AND BE A COP IN THE ARMY. I WANT TO DO IT HERE.
BUT HOUSING AND PRICES MAY STOP ME FROM STAYING IN THE CITY.
UNFORTUNATELY, I KNOW THAT THERE'S BEEN A LOT OF TALK
TODAY ABOUT REDUCING HOUSING PRICES AND THAT'S GREAT.
>> THAT'S ADMIRABLE. THERE'S A LOT OF CROSS PURPOSE
GOING ON TOO. >> THERE'S MEASURES IN THE
COUNTY 12 ORDINANCES PROPOSED ABOUT NEW LANDMARK DESIGNATIONS
AND A 120 DAY LANDMARK DESIGNATION EXTENSION THAT I
IMAGINE WOULD BE APPROVED BY UNANIMOUS CONSENT.
>> AND THERE'S ORDINANCE GOING THROUGH THE COMMITTEE RIGHT NOW
TO REFORM THE PROCESS AND MAKE IT SIMPLER.
>> AND THAT'S GREAT. HOWEVER, AS IF HERITAGE EXPECTS
FOR THAT PROCESS AND THAT ORDINANCE AS IT IS NOW TO
DOUBLE THE NUMBER OF LANDMARKS IN SAN FRANCISCO BY 2030
AND LANDMARKS WHICH ARE LAUDABLE AND ADMIRABLE CAN
REDUCE DEVELOPMENT. SIX MONTHS A YEAR AFTER TWO
AND A HALF YEARS LONG IS WHEN I FOUND.
>> SO AS A AS YOU GO FORWARD CONSIDERING LANDMARKS
AND CONSIDERING PROCESSES TO AMEND AND IMPROVE THAT PROCESS
,PLEASE KEEP IN MIND THE HOUSING PURPOSE BECAUSE DURING
EVERYTHING THAT YOU CAN TO IMPROVE HOUSING BY MAKING
HOUSING HARDER TO DEVELOP IS COUNTERPRODUCTIVE.
AND I ALSO WANT TO SAY THANK YOU TO SUPERVISOR MAILMAN FOR
PAYING ATTENTION AS I SPOKE. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. NEXT SPEAKER.
YEAH. >> HI, I'M I'M SORRY.
I'M FELICIA RAINEY, LITTLE SISTER.
>> MM HMM. I I REALLY DON'T KNOW WHAT TO
SAY, HONESTLY. >> NOT AT YOU GOT TO GO BACK.
>> BUT MY SISTER, SHE WAS MY SISTER.
SHE WAS A MOTHER. SHE WAS AUNTIE.
>> THAT'S HER ONLY NEPHEW RIGHT THERE.
OH, I DON'T KNOW. SHE YEAH, IT'S A HI.
GOOD EVENING, EVERYONE. MY NAME IS DOMINIQUE BROOKS
AND FELICIA OPIE WAS MY BEST FRIEND.
>> JUST OUR SISTER SAID. WE HONESTLY DON'T KNOW WHAT TO
SAY. IT WAS TRAGIC LOSING SOMEONE
IN SO CLOSE OF AGE AS I AM. >> UM, JUST A SHOCKER.
I WANT TO THANK YOU GUYS FOR TAKING THE TIME TO GIVE HER THE
MOMENT OF SILENCE AND ACTUALLY, YOU KNOW, APPRECIATE AND SHOW
HER HERE ON YOU GUYS AGENDA TODAY.
>> IT JUST SHOWS US A LOT SHOWS US THAT YOU GUYS ACTUALLY SEEN
THE PERSON OPIE WAS IF OPIE CAME TO HER ROOM SHE BRIGHTENED
UP A ROOM. >> I MEAN OPIE HAS BEEN FRIENDS
SINCE BABIES LITERALLY SINCE MY LITTLE GITS I STAYED IN MAUI.
>> IT WAS ALWAYS ME HER, YOU KNOW, EVERY TIME WE WOULD GO
OUT IT WAS ALWAYS NEAR HER. IT WAS NEVER NOBODY ELSE BUT ME
AND MY BEST FRIEND. RIGHT NOW I REALLY DON'T HAVE A
LOT TO SAY BUT TO SAY THANK YOU UM I DID WANT TO BRING
SOMETHING TO THE ATTENTION. >> BACK IN 2019 MY BEST FRIEND
DID COME AND SHE WAS ONE OF THE SPECIALISTS.
I TRULY APPRECIATE YOU GUYS FOR TALKING ABOUT HER SPEAKING THE
GREAT WORDS BUT I KNOW SHE WAS PROMISED A LOT OF THINGS THAT I
FEEL LIKE THAT DIDN'T HAPPEN WHEN SHE WAS HERE.
SHE FOUGHT FOR THE CLOSURE OF JUVENILE HALL.
I KNOW SHE WAS PROMISED THAT CLOSURE OF JUVENILE HALL
AND JUVENILE HALL. I STILL HERE TO THIS DAY.
SO I JUST FEEL LIKE, YOU KNOW, MAYBE ONE DAY WE COULD COME
BACK AGAIN AND YOU KNOW, KIND OF BASICALLY BE HER VOICE AGAIN
AND SEE IF WE CAN BRING THAT BACK AGAIN BECAUSE I JUST FEEL
LIKE, YOU KNOW, SHE FOUGHT FOR EVERYBODY, RIGHT?
>> SHE GOT ON THAT STAND AND TALK AND WAS VOICES THAT
PEOPLE BECAUSE THE SYSTEM IS MESSED UP IS A MESSED UP SYSTEM
YOU KNOW AND I JUST FEEL LIKE SOMETHING NEEDS TO BE DONE
ESPECIALLY NOW THAT SHE'S NOT HERE.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS .
YOU AGAIN APOLOGIES FOR CUTTING YOU OFF OR PROVIDING EVERYONE'S
OF THE SAME TWO MINUTES. >> NEXT SPEAKER.
>> HI I'M LINEARITY. I'M FELICIA'S OLDER COUSIN
AND SHE'S OLDER COUSIN. I WANT TO SAY THANK YOU GUYS
FOR, YOU KNOW, APPRECIATING MY COUSIN.
IT'S KIND OF WHERE WE ARE JUST REALLY NO WORDS FOR IT BECAUSE
UNDER THE CIRCUMSTANCES YEAH BUT I'M GONNA SAY THANK YOU
GUYS FOR SUPPORTING MY COUSIN AND I WANT TO LET YOU KNOW LIKE
WE LOVE HER AND WE'RE HERE FOR HER AND YEAH.
THANK YOU GUYS. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NEXT SPEAKER HELLO, MY NAME IS KAMARI.
>> I'M A COMMUNITY ORGANIZER. I WANT YOUNG WOMAN'S FREEDOM
CENTER. I'M HERE FOR TO SUPPORT M.S.
AND ALL OF HER FAMILY AND I JUST I WANT TO HONOR O.P.
AND THANK YOU GUYS FOR SPEAKING HER WORD IS HERE ANY THANK YOU
FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> NEXT SPEAKER HI, MY NAME IS
DALE WASHINGTON. I'M ALSO A COMMUNITY ORGANIZER
AT THE YOUNG WOMEN'S FREEDOM CENTER HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO,
CALIFORNIA. AND I'M ALSO HERE ON THE BEHALF
OF EMCEE TO HELP HER SUPPORT HER IN HER LOSS THE PURSES
THEIR OPI. >> I ALSO JUST WANT TO SAY
THANK YOU AS WELL FOR TO GIVE US THIS OPPORTUNITY FOR US TO
SPEAK OUT LOUD AND TO HAVE THE YOUNG WOMEN'S FREEDOM CENTER AS
WELL AND THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NEXT SPEAKER. >> HI, I'M JULIA ARROYO AND I'M
THE EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF THE YOUNG WOMEN'S FREEDOM CENTER.
>> O.P. O.P. REPRESENTS A LOT OF US A LOT OF GIRLS THAT GROW
UP IN SAN FRANCISCO, ESPECIALLY IN THE DISTRICT IN AND I'M ALSO
A RESIDENT OF DISTRICT TEN MYSELF AND I GREW UP IN MY ONE
OF MY FIRST EXPERIENCES WAS THE BEING IN JUVENILE HALL AT 13
YEARS OLD YOU KNOW, AND OPIE DID SOMETHING VERY BRAVE.
SHE EDUCATED US ABOUT WHAT SHE WAS EXPERIENCING AND SHE GAVE
US THE ACTUALLY THE PRIVILEGE TO HAVE A LITTLE BIT OF
KNOWLEDGE OF LIKE ACTUALLY WHAT THAT EXPERIENCE IS LIKE.
SO THEN WE CAN UNDERSTAND WHEN YOU SIT IN THE SEATS THAT
YOU'RE SITTING IN HOW SOME OF THE DECISIONS THAT YOU MAKE
TODAY CAN IMPACT ACTUALLY YOUNG PEOPLE GROWING UP IN SAN
FRANCISCO IT'S SO HARD TO GROW UP HERE.
I SIT DOWN WITH YOUNG PEOPLE ALL THE TIME THAT ARE LIKE I
DON'T FEEL WELCOME HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
I DON'T FEEL WELCOME. I FEEL LIKE I HAVE TO LEAVE
IN ORDER TO GET HOUSING, IN ORDER TO GET RESOURCES.
THEY'RE NOT GETTING THE RESOURCES THAT THEY NEED SO
THEY CAN THRIVE AND BE ABLE TO BECOME THE BUSINESS OWNERS OR
GO TO COLLEGE AND ALL OF THOSE THINGS THEY'RE THINKING ABOUT
THE THE DAY TO DAY THINGS TO BE ABLE TO GET THROUGH AND TO BE
ABLE TO SURVIVE THROUGH THIS AND WE JUST WE NEED TO DO
BETTER. WE NEED TO DO MUCH BETTER.
>> AND OPIE WAS A JUST A POWERFUL YOUNG PERSON.
YOU KNOW, HER WHOLE FAMILY GREW UP HERE AND IT IS THE
RESPONSIBILITY OF ALL OF US ALL OF US WHEN ONE OF OUR YOUNG
PEOPLE ARE STRUGGLING, IT'S ALL OF OUR RESPONSIBILITY TO BE
ABLE TO CREATE SOLUTIONS FOR THEM TO BE ABLE TO HAVE BETTER
LIVES. >> AND THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR
SOME OF WHAT'S IN FOR BEING ABLE TO MEMORIALIZE HER
AND BRING HER NAME UP. SHE WAS A VERY IMPORTANT PERSON
TO MANY PEOPLE. I SAT AND THESE YOUNG GIRLS
ORGANIZED BEAUTIFULLY THE FUNERAL, THE RESOURCE IS WHEN
PEOPLE SAID THERE'S NO RESOURCES, THERE'S NO RESOURCES
TO BURY HER AND THEY ALL THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS, ALL OF
THEM. AND WHEN THEY HAVE TO
EXPERIENCE THAT THEY THE NEXT SPEAKER IS SO THESE ARE THE
SUPERVISORS AND THE GENERAL PUBLIC.
GOOD AFTERNOON EVERYBODY. IF YOU REMEMBER LIKE TWO WEEKS
AGO I WAS OVER HERE, I CAME OVER HERE AND I TOLD YOU I WAS
HERE TO CREATE THIS AWARENESS ABOUT A CASE THEY HAVE WITH THE
POLICE. WHY MY HEAD TODAY AGAIN THIS IS
THE SECOND TIME TO REMIND YOU GUYS BECAUSE YOU GUYS HAVE BEEN
ELECTED AND THE SECURITY AND THE SAFETY OF THE PEOPLE OF
THE RESIDENTS OF SAN FRANCISCO LIES IN YOUR HANDS.
YOU GUYS HAVE THE POLICE CHIEF AND THE THE THE POLICE
COMMISSIONERS AND THE WHOEVER I SEE WHOEVER IS IN CHARGE OF THE
INVESTIGATIONS OF THE POLICE, YOU GUYS HAVE THEM AT YOUR BECK
AND CALL. >> SO I'M HERE AS THE SECOND
TIME TO COME OVER HE HAS A RUMOR THAT DAY NUMBER TWO TO
KIND OF COMPEL YOU GUYS TO TRY WITH YOUR BEST TALK TO THE
POLICE CHIEF. SO AT THE END OF THE DAY MY
CASE CAN BE INVESTIGATED BECAUSE I KNOW THE POLICE FOR
MONTHS LIKE I SAID THE LAST TIME I CAME OVER HERE AND THE
POLICE DID NOTHING ABOUT MY CASE AND THIS IS A PENDING CASE
I'VE BEEN ADDRESSED TO MY HAND FOR THE FOR THE PAST FOUR YEARS
OF YOU KNOW, MY CONTROL A REASSESSMENT ELECTRONIC
STALKING AND ELECTRONIC TORTURE AS WELL.
THESE ARE KIND OF THEM. HE SAID THEY SHOULD NOT CALL
IN A CITY LIKE SAN FRANCISCO FOR CRYING OUT LOUD.
THIS IS ONE OF THE MOST ADVANCED CITY IN AMERICA AND IF
YOU HAVE THE CASE OF THE POLICE AND THERE'S A CRIMINAL ELEMENT
AND THEY'RE NOT INVESTIGATING AND WHEN THEY CALL THEM THEY
DIDN'T TELL ME THE REASON WHY THEY DIDN'T INVESTIGATE THE
CASE AND IS A PENDING CASE FOR YEARS.
SO YOU GUYS LET ME REMIND YOU OF THE CASE ONE MORE TIME.
THE CASE NUMBER IS 260. YOU GUYS ARE NO RESIDENT IN OUR
POLICE. COULD YOU WRITE IT DOWN?
260242515. I'M GOING TO REPEAT THAT ONE
MORE TIME 260242515. HE'S A CASE THAT HAS TO DO WITH
THE CALIFORNIA PENAL CODE 6646.9 A LETTER AND STALKING
YOUR MOM. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
THANK YOU VERY MUCH. >> NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE.
PRESIDENT MAN OPEN SUPERVISORS. >> MY NAME IS RICHARD SD
PETERSON. I REALLY DON'T HAVE MUCH TO
TALK ABOUT TODAY. I THINK PRETTY MUCH IT'S BEEN
COVERED AT LEAST AS FAR AS ARTIFICIAL INTELLIGENCE.
I COULD TALK ABOUT PARCEL TAXES YOU KNOW THAT'S RELATED TO MUNI
WHEN WILLIE BROWN AND AS MILLENNIUM TOWER PAYS THE SAME
AS I DO IN MY ONE STORY 25 BY 24 FIVE FOOT COTTAGE I'LL BE
SATISFIED BUILDING CODE WELL I HOPE THAT TIPPING POINT PROGRAM
THAT IS ADOPTED BY THE CITY EVEN WITH RAILS I GUESS PUT ON
IT I HOPE THAT WORKS BUT THAT WAS THE MAYOR'S THE SPECIAL
PROGRAM THAT HE CREATED WITH HIS PROSE OR HIS PROSE CREATED
FOR HIM FOR TIPPING POINTS FREE SPEECH.
I THINK WE'VE COVERED THAT TODAY RACISM I THINK WE COVERED
THAT TODAY PUBLIC BANK I THINK THAT WE REALLY SHOULD MOVE
TOWARD A PUBLIC BANK BUT MAY I SUGGEST THAT IT BE CAPITALIST
ORIENTED AND NOT SOCIALIST ORIENTED AND HOUSING?
I MUST SAY THAT STILL AFTER EIGHT YEARS WITH PLANS IN THE
CITY HALL A HOUSE THAT I PROPOSED TO BUILD ON AN EMPTY
LOT STILL HAS NOT BEEN ENTITLED.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NEXT SPEAKER MR. PRESIDENT, MADAM SECRETARY, UH, I'VE BEEN
WATCHING THAT I FILLED OUT AS WELL.
IT SEEMS TO ME THAT THESE THINGS ARE VERY CAPITAL
INTENSIVE. THE ONE SINGLE FACILITY IS MANY
BILLIONS OF DOLLARS AND IT MAY HAVE AS MANY AS 30 OR 40
PERMANENT EMPLOYEES. THAT'S SOMETHING LIKE AT LEAST
$100 MILLION PER EMPLOYEE. NOW MOST JOBS AROUND HERE THEY
RUN ANYWHERE FROM $100,000 IN CAPITAL COSTS TO 2 OR
$300,000. BOARD OF SUPERVISORS, FOR
EXAMPLE, THE MAJOR CAPITAL COSTS IN THE BUILDING HERE
AND ALSO THE BUILD OUT AND OTHER THINGS.
BUT IT'S THAT FOR THE FOR THE THESE DATA CENTERS IT'S $100
MILLION PER EMPLOYEE. >> YOU WOULD HAVE TO BE AN
ASTRONAUT IN THE SPACE PROGRAM GOING AROUND THE MOON TO HAVE A
JOB THAT CONSUMES THAT MUCH CAPITAL COSTS.
>> THE OTHER SIDE OF IT IS OF COURSE THE ENERGY.
IT'S VERY ENERGY INTENSIVE FOR EVERY EVERY WORKER AND ONCE
AGAIN YOU WOULD HAVE TO BE IN THE SPACE PROGRAM TRUCK
DRIVERS DRIVING INTERSTATE TRUCK DRIVERS CONSUME LESS
ENERGY PER JOB THEN THAT THEN THEN DATA CENTER WORKERS.
>> I DON'T SEE HOW IT ADDS UP. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
ARE THERE ANY OTHER INDIVIDUALS WHO WOULD LIKE TO PROVIDE
PUBLIC COMMENT? SEEING NONE WE WILL GO TO THE
REMOTE CALL IN LINE WE HAVE BILLY CHECKING TO SEE IF WE
HAVE ANY CALLERS AND THERE ARE NO CALLERS.
>> MR. PRESIDENT. ALL RIGHT.
PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW CLOSED. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ME
FOR ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE AGENDA WITHOUT
COMMITTEE REFERENCE AGENDA ITEMS 51 THROUGH 59 TOGETHER
YES ITEMS 51 THROUGH 59 WERE INTRODUCED FOR ADOPTION WITHOUT
COMMITTEE REFERENCE. A UNANIMOUS VOTE IS REQUIRED
FOR ADOPTION OF A RESOLUTION FIRST APPEARANCE ANY SUPERVISOR
MAY REQUIRE RESOLUTION FIRST APPEARANCE TO GO TO COMMITTEE.
>> SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANK YOU PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN I'D LIKE TO
FOR ITEM 52. SUPERVISOR MELGAR 58 MADAM
CLERK COULD YOU CALL THE ROLL ON THE ITEMS OTHER THAN 52
AND 50 EIGHT? >> YES ON THE REMAINING BALANCE
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN ABSENT SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN MANDOLIN I
SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EITHER NICE WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED AND THE MOTION IS APPROVED PLEASE CALL
ITEM 52. >> ITEM 52 IS A RESOLUTION TO
DECLARE SATURDAY, SEPTEMBER 19TH, 2026 THROUGH SUNDAY
SEPTEMBER 20TH, 2026 AS MUNI HERITAGE WEEKEND IN THE CITY
AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO IN RECOGNITION OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO MUNICIPAL RAILWAY'S ENDURING LEGACY CULTURAL
SIGNIFICANCE AND HISTORICAL CONTRIBUTIONS TO THE CITY'S
IDENTITY AND TRANSPORTATION. >> SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANK YOU
PRESIDENT MELBOURNE COLLEAGUES I AM PROUD TO OFFER THIS
RECOGNITION FOR THIS COMING WEEKEND AS MUNI HERITAGE
WEEKEND IN SAN FRANCISCO FOR 113 YEARS MUNI HAS CONNECTED
GENERATION OF SAN FRANCISCANS TO THEIR JOBS, SCHOOLS,
NEIGHBORHOODS AND TO ONE ANOTHER AS THE FIRST PUBLICLY
OWNED TRANSIT SYSTEM IN A MAJOR AMERICAN CITY, MUNI IS ALSO AN
ENDURING EXPRESSION OF SAN FRANCISCO'S BELIEF THAT
RELIABLE PUBLIC TRANSPORTATION IS AN ESSENTIAL PUBLIC GOOD
MUNI HERITAGE WEEKEND BRINGS THAT HISTORY TO LIFE THROUGH
CABLE CARS, STREETCARS AND BUSSES THAT HAVE BECOME
ICONS OF OUR CITY. IT ALSO HONORS THE GENERATIONS
OF OPERATORS, MECHANICS, ENGINEERS, STATION AGENTS,
CLEANERS, DISPATCHERS, ADVOCATES AND RIDERS WHO BUILT
AND SUSTAIN THIS SYSTEM AND THE S.F. MTA AND MARKET STREET
RAILWAY EMPLOYEES WHO PRESERVE THAT LEGACY TODAY AND EVERY DAY
THIS RECOGNITION COMES AT A CRITICAL TIME THIS YEAR THE FTA
FACES A $307 MILLION BUDGET SHORTFALL SHORTFALL ALL THE
LARGEST IN ITS HISTORY. WITHOUT ADDITIONAL FUNDING MUNI
COULD FACE SIGNIFICANT SERVICE REDUCTIONS AS WE CELEBRATE
MUNI'S LEGACY WE ALSO RECOGNIZE THE IMPORTANCE OF PROTECTING
ITS FUTURE. HONORING MUNI MEANS INVESTING
IN ITS FUTURE AND WITH THIS RESOLUTION WE HONOR THE PEOPLE
WHO BUILT MUNI SUPPORT THE PEOPLE WHO ARE RUNNING IT TODAY
AND REAFFIRM OUR COMMITMENT TO THIS ESSENTIAL PUBLIC SERVICE
OF THE SAN FRANCISCANS CAN CONTINUE TO DEPEND ON IT.
>> TOMORROW MY OFFICE INTRODUCED THIS RESOLUTION
RECOGNIZING MUNI HERITAGE LAST YEAR AND I'M PLEASED TO
CONTINUE THAT TRADITION AS WE CELEBRATE MUNI'S REMARKABLE
HISTORY WE SHOULD RECOMMIT OURSELVES TO A FUTURE WHERE
PUBLIC TRANSIT REMAINS SAFE, RELIABLE, ACCESSIBLE
AND CENTRAL TO THE LIFE OF OUR CITY.
I'D LIKE TO THANK OUR DISTRICT SIX INTERN ZARA ZAIDI WHOM WE
HEARD FROM A SHORT TIME AGO WHO AUTHORED THIS RESOLUTION AS
MANY AS MY AS WELL AS MY REMARKS AND FOR ALL THE
EXCELLENT WORK SHE DOES IN OUR OFFICE.
I'D ALSO LIKE TO THANK MY CO SPONSORS SUPERVISORS MAHMOOD
CHERYL SADR, WONG MANDELBAUM AND FIELDER CHEN AND CHEN AND I
HOPE YOU'LL ALL JOIN THE CELEBRATIONS THIS WEEKEND ON
SATURDAY AND SUNDAY FROM 10 TO 4 P.M. AT THE SAN FRANCISCO
RAILWAY MUSEUM ADMISSION AND STUART STREETS WHICH IS
ALMOST BUT NOT QUITE IN DISTRICT SIX THE CELEBRATION
WILL FEATURE FREE HISTORIC VEHICLE RIDES A PROMENADE OF
HISTORIC BUSSES ACTIVITIES THE MUNI DIARIES A PHOTO WALKING
TOUR AND OPPORTUNITIES TO ENGAGE WITH COMMUNITY PARTNERS.
THANK YOU COLLEAGUES FOR YOUR SUPPORT AND FOR LEADING OUR
CITY IN CELEBRATING MUNI'S HERITAGE.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. >> MADAME CLERK, PLEASE CALL
ITEM 58. >> ITEM 58 IS A RESOLUTION TO
DECLARE SEPTEMBER 15TH THROUGH OCTOBER 15TH TWO 2026 IS LATIN
HERITAGE MONTH IN THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO TO
HONOR AND TO CELEBRATE THE CONTRIBUTIONS OF THE LATIN
COMMUNITY SUPERVISOR MELGAR THANK YOU PRESIDENT HAPPY LATIN
HERITAGE MONTH COLLEAGUES. I AM GRATEFUL TO BE BRINGING
THIS RESOLUTION FORWARD WITH MY COLLEAGUE SUPERVISOR FIELDER
AND CO SPONSORS SUPERVISOR MANDELL MEN CHEN MAHMOOD
AND CHAN. >> TODAY IS PARTICULARLY
SPECIAL TO ME. >> IT IS INDEPENDENCE DAY FOR
AL-SALEH THEODORE IT IS DIFFERENT THAN INDEPENDENCE DAY
IN MEXICO AND IT IS ALSO THE INDEPENDENCE DAY OF COSTA RICA.
WHAT THEY MAY ALLOW UNDER ARREST IN NICARAGUA AT THIS
THIS MONTH SERVES AS A REMINDER TO HONOR THE LEGACIES OF
RESISTANCE AND RESILIENCE THAT CONNECTS US IN THE LATIN
AMERICAN AND DIASPORA IN OUR CONTINUED FIGHT FOR JUSTICE,
DIGNITY AND THE HOPE FOR A BETTER TOMORROW.
IT IS PERSONAL TO ME MY MATERNAL GRANDPA GREAT
GRANDPARENTS MOVED TO SAN FRANCISCO IN 1930 TWO AND LIVED
ON HAIGHT STREET WITH THEIR FIVE SONS.
>> THEY WORKED AT A CHICKEN PROCESSING PLANT IN THE MISSION
AND SEND MONEY BACK HOME SO THAT THEY COULD RETIRE AND GO
BACK TO EL SALVADOR. AND LIKE MY PEOPLE, PEOPLE FROM
CENTRAL AMERICA HAVE COME BACK AND FORTH TO SAN FRANCISCO
AND ADD IT TO THE WONDERFUL FABRIC OF OUR CITY WE HELPED
BUILD IT. >> SO I AM PROUD OF THE
DIVERSITY OF SAN FRANCISCO. I AM PROUD OF MY CENTRAL
AMERICAN HERITAGE OF OUR LATINO FLAVOR IN SAN FRANCISCO OF
HAVING BEEN ABLE TO MAKE MISSION BURRITOS AND THE
MISSION HOT DOGS ALL OF THESE THINGS THAT MAKE UP THE
WONDERFUL LIFE THAT WE HAVE HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO AND THE
CONTRIBUTION OF CENTRAL AMERICANS AND LATINOS INTO OUR
CITY IN DURING A TIME WHEN OUR FEDERAL ADMINISTRATION IS
VIABLY PERSECUTING IMMIGRANTS AND MAKING LIFE DIFFICULT
SEPARATING FAMILIES AND OPPRESSING PEOPLE, IT IS
REALLY IMPORTANT THAT WE CELEBRATE THE JOY OF DIVERSITY
OF BEING TOGETHER AND THE CONTRIBUTIONS OF OUR LATIN
NEIGHBORS. >> THANK YOU VERY MUCH
COLLEAGUES, FOR YOUR SUPPORT. I HOPE YOU WILL ALL JOIN THE
CITY HALL CELEBRATION ON THURSDAY, OCTOBER 1ST AT THE
ROTUNDA. >> THANK YOU SUPERVISOR WALTON
THE LIBRARY AND OF COURSE THIS IS SUPERVISOR FIELDER.
>> I JUST WANTED TO THANK SUPERVISOR MELGAR FOR LEADING
THIS RESOLUTION AND AS YOU SAID IT BEST AS A FEDERAL
ADMINISTRATION CONTINUES ITS ATTACKS ON IMMIGRANT
COMMUNITIES, IT'S IMPORTANT TO CONTINUE CELEBRATING THE
AMAZING COMMUNITY THAT WE HAVE IN SAN FRANCISCO AMONG THE
LATINO COMMUNITY. >> THANK YOU.
ALL RIGHT. WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM SAME
HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS
ADOPTED. MADAM CLERK, DO WE HAVE ANY
IMPERATIVE AGENDA ITEMS? >> NO, WE DO NOT HAVE ANY
IMPERATIVE AGENDA ITEMS TODAY. COULD YOU PLEASE READ THE
IN MEMORIAM? >> YES.
TODAY'S MEETING WILL BE ADJOURNED IN MEMORY OF THE
FOLLOWING BELOVED INDIVIDUALS ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR WALTON
FOR THE LATE MS. FELICIA FREENEY AND ON BEHALF OF SUPER
PRESIDENT MANDOLIN FOR THE LATE MR. JEREMIAH HALSEY AND ON
BEHALF OF PRESIDENT MANDOLIN FOR THE LATE MR. THOMAS TOM
FRANKEL AND FOR THE LATE BY MR. PRESIDENT AND THE ENTIRE BOARD
FOR THE LATE MRS. MAILING LOW LOW SORRY I THINK THAT BRINGS
US TO THE END OF OUR AGENDA, MADAM CLERK DO WE HAVE ANY
FURTHER BUSINESS BEFORE US TODAY?
THAT CONCLUDES OUR BUSINESS FOR TODAY.
>> THEN WE ARE ADJOURNED